Kimi's latest K three is buzzing summed up in three words,
big, good, and open source!
But now, each large language model bests the last
and tomorrow, they get even bigger!
So what are they competing over, exactly?
Well, it boils down to three things,
first, the model’s parameter count
that is the most literal meaning of large
in large language model .
Today, open source model shave
started joining the one T parameter race,
including Meituan's LongCat, DeepSeek, and Kimi,
a feat once solely the domain of closed source models.
The second battleground is context length—back then,
we’d often test this by seeing
if a single chat
could read through the whole of “The Three Body Problem”.
For cutting edge large language models,
a million token context length has swiftly gone
from a novel gimmick to a standard feature.
Because even a regular person
can spawn tons of long agent
tasks—beyond just chatting on a webpage.
The third battleground is modal support.
Supporting more modalities beyond text
greatly impacts the user experience.
For instance, we always ask: when will DeepSeek support images?
That speaks to the hunger for multimodal capabilities,
and one reason Gemini blew up back then
was the debut of its native multimodal feature.
See? The current three point five Flash supports
up to five modalities,
while this new K three
brings all three of those key ones together!
two point eight T
params—the largest
open source model yet—plus a million token context
length AND multimodal support!
Plus, what piqued my curiosity is that,
as an open source model,
it ranked just behind GPT five point six and Fable five
in many key benchmark tests!
and some even snagged number one!
Of course, this bigness is just on the surface,
what truly matters are the technologies
behind the scenes that support it
and today, I will break it all down for you!
First, let us see what issues a high parameter count brings.
This is the bedrock of large language model s:
the Transformer architecture;
and within it, the part with the most parameters
are these Feed Forward Network layers,
which are just simple, multi layer neural networks.
except that the number of neurons
and thus, parameters is huge.
So, the fix is quite simple,
break it down into many smaller neural networks.
Then, for each new token,
a trained routing layer
directs it to one of those smaller neural networks.
This way, the total parameter count stays the same,
but for each token,
far fewer parameters are actually used in computation.
That is the classic MO E Mixture of Experts architecture ,
DeepSeek even put their own spin on it ,
adding  shared experts , dubbed DeepSeek MO E .
Kimi this time also uses an M O E architecture,
eight hundred and ninety six experts, only
sixteen activated at a time.
More precisely, its Latent Mo E scheme
optimizes compute efficiency
via dimension reduction in the expert routing layer.
Anyway, just recall this,
anything with latent prepended shares
one goal, to first shrink then expand dimensions.
so you can compute in this low d space to boost efficiency.
The latent in M L A works the same way.
Okay! So, M O E eases computational strain
by cutting down on parameters during inference.
But, the total parameter count stays the same,
and during training, all those params still get trained up.
But as models grow larger,
the Transformer layers get very deep,
which in turn makes the training process
prone to instability.
For these basic deep learning principles,
see my prior video, Understand A I in One Hour.
Of course, a classic structure, Residual Connection,
can fix this issue quite well.
So, outside each layer’s transformation,
you add an extra link
and just mindlessly tack on the prior value—super simple!
But there’s a snag: it’s too rigid.
For instance, by the time info from A one reaches A four,
not much is left;
so, ByteDance came up with a new scheme called HC.
Simply put, they copy A one multiple times,
and what gets passed on is not just added on,
but rather multiplied by a learnable matrix.
This way, the info passed along
stands a better chance of being retained.
But the snag is, if this learning matrix has no constraints,
its repeated products could spiral out of control again.
So, DeepSeek's m H C
adds fluidity constraints to these learning matrices.
Simply put, it keeps these matrices,
no matter how they are multiplied,
within a controllable range
thus, an enhancement to H C.
But Kimi chose a different path.
In fact, from a broader view,
no matter how these methods get optimized,
they all add to the Residual Stream
layer by layer, from bottom to top.
whereas Kimi, right within the Residual Stream,
uses the attention mechanism
to perform a weighted sum of prior residuals.
to ensure each layer’s residual info
gets a chance to be noticed.
This is Kimi’s Attention Residuals—many big shots
reposted and liked it
back then,
sparking community chatter,
and I even made a video on it!
And this time, the Kimi K three model
puts that tech from that classic paper to use.
Nice! Another open source model with new tech to check out!
Okay! So, the issues stemming from vast parameters
computational load and training stability
are solved via the familiar M O E
and Kimi is own Attention Residuals.
So, what about the computation issues
stemming from that million token context?
Back to this Transformer architecture diagram—indeed,
the biggest issue with million token contexts
is that it balloons the computation for the Attention Layer.
since each token in the Attention Layer
must run an attention calculation
with every other token to yield a coefficient.
So, how do we cut down on this compute?
Simple! One way is to shrink the vector length,
for example, M Q A, G Q A, M L A, and so on.
But these still
fall under dense
attention—meaning, the number of vectors computed
stays the same;
only the vector length is reduced.
Then, of course, there’s another class
that cuts down on the number of vectors
computed—say, by fixing a computation window to select tokens.
or, via some method, sieve out a few Tokens,
not all of them.
Classic methods say, D S A, S W A C S, H C A, and so on
are termed sparse attention,
where the number of vectors grows sparse.
Then, there is the most potent class
that slashes computational complexity
straight from n squared down to n
this approach is called Linear Attention,
which includes these methods here.
So, K D A here stands for Kimi Delta Attention
an in house Linear Attention scheme from Kimi
that is also been used in this K three model.
Of course, this Linear Attention, in some ways,
reverts back to an RNN like method.
So, typically, every few layers,
a Linear Attention is used
and blended with the normal Attention Layer,
hence, it is called Hybrid Attention overall.
To sum up,
a large language model boils down to two key things,
the parameter count of its Feed Forward Network,
and the compute load of its Attention Layer.
And this time, K three uses the Latent MoE scheme
to sparsify the Feed Forward Network’s parameter count
and compress its length, too.
with K D A Linear Attention, greatly
cutting the Attention Layer's computation.
It also provides a strong case for the effectiveness
of the much debated Hybrid Attention Scheme.
then, they used their novel Attention Residuals
to ensure training stability.
I wager that many future open source efforts
will widely discuss and adopt these techniques.
So, I gave it a test myself
but using my prior model evaluation tool,
I ran into lots of server timeouts.
Perhaps this K three release broke out of its niche
so much that it crashed the servers
which counts as a worthy finding,
I would say!
As for the exact scores,
let us re test in a few days once server strain eases up.
Of course, what matters more is its agent capabilities
and in public tests, K three's performance was quite stellar.
Well, as it happens,
I’ve been working on automating agent evaluations lately,
so let’s give it a shot.
My plan is quite simple,
I create a directory like this,
and for each one, I pop in a task dot m d file
and jot down its task requirements.
Then, in the top level root dir,
have the agent tackle all tasks in each subdir, one by one.
So, my tasks comprise these,
which not only tests the model’s basic agent skills,
but also its overall planning prowess.
Plus, it is comprehensive and simple to test.
Plus, these tasks are all real ones
I face day to day—problems
that agents back then struggled mightily to solve.
First off, kudos to K three
it clearly used four separate sub agents in parallel
to get the job done,
and the output was super clear and straightforward.
In a past video of mine,
I praised Kimi Code’s ease of use it does look very slick!
And what is cool here is, an accident happened
that helped me test out some of its other skills.
So, since I’m running this task from my hotel,
and I have to head off to the World
Artificial Intelligence Conference soon,
So, I left the hotel early,
thus its net cut out.
So, once the net cut out, its fourth task went unfinished.
Once I got back to my hotel, I reconnected the net.
So, this was a perfect test to see if, midway through a task,
should the network cut out,
could it pick back up and finish the job properly.
At that point, I thought,
Oh man, was this recording all for naught?
But it pulled through
and ultimately completed all the tasks!
So, let us check out the results.
First, the text to audio, image to audio, and video workflow.
All A P I calls worked, and the page was intuitive.
Plus, kudos here: for video,
when I used Opus four point eight
before, the polling logic had flaws,
but K three nailed it this time.
Second, the large language model evaluation—this project required a full front end revamp, and yes, you can open it with a double click, and the logic is sound.
The review runs fine, and the styling is unchanged.
Third, three D file format
conversion—this requires pinpointing
where the Blender app sits on my PC
and knowing how to use its command line syntax.
So let us test this output just drag it straight into P P T,
and that works fine, too.
Fourth: adding features to spaghetti code!
This is that spaghetti code canvas app
I whipped up ages ago with some shoddy tokens—though,
gotta say, it IS flawed.
The new text addition feature click it, and zip happens!
Of course, this lets us test its problem fixing skills,
so let us give it another shot at fixing this.
In the end, those issues were all fixed with ease!
And based on my experience using it these past few days,
K three’s benchmark scores this time around
really pack a punch.
Lastly, some personal thoughts,
training a super large model is not just a tech issue,
it is more about cost and risk.
A single training run might need thousands
upon thousands of GPU's and take months—
and if it crashes midway,
that’s pretty much money down the drain.
Plus, in this fiercely competitive large language model scene,
falling behind even for a moment—well, that’s a huge risk.
Of course, we should be wary
of over hyping our models’ abilities,
while also showing more patience and openness.
Understand that this process of training
a large language model —much like alchemy—involves many costs,
risks, and non technical factors to weigh.
Uh, here is hoping China’s large language model
can go even further down this path!
Go!