Let's continue our journey into NLP.
Today, we're going to look at the RNN architecture.
It allows the model to move beyond just understanding words,
to the point where it can understand entire sentences.
In the last video, we introduced the concept of embedding.
It can take discrete text labels
represented as numbers within a continuous vector space.
This makes them computable.
And on top of that, it also carries some semantic meaning.
So, words with similar meanings are closer to each other.
and also computable.
And just like that, the computer can understand words.
Now, a sentence is obviously made up of a bunch of words.
So, since the model can understand a single word,
So, does that mean it can understand the entire sentence?
But that's not actually the case.
Let's look at a few examples.
For example, take the sentences "I like watching this movie" and "I don't like watching this movie."
If we just look at it from the perspective of embedding technology,
These two sentences are very similar.
Their vector spaces are almost identical.
But the only difference is the addition of the word 'not'.
But the meaning they convey is completely different.
And then you have the difference between 'fighting the White Bone Spirit' and 'the White Bone Spirit fighting Sun Wukong'.
Their embeddings are actually identical.
The words themselves don't have that information.
are exactly the same.
However, because their order is different,
This completely changes the subject and the object.
Or take these two sentences: "Apple released a new product" and "I ate an apple."
They both use the word 'apple'.
But, in different contexts,
the meanings they convey are completely different.
For example, if we rely solely on embeddings,
we can't really understand a complete sentence.
It's not just about knowing which words are in a sentence.
We also need to know the order of these words.
and the context surrounding them.
Only then can we accurately understand the sentence.
So, you might be thinking, "Why not just use an FN?"
So, could we just use a neural network to solve this problem?
So first, let's take a look at what a feedforward neural network is.
I'm sure when you've all seen the Transformer architecture,
and at the end, there's also an FNN layer.
And the reason it's called a 'feed-forward' network is...
It's a type of network where information flows in one direction only.
Does the front give feedback to the back?
The data starts from the input layer,
passing through the hidden layers,
until it reaches the output layer.
and makes a prediction.
There are no recurrent connections within the network.
It just keeps moving in a single direction.
It doesn't loop back on itself and go through various cycles.
The MLP we learned about earlier is a classic example of an FNN.
But this kind of structure isn't really suitable for direct processing.
There are two main reasons why it's not suited for natural language sequences.
The first reason is that it can't model the dependencies between preceding and following words.
Take our natural language sentences, for example.
I'm going to the bank to deposit money.
The meaning of the word 'bank' can only be determined by looking at the context that comes before it.
There's a sequential relationship between them.
Now, with a traditional approach, if we were to just flatten these words,
and feed them into the network,
and feed it in all at once,
and get an output all at once.
In reality, they don't capture this sequential order.
the sequential order and dependencies between them.
Instead, they just treat the entire sequence as a single, fixed vector.
So, in this case, the architecture itself simply doesn't have that kind of mechanism.
So, it just can't understand the sequential relationships between these words.
And what's the other thing?
Variable-length sequences are difficult to align with its fixed input.
Now, we know that for the input to our neural network,
is actually a fixed one.
For instance, let's say we're talking about how many neurons we have in the first input layer.
This determines the length of the input I can accept.
But the thing is, for natural language sentences, their length is actually variable.
Different sentences have different lengths.
And of course, to force them to align,
So, when you want to use an FN to represent it,
The inputs have to be the same.
It's not that it's impossible, though.
What I can do is set a fixed length.
And for the parts that go over, I'll just truncate them.
And for the next input, what if it's too short?
I can just pad it to make up the difference.
This also forces the sequences to be aligned.
And just like that, it's ready for input.
But truncation means you lose information.
And if you pad it by filling in with empty spaces, you'll just introduce some noise.
This affects the model's learning.
This, in turn, makes the training process extremely difficult.
So, since these methods can't solve the problem,
So, what's the solution?
So basically, what RNN did was make some changes to the overall approach.
It didn't change the independent variables either.
I mean, the word vectors, they stay exactly as they were.
What it changes is how we read the sentence.
It's not like the old methods.
Instead, it's about combining the entire sentence into a single, fixed vector.
It reads the input sequentially, performing calculations layer by layer.
and then spit out a result.
So, how does it work?
From left to right.
one token at a time.
reading one token at a time.
When it reads the first word,
it can only determine a state based on the current input.
Then it moves on to the second word.
So, it reads the, uh...
The first thing it does is remember that word.
and create a vectorized representation of it.
Then, when it reads the second word,
and combines it with the state representation from the previous step.
and combine them.
And based on these two, it then reads the third word.
And it goes on, layer by layer.
until it's completely processed.
Let's look at a simple example.
For example, let's say it needs to process the natural language sequence "I love nature."
So, how does it read it?
So, first, it only reads this one token, 'I'.
This is what we call a time step.
Because, you know, it's a process that's completed in multiple steps.
So, T equals one.
So, after it's processed my input and formed an understanding,
and store it somewhere.
We call this the hidden state.
We'll call this H1.
So at this point, it knows the word is 'me'.
Then, the second word, 'I', is fed in as the next input.
So, when it's processing the 'I'...
It remembers that the previous word was 'my'.
So, it understands the word 'I' based on the context of 'my'.
So it combines these two to understand the meaning.
And just like that, it's remembered the sequence "I love."
So, when it gets to the next word, 'nature'...
and combine it with the words 'I love' and 'nature'.
and it kind of puts two and two together, you know?
and it understands the phrase 'I love nature'.
So, during this process,
In other words, with each step of the process,
When it reads in one,
it generates a hidden state.
Then, when it reads the second one,
it combines with the first hidden state.
to produce the second hidden state.
Then, it reads the third token.
and then combines it with the second hidden state.
to produce the third hidden state.
This process continues until it reads the end-of-sequence token.
the end of the sequence.
And that final result is all that matters.
to produce the final output.
So, that's the basic idea.
So, what exactly is this hidden state?
So, in the logical deduction we just went through,
It does give off a sense of memory, doesn't it?
Well, mathematically speaking, it's actually a vector.
represented by a vector with a fixed dimensionality.
and it calculates a set of floating-point numbers.
And this information is multidimensional.
It's not that
But it's not exactly the same as the embedding result either.
And it's not like each one of them corresponds to a single word.
Together, they reflect the overall picture.
This is the memory processing work I'm doing on your previous input.
And it gets updated with each step.
But its dimensionality doesn't change.
Let me express this mathematically.
So, for example, how is the hidden state at timestep T generated?
is a function of...
First, we have my input.
my XT,
So, step seven.
So, I take my input and the hidden state from the previous step,
and we perform a combined operation on them.
And that gives us the new hidden state for this step.
So, HT is the hidden state generated at step T.
And XT is the current input.
So, let's take the example again of the sentence, "I do not like this movie."
So, how does this process work?
First, at H0, the initial state could be all zeros.
Or of course, it could also be a set of parameters from the model's training.
Either way works.
So, when T is equal to one...
meaning there's no hidden state.
I just need to input "OK," and it gets me.
and puts it into the hidden state, H1.
So, what we're actually doing is computing the hidden state for this step.
And for the second step,
So, by the second step, it has already understood me.
Right?
So it combines me and my input, which becomes my hidden state, right?
It's about understanding me.
So, it just goes on and on, using the result from the previous step in this process.
Doesn't this feel familiar, especially if you're into programming?
This should feel pretty familiar.
Right?
This is actually kind of like recursion.
is the hidden state.
So basically, it represents, uh, the information from what I've read in before.
understanding of a sequence.
So, let's take a look at its entire cycle.
So, maybe if we go back one step from T to the seventh step, the input at that point...
So, at time step T minus one...
and that gives us HT minus one, which is this hidden state.
So, you can think of it as...
I combine my previous memory point with my current input,
to form my current memory point.
and then process the next input.
So, as you can see in the diagram, there are a lot of these RNN cells.
So, for each of these processing steps...
So, this whole process of processing the hidden state and the input...
And we call this an RNN cell.
They are all the same cell, you see.
It's just that it's used repeatedly at different points in time.
And this process, doesn't it look a lot like a loop?
So, if we were to represent this in pseudocode...
So, H0 is just the initialization.
So, I'll just loop through, calling the RNN cell to process each token in the sequence.
And with each processing step, we store that information in the hidden state.
So, I'll use a while loop for the current input,
as long as it's not the end of the sequence.
until it's a continuous end-of-sequence token.
So, what do I append to the current hidden state?
So, for this RNN function...
It takes the current input and the previous hidden state,
and append it.
and at T plus one, it processes the next step.
And you just keep repeating this loop.
And finally, let's say I'm ready to make an output.
I've learned everything there is to learn.
and then I can make the output, right?
I don't need to wait until the very last hidden state.
Once it's processed all the inputs,
I can just use that final hidden state,
and feed it into something called a task.
and place it outside the loop.
to make an overall prediction.
And with that, I can make a prediction for the entire sequence.
So, this is basically how an RNN works.
This is the most basic workflow.
Of course, we've also included the output for each step here.
That is, the prediction at each step.
But this step isn't always necessary, though.
This depends on the specific task.
Next, we'll cover the different types of tasks.
The timing of its output is different.
Take the example I have here, for instance.
none of the previous ones have it.
It only produces an output at the very last step.
and make the output after HT plus one.
So, after the entire loop is finished,
I only produce an output once.
But sometimes, I need to produce an output at every single step.
So, what we do is, within the loop, we make use of the current hidden state.
and just use that to make an output.
We'll see a practical example of this in just a moment.
From a local perspective,
So, let's take a look at what's happening inside an RNN.
So, what's happening inside the RNN...
So, what it does is, it takes the input and the hidden state from the previous step,
to produce a new hidden state.
So, XT is the word vector for the current token.
This is the new information from the current step.
And H subscript T minus one?
This is the vector representation of the context accumulated so far.
Okay, so for RNNs...
and combines them into a new hidden state.
And that completes one state update.
Then, when it's used in the next position,
it will then call upon it.
So, what's going on inside it?
So, we can see that when the input X comes in,
First off, it has a matrix parameter, which is WI.
So, it's really all just WX plus B, you know.
So, what exactly is this W?
This is the hidden state, H, that's specifically learned from X.
It will also be processed by a similar matrix.
But this is a separate set of parameters.
WHH, and then we multiply it with the previous hidden state.
So, after we multiply these two,
and then we do an addition.
And maybe it's because this part isn't actually shown in the demo.
And in this step, there might also be an addition operation.
And finally, a bias term is also added.
It's actually just like what's shown in this little formula right here.
So, it's WXH plus ST, which is WH plus HT minus one.
And finally, we add a ***.
which is basically its bias.
So after we add them up,
We might use tanh, or other functions like ReLU,
and other activation functions to introduce non-linearity.
And that gives us a new one.
And just like that, we get a new hidden state.
So, if at this step,
And that's what I pass on to the next timestep.
So, if at this current step, I need to produce an output,
Then I'm just performing the calculation for it.
and just let it generate the output.
This will involve a new set of weights.
So, depending on the specific task, you'll be training different parameters.
And G here represents its activation function.
Of course, this step is optional.
So, it's possible that the current RNN cell doesn't necessarily have to produce an output.
I just need to calculate the hidden state.
Sometimes, a hidden state is produced at every step.
But that doesn't mean an output is generated at every single step.
We'll look at specific tasks in a moment.
and it will all make sense.
So, before we get into the specific tasks,
So, let me explain a bit more.
Although it has multiple RNN cells stacked together,
Now, you might be thinking, 'Wow, how many parameters does that even have?'
But in reality, the number of its parameters isn't that large.
That's because each RNN cell is identical.
And when we say 'the same,' we mean that their parameters are identical.
It's a set of param-
Specifically, the weight parameters and the biases.
and biases.
They are not actually being updated during the training process.
In fact, they are also updated synchronously over and over again.
So, this approach has a few advantages.
First off, it works like this.
This decouples it from the sentence's length.
No matter how long or short the sentence is,
In fact, it's all a loop.
And the CEL parameter that's hanging there? It stays constant.
And every time I update, I'm updating all of them as well.
Let's take the weights within an RNN cell,
so that it can be understood from different perspectives.
no matter how long it is,
I can understand the entire sequence, and the number of parameters is manageable.
So, what this means is,
And it doesn't matter if your sentence has ten tokens,
or even 100 tokens, I can handle it all.
And that solves the problem.
Unlike the FNN, the feedforward neural network we just mentioned,
it's not very good at handling sequences of variable length.
Now, let's circle back to the issue of output that we just mentioned.
So, you have to generate a hidden state at every single step.
But that doesn't mean it has to produce an output every single time.
So, in an RNN architecture, when exactly do we produce an output?
This depends on the specific task it's designed for.
There are three common types.
The first type is called global classification.
For example, after reading a sentence,
I need to make a judgment call on it.
Is this sentence expressing a positive sentiment,
or a negative one.
Take movie reviews, for example.
Once I've finished analyzing it,
Is this a positive review or a negative one?
I need to process every single word the user says, from start to finish.
So, after all the hidden states are processed,
Finally, we add a classifier.
through a linear layer,
and then add a softmax layer to classify it.
All you have to do is determine if it's positive or negative.
This is the final output after reading the entire sequence.
And there's another type where you need an output at every single step.
For instance, when I'm trying to understand a word,
like when you're trying to understand the meaning of a word,
Let's say we want to do some part-of-speech analysis on it.
And for each sentence in between,
For instance, some sentences might have pronouns involved.
This token here is a verb.
The next one is an adverb.
and the one after that is a noun.
And I have to use the hidden state every single time.
to generate an output from the current hidden state.
And that's also a possibility.
But of course, there's actually a bit of a difference here.
Each time, it uses the current token.
and the new hidden state that is generated.
Next up is sequence generation.
Actually, when we use GPT to generate text today,
That's pretty much what it is.
So, at each step, I have to base my decision on all the input I've received so far.
to predict the next word.
It's like how GPT is constantly predicting the next token, right?
So, you could say that I, too, am a gift from you.
So, for every single one I read in,
I'll generate the next one for you.
and use it as the next input.
Then I'll feed that next word back in as the new input.
and then predict the one after that, always just predicting the next word.
In fact, it also has to produce an output at every single step.
So, these tasks are actually different.
Alright, so let's take a general look.
First, let's look at the overall classification.
It only outputs a result at the very end.
This one is relatively simple.
What we input is a sequence.
and the output is a single label.
For example, sentiment classification.
This is the most classic example.
So, what do we do about it?
Actually, you really have to look at the code directly.
This might make things a bit simpler.
We just read through the entire sequence.
Only the final state...
and then feed that final hidden state into a classifier.
I don't need any of the previous ones.
I only need the last one.
This is because the final hidden state already contains all the information from the preceding steps.
and finally, output a single overall label.
So, first, let's take a look.
So, when we define a model,
First, let's talk about the embedding.
And that's what an embedding is.
How large is my vocabulary?
I'm thinking, for my entire vocabulary, what dimensionality should I use?
So, a 100-dimensional space is enough to represent it.
Or maybe 10,000 dimensions, right?
in the middle, in the RNN layer.
So, for this step in the RNN, all we need to input is the pair.
It's basically just the one from the previous step.
How many dimensions is your embedding?
your hidden layer.
In other words, that's your hidden state.
So, what size vector do you want to use to represent it?
Well, that depends on the scale of your sentences.
And another thing,
Of course, this is what determines the, uh, structure.
So, do you put the batch dimension first,
Or do you put the sequence length first?
Because when we train the model, we're processing multiple sentences at once.
We're not training on just one sentence.
It determines it, just like this.
It outputs the batch.
So, by setting batch_first to true, it will output the batch dimension first.
and then the length of the sequence.
and then the result of the embedding.
If it's set to false,
So first, we output the sequence length.
This is more of a PyTorch syntax issue.
Finally, we just need to define a classifier.
It's a linear layer.
and just classify it.
Of course, this linear layer alone can't handle the classification for us.
Ultimately, we'll definitely need to do some processing on our own.
Now, let's take another look at our forward propagation process.
So, the first step is to embed all of our tokens.
And we get...
Each time, we call the RNN.
Then, each time, we pass the current input through the RNN.
It outputs the current hidden state and all the past hidden states.
So, what exactly is this state?
Because for this one, we only need to take the last layer.
We just need to take out that last layer.
Then, we just need to perform classification on the final layer.
And that's how we get the classification result.
The code, for the most part, isn't that complex.
Now, let's look at the second application: sequence tagging.
For each position, I need to output a label.
So, "I" is a pronoun, right?
This is an adverb.
"Like" is a verb.
Movie is a noun.
So, let's look at how humans express sentences.
This means we need to produce an output at every single step.
So, what do we do in a situation like this?
We're dealing with the same kind of task here.
So, at every single time step, we have to make a prediction.
So, let's take a look at what our code might look like.
This is actually super similar to what we just saw.
This entire section is the embedding layer.
This part is the same.
And the RNN part hasn't changed much either.
and it's also connected to a classifier.
But the difference, as you can see, is what?
So first, after we've used the embedding to properly represent X,
and pass it into the RNN layer.
and we also get the states and HN.
But this time, things are different.
So, let's recap what we did in the last step.
We only used the final h_last.
the final hidden layer.
So, what about this one?
I'm taking the state from every single step,
This is from each step.
I need to use all of them, not just the last one.
So, I just need to output the results for each position one by one.
I need to output at every single position.
Basically, it just depends on the parameters you pass to it.
Now, let's take a look at sequence generation.
At each position, it has to predict the next token.
And this is actually the hottest thing in generative tasks right now.
So, each time, I have to output the probability for the next token.
So, the input we're training on is 'I don't like this movie maybe'
But our goal is to predict the next five characters.
When it's my turn, you make a prediction.
The probability for 'bu' should be the highest.
I write 'I'...
So, I'll just treat "boa" as the second input.
So now you know about these two.
So, it would predict the next word is 'like', as in the 'GT' we use every day.
So, that's pretty much how it works.
It's just that behind the scenes, it's not using an RNN architecture.
So, how does it do that?
It's pretty much the same as these steps.
This part here will look very similar to what we just saw.
It's just that the task we're dealing with here will be completely different.
based on what we give it during backpropagation.
some of the training tasks,
And different tasks will have different losses.
And this way, we gradually get it to make a prediction at every step.
So, the prediction we just made was for a single label.
And this time, we're also feeding in all of the states.
to predict the probability of the next one.
As I mentioned earlier,
Although they use the same task head,
different task heads.
and that might also determine the position of its output and...
what the output will be.
But the training process is pretty much the same for all of them.
First, we have the forward propagation, which generates the output.
Then, we use the loss function to calculate the loss.
and then we use backpropagation to calculate the gradients.
Then, we use gradient descent to update the parameters with that gradient.
And that's how it's done.
So, it's not really any different.
So, how does training this compare to the regular neural networks we saw earlier?
The difference isn't that big either.
Now, let's look at a slightly more complete example of an RNN.
Given a few words,
and then continuously predicts the next word.
until a complete sentence is generated.
So, for a given sequence from W1 to WT, the model...
At each position, it has to estimate the probability of the next token.
And that's pretty much what GPT does, more or less.
The only difference is that it doesn't use an RNN.
it just uses the Transformer architecture instead.
So, speaking in terms of probability,
So, given that words W1 through WT have already occurred,
we want to find the probability of W sub T plus one occurring.
So, which one is the largest?
Of course, all our words need to be in the vocabulary.
We can also generate them ourselves.
or find some training sentences to train it.
So, during the training process,
For example, let's say the sentence is "I like to eat apples."
the end of the sentence.
So, what do we feed into the model?
I like to eat apples.
We want it to predict on its own where the sentence should end.
So, what should our goal be at that point?
So we'll just skip the first word.
Because the first word is already given, right?
So, we start by having it predict from the first word.
the second one.
and use the second one as the input.
and predict the next one based on the previous two.
So for the third step, it's basically like we're just dropping the first one.
and shift it over by one position.
The entire sequence shifts one step to the left.
And with these, we might have tens of thousands of training sentences.
So, we shift each sentence one position to the left.
And from this training,
So our goal is to predict the next word based on the word 'I'.
So, given the words "I" and "like," the model predicts the word "eat."
predicting 'apple' based on 'I like to eat'
and then, based on 'I like to eat apples'
and predict the end-of-sentence marker.
So that's what it does.
Alright, so for our overall code, the first step is to find a corpus.
and load it into the program.
and build a vocabulary.
Actually, it's similar to when we were doing the embedding.
As we've also mentioned before,
So, when we do that,
We shift each sentence one position to the left.
So, we define our RNN model using a training set.
And we just keep training it over and over again.
Once the training is done, we can start making predictions.
Let's take a look at the specific program.
First, we need to prepare the corpus and the training data.
We can find some of these online beforehand.
Whether it's from a novel or something else,
We might generate different batches for them.
Each batch might contain, say, ten sentences or five sentences.
It doesn't really matter.
And it's best if the lengths of these batches are consistent with each other.
And it's not just based on the longest sentence.
So for the shorter ones,
So, for the shorter ones,
we just pad it with this special token to make up the difference.
But we just ignore it when calculating the loss.
Now, what if some very unfamiliar words show up that aren't in our vocabulary?
What if it's not in the vocabulary?
So, we'll also use a special marker for that.
to act as a placeholder.
So, to mark the end of a sentence,
So, we use this one special token to teach the model,
So, when should it stop?
You can't just keep generating forever, right?
Right?
So, let's take a look at the actual code.
Alright, so first, after we've imported the necessary dependencies,
So, what we can do here is...
So, for example, let's say we've already got a model that we've trained.
and found a corpus.
So, for the training corpus,
We've placed a TST file in a specific directory.
So, let's go ahead and read it in.
Let's split it by line.
And then we'll get rid of any empty lines.
Let's split it by spaces.
Now, for English text,
and we can tokenize it into a list of tokens.
And this is the table we get.
And these are a few special tokens used for padding.
and an unknown word token.
And an end-of-sentence marker.
So, after we get rid of those,
And with that, we can build our vocabulary.
So, once we've compiled our vocabulary,
So, basically, we're creating the training data.
So, as we just said, we'll shift them by one position.
Okay, so that's pretty much it for the preparatory work. Once we have all that ready,
Now, we'll define the model.
The model essentially consists of three main steps.
First, the embedding.
Second, we have the main RNN structure itself.
And third, we process it with a linear layer.
to get the raw scores.
So, we don't need softmax during training.
Later, when we make the final prediction for everyone,
that's when we need to take a look at this definition.
It's pretty much the same as what we just used.
So first, we'll embed it.
So, it's determined by a few dimensions.
So for this one, we might need to do some padding.
We didn't do that just now.
The second one is the same as before.
And we'll set 'batch_first' to True.
And the linear layer is defined in the same way.
Because for this one, we need to make a prediction at every single step.
Right?
So, when we're defining the forward propagation,
First, we have the embedding.
So, for the input sequence,
After the embedding,
So, this is where the RNN performs its prediction.
The prediction result we get at each step is actually the hidden state from that same step.
So, the output from the cf layer is basically just a linear layer.
So, we just need to process it once at each step.
Let's see what the score is.
Now that we have the model definition,
and we can start training.
and then we can generate predictions.
We can treat each valid position as a classification problem.
We use cross-entropy for backpropagation, repeatedly propagating the error forward.
and update the parameters.
And that's how we train the model.
So, we use the cross-entropy loss.
And it will automatically apply softmax here.
and we'll use a gradient descent optimizer.
So, we can just use 'item' here.
Set the learning rate to 0.01, and you can train it for, say, 10,000 epochs.
The exact number of epochs will depend on your machine, though.
This also depends on the size of our corpus.
First, we need to get the results from the trained model.
and calculate the loss.
Alright, so after we've calculated the loss,
and clear the gradients.
and start the backpropagation.
And after backpropagation is complete, we let it update the parameters.
I'm sure we're all very familiar with these steps by now.
In the fundamentals of neural networks,
So, it's all the same process.
So, that's why in the first dozen or so lessons,
are the various architectures that came later.
including the foundation for Transformer.
In fact, the core ideas behind all of them are essentially the same.
and then we can make our predictions.
So, let's look at the final step.
We just need to look at the distribution from the final step.
Because each prediction is based on all the previous ones.
So, when we're predicting the next word,
that's where we need to manually tweak the softmax.
So, you take the top k, and then from within that top k, you repeatedly select the one with the highest probability.
If you've ever worked with some of the large models,
So, when it comes to developing these models,
When you're configuring it,
And sometimes, it even asks us to pass in something called a 'temperature' parameter.
Actually, it doesn't necessarily have to pick the one with the highest probability.
Let's see if we want to maintain some diversity.
Sometimes I might not even want the one with the highest probability.
I might do that just to introduce a bit of diversity.
Okay, so this function mainly has two parts.
The first one is 'predict'.
Next.
One is to predict the next word, and the other is to generate, just keep on generating.
So, what it's actually doing is just calling itself over and over again in a loop.
So, it's just a matter of predicting the next word, right?
and just keeps appending it to the end of the sentence.
So, what exactly is happening inside this 'predict_next' function?
Basically, it converts the words in the prefix into vectors.
If it's not in the vocabulary,
So we just use this one as a catch-all.
So, let's see what happens after we've trained the model.
So, here's the logic.
So, what we do is, we don't allow the model to generate certain things in its output.
We don't want it to generate these special tokens.
and just kick it out.
and then it's displayed on its own.
Then, we apply the softmax function to convert them into probabilities.
From the top k, we might just pick the one with the highest probability.
Or, we can decide for ourselves which one to pick.
and take the one with the highest probability for the next word.
Or maybe I want to add some diversity.
or something like picking one of the top three each time.
These are all our own strategies.
By repeatedly running this loop, we can generate a sentence.
So, this is really just a simple illustration.
So, this is basically how it works.
For example, let's say we have the sentence, "I... I like him."
So, the probability of it predicting 'eat' is the highest.
This is a result of the training corpus we're using.
He might also have some other activities like watching, reading, listening, or swimming.
But it knows that 'eat' has the highest probability.
So I'll just append 'eat' to the end.
Then, if we predict the next word, we'll find that 'apple' has the highest probability.
But of course, this all depends on the training corpus you're using.
And just like that, it can keep making predictions.
Of course, 'the weather today' could also be the one with the highest probability.
The probability for that is just a little bit lower.
So, it really just depends on which one you want to use.
And the probability for 'the weather tomorrow might be' would be close to one hundred percent.
So we'll use this greedy method to keep generating new tokens, one after another.
until it generates the "EOS" token.
This means the model thinks the probability of this sentence needing to end is the highest.
and we'll stop there.
and it won't make any more calls.
Alright.
So, that's the basic principle behind it.
But the thing is, we're going to...
So today, let's circle back and take a closer look at this thing called the hidden state.
The hidden state is incredibly important.
Because it's what gives the RNN its ability to remember.
and thus understand the complete sentence as a whole.
Whether it's for generation,
or determining the sentiment of a sentence,
or performing some part-of-speech tagging on a sentence.
So, this hidden state is incredibly important.
So, in an RNN,
So, it doesn't matter how long our sequence is.
Because it can handle sequences of variable length, right?
At each step, the RNN has to take the current input and all the past information,
and compresses it all into a fixed-dimensional hidden state.
For example, let's say we're using a...
a 128-dimensional vector.
So, the hidden state...
So, let's say I only have five tokens at the beginning,
it still has to be compressed into a 128-dimensional vector.
But what if I have 500 tokens?
it still has to squeeze everything into that same 128-dimensional vector.
And this is where you can start to see a problem.
In short sentences,
This summary is basically just a summary of what came before.
But as the sequence gets longer,
So, the earlier information is more likely to be overwritten by what comes later.
And that's actually pretty easy to understand.
Each time, it's performing a multiplication operation.
The most recent information is bound to leave a stronger impression, right?
What the RNN is actually storing is a task-relevant summary.
It's not a perfect, lossless backup of the historical content.
It's a lossy process.
The more recent the information, the more clearly it's remembered.
The longer your sequence gets,
the information from the earlier steps gradually gets lost in all that multiplication.
So, that's one of its problems.
So, as our sequences get longer and longer...
So, RNNs actually run into a few obvious difficulties.
The first is its capacity for representation.
So, as you're writing the current...
as it continuously writes into a state of fixed dimensionality,
the earlier content tends to get weakened or overwritten.
In other words, it's hard to retain information from far back in the sequence.
So, for a really long sentence,
Take this sentence, for example.
For example,
So, we were talking about what problems RNNs solved, right?
when it comes to the problem,
He's already forgotten which architecture actually solved that problem.
And that's very likely to happen.
So, what about the loss at the very end of the optimization path?
propagating backward along the time chain.
So, during this process,
Each time it passes through, it performs multiple matrix multiplications.
Actually, as we go further, we run into a familiar problem.
This leads to the problems of either vanishing or exploding gradients.
Gradient explosion, on the other hand, is something we can still manage to some extent.
But vanishing gradients are nearly impossible to control.
The longer the sequence is,
the more likely this problem is to occur.
So, for these two reasons, it's just not very good at handling long sequences.
They're still okay for understanding short sentences, though.
Another issue is computational efficiency.
So, when we were looking at that simulation code earlier,
And you can see from that as well,
It's basically like a while loop.
In fact, it's basically a recursive call.
Each new output depends on the previous one.
So, that's why it can't be parallelized.
It has to be executed sequentially.
You have to get the result from the first step before you can use it to calculate the next one.
the second step.
and only after the result of the second step is computed, can you use it for the next step.
The calculation for the third step is a serial, interdependent process.
This means there's a dependency between the steps.
This inherent dependency means it cannot be parallelized.
This makes it extremely inefficient.
So, in essence, RNNs solved the problem of how to pass context along a sequence.
this one problem.
through a memory unit.
However, it didn't completely solve the problem.
the memory problem in long sequences.
and the corresponding optimizations.
Another issue was the problem of training efficiency, which also remained unresolved.
So, these are some of its shortcomings.
So, RNNs basically laid the foundation for...
Basically, this is the approach to handling sequence tasks.
It's a core concept.
And all the various models that came after,
all built upon the RNN's core idea and made certain optimizations.
in an attempt to solve these problems.
including the Transformer.
So, first off, LSTM and GRU were developed to tackle these issues.
the problem of long-term dependencies.
They both introduced some gating mechanisms.
This also keeps the gradient under control.
Basically, it's about selectively retaining information.
You don't have to remember every single thing, right?
and forget some things appropriately.
Next up, we have the encoder-decoder.
This means the lengths of the input and output sequences can be vastly different.
So, we can organize these processes of reading and writing into a structure.
the complete sequence.
transforming it into a sequence-to-sequence mapping.
This is essentially the 'sequence-to-sequence' problem.
A classic example of this is machine translation.
And for machine translation, it's not a word-for-word translation, you know.
Unlike the part-of-speech tagging example we just saw,
What it actually does is understand the entire sentence first.
and then translates it into another sentence.
First, it performs an encoding.
First, it encodes it for you,
and then decode it for you.
So, this means the length of its input and output...
So, the English text could be exceptionally long.
In Chinese, you can just use an idiom to sum it up.
This is a very likely scenario.
This was incredibly difficult to achieve in the past.
Now, if we use this architecture, things get a little simpler.
And we'll find that...
But the thing is, these methods still can't fundamentally solve the problem of longer-term memory.
It only helps to alleviate the problem.
And this, in turn, led to the development of...
The core issue is still that you're trying to cram all the information
For sequences of variable length,
and compress all of it into a fixed-length state.
So, to solve this, we later introduced the attention mechanism.
And that is attention.
But this isn't self-attention yet.
So, what about the attention mechanism?
Basically, it helps you understand how everything connects with each other.
It helps you, uh, understand the entire input sequence.
This helps to alleviate that bottleneck.
And later on, this led to the development of the Transformer.
But the Transformer, on the other hand, uses self-attention.
It addresses the problem within a single sentence,
within itself
Every word needs to understand its relationship with every other word.
Let's take a look at the relationship between them.
So in this way, it doesn't actually depend on it either.
And it brought another added benefit.
So, it allows for parallel computation, right?
So, it's no longer advancing through cycles.
It gets the whole picture right from the start.
And on top of that, if every single word has to be connected to all the other words,
Then I don't need to rely on your previous result anymore.
Each word can just act as its own spy, independently.
And then, when we get to the Transformer...
We'll also break that down and explain it in detail for you.
Finally, let's wrap up with a summary of the RNN architecture.
So, what exactly did the RNN do?
Essentially, it uses the same set of parameters to process sequences of varying lengths.
The network then begins to recursively update itself along each timestep.
and the context is also unified for the overall classification.
as well as tasks like sequence labeling and text generation.
All of these can be handled by this single architecture.
So, it basically established the framework for sequence modeling.
ushering in the era of end-to-end training frameworks.
This allowed everyone to build upon its ideas and make further advancements.
However, it didn't solve the problem of long-range dependencies.
And of course, the vanishing and exploding gradient problems are the core issues that come with it.
It uses a fixed-length vector to maintain this state.
So, this is a problem that it didn't solve.
Another thing is its step-by-step inference approach.
This also makes it impossible to parallelize the computations.
This inability to parallelize makes the training process quite inefficient.
So, RNNs defined the fundamental problem of sequence modeling.
So, it established the fundamental paradigm for us.
So, from this point on, the focus was really on continuously improving it.
So, in the next lesson,
So, let's first take a look at LSTM and GRU.
This was a direct modification of the RNN.
So, it's a direct evolution of the RNN.
When you have a state with a fixed dimension,
when it can't remember information from further back in the sequence,
So, they introduced gating mechanisms to alleviate this problem.