Let's take a look at the loss function.
The loss function is crucial for training a model.
So, in our series of videos on machine learning,
in linear regression and logistic regression, respectively.
we've already provided a detailed introduction to the loss function.
But, some of you might have skipped the machine learning part.
and started directly with deep learning.
So, let's do a quick recap for everyone.
So first, let's take a look at what a loss function actually does.
So, after the model has been trained,
We need to use a number to tell the model,
just how badly you messed up in this training session.
And it also tells the model what changes to make to get it a little less wrong next time.
So, this number is actually provided by the loss function.
calculated for us.
Throughout the entire model training process,
In fact, it plays three key roles.
The first one is to measure the error.
It has to tell the model,
So, after this round of training,
between your predicted results and the actual labels of the data.
In other words, how big is the gap between your prediction and the actual value.
We take the derivative of the loss function.
And this result is what we call the gradient.
And this is the starting point for backpropagation.
And finally, it also serves to set the objective for the task.
So, if I tell the model,
A model won't understand if you just tell it, "I want to build a classification model."
And that's all it takes.
So, this loss function's job is to translate our human intentions into a language the optimizer can understand.
In other words, it's the only channel for gradient descent.
This way, the gradient descent algorithm knows what to do.
So, let's take a look at how this process actually works.
First, let's look at the loss function for regression tasks.
And the one that's widely used is MSE.
MSE stands for Mean Squared Error.
Its formula looks something like this.
So basically, the mean squared error represents three operations.
First, I need to calculate the error.
This means you subtract the actual label value from the predicted value.
and then we square that error.
And finally, we sum all of that up.
and then take the average.
And that's why it's called the Mean Squared Error.
Each step is a separate operation.
Let's look at it in reverse.
And a lot of the time, you'll also see this,
And that's what the formula looks like when you put it all together.
But a lot of people might see a 1 over 2N in there.
It's just an extra multiplication by one-half.
Actually, this is just to make the derivative calculation more convenient.
Either way, it doesn't affect the final optimization result.
So, why do we square it?
First off, it's to get rid of the positive and negative signs.
If there are any,
So, for example, let's take this red line.
This is the linear model that we've predicted, right?
And this point here represents the actual value.
So, it's likely that each prediction is a little bit off from the actual value.
Some of these errors are big, and some are small.
If you don't square them,
the large and small ones might just cancel each other out,
as if there were no errors at all.
But in reality, some of these errors are large,
and some are small.
Now, a lot of you might be asking,
So, couldn't you just use the absolute value instead?
So, that brings us to the question: why not just use the absolute value?
By squaring the error, you're essentially amplifying it.
For instance, we obviously want the error to be zero.
But other times, my calculated error might be three.
and when I square it, that's nine.
So, this value actually gets bigger.
But what if, for instance, my calculated error is 0.4?
The difference is actually quite small already.
So, if I square that, I get 0.16.
This makes the error even smaller.
This way, we're making the model more sensitive to larger errors.
In other words, it prioritizes the big picture over minor details.
This allows it to
Of course, squaring the error brings another advantage.
And its derivative is incredibly simple.
is two times...
which is the predicted value minus the actual value.
So, as soon as you see this,
and you'll see what I mean.
So, why do a lot of people immediately multiply it by one-half?
So, it's just the residual.
So, this way, it's a straight line that passes through the origin.
The further you are from it,
the larger it gets, right?
The closer you get to the origin, the smaller it becomes.
This way, it can adaptively compensate for the error.
But what if we use MAE instead?
it actually remains constant.
you won't be able to calculate the derivative.
But MSE actually makes an underlying assumption.
It assumes that our data is actually Gaussian distributed.
In other words, a normal distribution.
In this case, the majority of the data points are still very close to zero.
and the further you get from zero, the rarer they become.
So, in this case,
Then, MMSE is equivalent to maximum likelihood estimation.
So, where MSE really shines is when the errors are symmetrical.
some predictions are large,
while others are under-predicted.
and they're also clustered around zero.
and the closer they are to zero, the more of them there are.
And there aren't any data points that are way off the mark.
In situations like this, using MSE is actually a perfect fit.
But a lot of the time, you do have some outliers.
This means the error is just outrageously large.
In cases like this, squaring the error will just make the problem even worse.
So, in cases where you have a lot of these outliers,
using MSE wouldn't be very appropriate.
So, we can use the absolute value, which is the MAE.
Another thing is, let's assume the target is continuous and comparable.
This means that the error for X2 is four times more severe than for X1.
This holds true for things like housing prices and temperature.
But what if you're dealing with continuous values?
And that, in essence, is what a regression task is all about.
But if you're predicting categories,
For example, predicting a cat as a dog.
or predicting a dog to be an airplane.
So, for classification tasks,
In these cases, you're either right,
or it's just wrong.
There's no issue of magnifying the error or anything like that.
So in a situation like this,
So, what about MSE?
So, it's really not a good fit for classification tasks.
But actually, classification tasks have an even bigger problem.
the gradient will vanish.
making it unusable.
So, let's take a look.
So, MSE is just so great, right?
So why don't we use it for classification?
In binary classification, we use the sigmoid function to output a probability.
to see whether it belongs to the positive class or the negative class.
So, for the sigmoid, the calculation is basically, uh, written like this.
So, that's the loss function.
So, if we do backpropagation to calculate the derivative of L with respect to Z...
So, the derivative of L with respect to Z... well, that's just L itself.
And for Y times Y, that's the derivative of Y with respect to Z.
So, it can be written out roughly like this.
And of course, the derivative of the sigmoid function is just this.
So, it's just Y times one minus Y.
For example, let's say we get a positive sample today.
So it's being classified.
or it's one.
or it's zero.
So, the correct value for this classification should be one.
But our model predicted it to be zero.
So in a situation like this, when we do the math...
So, what should its derivative be?
So its derivative should be extremely large, right?
So, let's get these parameters fixed, right?
But in reality, if you plug in zero,
you'll find that the entire derivative evaluates to zero.
Basically, what this means is that the sigmoid function has been squashed flat around zero.
and you can't update the parameters anymore.
Because your derivative is zero.
This is something we've covered when we talked about backpropagation.
Because every time, it's the learning rate multiplied by the derivative, right?
to adjust the parameters.
So, if the derivative is zero,
the parameters just stop updating.
In other words, my prediction of 'win' was the most egregious error possible.
For example, the correct answer is one, but I predicted it to be zero.
But what happens is, the training just grinds to a halt.
So, to put it simply, you can't use MSE for classification tasks.
So, what should the loss function for a classification task look like?
So, when it comes to classification,
So, what should our new objective be?
In other words, how high is the probability P that the model assigns to the true class.
So for this picture, the probability you should assign to it being a dog is one.
That's the best-case scenario.
If you predict the probability of it being a dog is zero,
that would be the worst-case scenario.
If the prediction is 0.5,
that's basically the same as just guessing.
So, obviously, we want that predicted P to be as high as possible.
So, what we're inputting here is a probability.
So in this case, it's no longer just a single number.
Is it a probability between 0 and 1?
The model assigns a score to the true class.
rather than something like how many classes it's off by.
So, what we want is for it to be monotonically decreasing with respect to P.
In other words, the larger P is,
the smaller the loss.
Right?
So, when P is one,
the loss would be zero, right?
That means its prediction is completely correct.
But what if the prediction is way off?
the penalty should be more severe.
So, if its prediction is zero,
For the positive class, the prediction 'p' should be one, but when the prediction is zero...
the loss should be infinite.
This sends a strong signal to the model that it needs to correct its mistake.
You can't have the penalty for being completely wrong be the same as for being just a little bit wrong.
That won't work.
And it's additive across multiple samples.
Because, as we know,
So, for those N independent samples,
So, the total loss is best represented as a sum.
If you're dealing with continuous multiplication,
Now, as you all know,
Because it's a value between 0 and 1.
Even if you just multiply 0.9 by itself four times, it drops down to 0.6.
If you multiply it by itself ten more times,
and with enough multiplications, it just becomes zero.
In this case, we can't calculate the derivative again.
So, it's best to find one that fits these four characteristics.
So, we need one that fits these four characteristics.
Generally, there are two of them.
One is one minus P, which is your probability subtracted from one.
So, it's basically just how wrong you were, right?
So, if your prediction is one,
then you're completely correct.
But if you predict zero, you're wrong.
is one.
The other one is negative log p.
So, let's take a look at the graphs of these two functions.
In reality, for example, it's one minus P.
So, this curve as a whole still comes down to the four points we mentioned earlier.
They are basically all composite.
But in reality, the third point doesn't hold true.
So, what's the third one?
So, the more mistakes it makes,
the greater the penalty should be.
But its value, its maximum value, is actually one minus P.
Its maximum value is one.
no matter how wildly wrong I am,
I predicted it to be zero.
So your penalty is just one, and that's it.
So that's not going to work, right?
So, that's not ideal.
So let's take a look at negative log p.
Let's see what happens when its value is between 0 and 1.
Actually, it satisfies all of these conditions.
When your prediction is wrong,
its loss is infinite.
And when you predict the one and only correct answer,
the loss is zero.
And on top of that, it has another advantage.
Now, as we know,
log of a times b is equal to log of a plus log of b.
So, when we're actually doing the calculations,
Because, in essence, it's the product of this whole series of probabilities, right?
And finally, this allows us to convert it into a summation.
This way, it won't just become zero.
So, that's why we generally use the negative log of p as our loss function.
to be the loss function for classification tasks.
So, of course, when we write the loss function as negative log p...
It's not something that was just pulled out of thin air or discovered by accident.
Actually, it comes from Information Theory.
or in information theory, the meaning it represents is quite similar.
When something has a great many possibilities,
It means the outcome is uncertain.
So, we want to be able to determine its outcome.
So, how much extra information do we need?
When something is absolutely certain,
Does that mean you need very little information?
For example, let's say you have a loaded coin.
and it lands on heads 99% of the time.
So, if I flip it, and I ask you whether it'll land on heads or tails...
You'd need very little information to make that call.
You can just say it's going to land heads up.
But what if both sides are heads?
So, if I just ask you directly,
both sides are heads.
Then the amount of information you need is zero.
This means it's a 100% certain event.
No matter how you toss it,
and they all land heads up.
So, as you can probably tell from these two letters,
It refers to the difference between two distributions.
So, which two distributions are we talking about?
So, for classification tasks,
So, these two distributions refer to the probability distribution predicted by the model,
and the distribution of the true labels.
in other words, the gap between the two.
Of course.
The smaller the gap between these two,
And the more reliable the model's prediction will be.
First, let's take a look at the binary classification task.
But wait, that's not right.
Wait, didn't you just say it was negative log p?
Why does it look so complicated when you write it out like that?
Well, the thing is, in binary classification tasks...
In reality, there are only two possibilities.
Or, to put it another way, in the original data...
it's either positive,
or it's negative.
So, this is how we actually write it.
In fact, there are two ways to write the formula for this.
But, in order to force it into a single formula,
we used a little trick.
automatically turning the other one off.
For example, let's say our true label is positive.
So, when the sample Y equals one,
You'll find that this latter term just becomes zero.
So you can just ignore it, because one minus Y, one minus one, is just zero, right?
So, Y times Y... well, it becomes Y times the log of y.
So, what this really means is the negative log of p.
If our sample is a negative sample,
So, that term is just zero to begin with.
Then the first term here becomes zero.
So, only the latter term is useful here.
And since one minus Y is just one,
So we can just ignore that part.
So, it's log of one minus y, y hat.
And this part here is the prediction.
So in reality, it collapses down to something like this.
So, the reason we write it this way is just for the sake of our calculations.
Let's express this with a formula.
Its gradient calculation is actually combined with the sigmoid function.
So, we know that when we take the derivative of the loss function with respect to the sigmoid,
But, its derivation is, uh, particularly complex.
so I won't walk you through the derivation here.
But the result we get is surprisingly simple.
But when you look at the predicted value minus the actual value,
This is a probability, you see.
Because after it goes through the Sigmoid function, it's transformed into a probability.
Hmm, why does this look so much like MSE?
And that's actually no coincidence.
They were designed as a pair in the first place.
And that's how simple it is to calculate its derivative.
And that's all there is to it.
And that's actually another one of its advantages.
So why is it so widely used?
And the derivative is simple.
This makes backpropagation much simpler.
I won't go through the mathematical derivation with you all.
So, all you need to remember is this result.
The same applies to multi-class classification.
So, let's take a look.
So, let's say our neural network gives us an output.
We're dealing with a three-class classification task.
one of which is two,
one is one,
and the other is 0.1.
It has the highest score.
But this doesn't represent a probability.
Right?
So, what do we do?
So, first, we need to take these three values and run them through the Softmax function.
This process makes them add up to a total of one.
Let's say an event can happen in three different ways.
So the probabilities for each might be, say, 0.66, 0.24, and 0.1.
And they have to add up to one, right?
And that's pretty much the main job of the softmax function.
It takes the values of these three and transforms them into a sum.
a single value that equals one.
And it's always a positive number.
And at this point, they've been converted into probabilities.
So, once we have these probabilities,
So, we just need to plug it into the formula.
So, as you can see, when we plug it in, it basically looks like this.
So, one times this, plus zero times that, and so on.
So let's assume that our prediction for D is the correct one.
is the true value.
the one in the first position.
So, the corresponding true labels for the other two should be zero.
Because out of the three, only one can happen, right?
And that's exactly what the Bernoulli distribution is all about.
So, when only one of them can happen,
So, the probability of the other events occurring is zero.
So, the true value is one, and when you multiply it by one...
So you can see, this is the magnitude of the loss.
And the same goes for calculating its derivative.
The result is simply the predicted value minus the actual value.
It's incredibly simple.
It aligns perfectly with the four characteristics we discussed earlier.
making it perfect for classification tasks.
Plus, when it comes to backpropagation,
Whether it's used for binary classification with the Sigmoid function,
or multi-classification's Softmax,
calculating the derivative is incredibly simple.
This makes the computation extremely efficient.
is pretty much the go-to choice
it's the go-to choice for pretty much any kind of classification task.
Alright, to wrap things up, let's do a quick summary.
So, how do we choose between them?
So, for regression tasks,
A lot of the time, we just go ahead and use MSE for binary classification.
And for multi-class classification, you just apply Softmax.
So, their loss formulas basically look something like this.
It looks incredibly complex.
But their gradients are actually very simple to calculate.
Under the hood, they also make certain assumptions about the distribution of the data.
So, for MSE,
we assume it follows a Gaussian distribution.
in other words, a normal distribution.
As for binary classification, we assume it follows a Bernoulli distribution.
In essence, these two are mutually exclusive.
it either happens,
or it doesn't.
Both can't happen at the same time.
So, what about multi-class classification?
This is essentially the multinomial distribution.
It's basically a further extension of the Bernoulli distribution.
And we don't actually have to implement any of this ourselves.
is implemented.
So, let's take a look.
Now, for regression tasks,
So, once we bring in neural networks,
and you'll see it's just the MSE loss.
So, for the loss function...
You just need to plug in the predicted values and the actual values.
Now, for binary classification tasks,
For binary classification, you just use logistic regression.
And then, for multi-class classification,
In these cases, it's actually quite simple.
But, there's a hidden catch here.
As we know,
So, when we're writing the code to define our model,
So, as we know, when we use this one...
and you can get a whole bunch of neurons all set up.
and that defines every single layer for us.
And finally, we apply the softmax function to the last layer.
But what we'll find is...
its accuracy gets stuck at a random guess level.
It just won't train.
So, why is that?
And that's because of this step right here.
it has already applied softmax on its own.
So, when you're defining your model,
So, when we're defining our network,
don't include the Softmax layer in your code.
The loss function will take care of it internally.
So, what it wants you to output is the most direct, raw result.
that result.
It will apply the Softmax function on its own.
So, in situations like this, the training process gets a real boost.
So, to wrap things up.
So, the optimizer decides the path we take.
The loss function.
determines where to go.
So, the loss function essentially has three roles.
MSE is pretty much exclusively for regression tasks.
So, in the next lesson, we'll start introducing some code.
Let's see how a very simple neural network works.
And at that point,
So, when we're looking at this kind of code,
and it'll all make sense.
And from an engineering perspective, remember this:
So, when you're implementing this Softmax layer, never, ever write it yourself.
Alright then.
So, about the loss function...
So that's a quick rundown for you all.