In the last video, we covered how images are represented inside a computer.
and how
So why is it that when it comes to handling complex visual tasks, MLPs...
leads to a parameter explosion.
and lead to overfitting.
and broke down the unique nature of image data.
the structural information it inherently contains.
And from there, the CNN architecture was gradually developed.
Alright, so starting with this video,
let's take a detailed look at the CNN architecture.
and how it recognizes an image step by step.
And the most crucial components are convolution, feature maps, and pooling.
First, let's take a look at the overall architecture of a CNN.
This will make it easier to understand the specifics that follow.
Actually, the architecture of a CNN isn't that complex.
It can be broken down into two main parts: a front end and a back end.
The first part can be thought of as a feature extractor.
and the latter part takes these extracted features,
After processing those,
to give the final classification of the image.
to achieve our goal in visual processing.
For instance, the final output for this image might simply be 'landscape'.
So, how exactly do they extract these features?
And this process is carried out by three specific components.
And each of these components forms a distinct layer.
The first of these layers is called the convolutional layer.
This one is, of course, the most important part.
And that's also where the 'C' in CNN comes from, right?
So, the convolutional layer works by using a small matrix,
and it scans the image over and over again.
to extract local features.
and generates a feature map.
So, once that's generated,
ReLU,
And this, we're all very familiar with.
to introduce non-linearity.
The activated result is then passed to the next layer for pooling.
So, what is 'pooling'?
Basically, it's just about reducing the size of the feature map.
But the thing is, our convolutional kernel...
In other words, this small scanner...
its size stays the same.
So, as the image gets smaller,
my scanner sees relatively more of it.
This means we can take the features from the convolutional layer and combine them in an abstract way.
But a single set like this isn't enough.
And beyond that, these layers can be stacked repeatedly.
And this holds true for multiple layers.
However, each time, it's the combination of these three layers that we're talking about.
The specific number of layers is typically not limited.
Ultimately, this allows us to abstract away from the raw image.
a more complex, higher-level combination that the network can understand.
This is what's called a feature map.
we then flatten this feature map into a one-dimensional vector.
Finally, we'll pass it through a fully connected layer.
and then the softmax function gives us the final output.
And just like that, we've classified the image.
This architecture, as it turns out, isn't actually that complex.
In fact, as we can see from the description,
The core of it is the convolutional layer.
So, how do we scan it piece by piece,
and see its features without having to flatten the image first.
and eventually recognize the image.
So, let's dive into the specifics now.
the core components: the convolutional and pooling layers.
And lastly, the fully connected layers.
The first part of the network acts as a feature extractor.
So, these three groups of layers emerge repeatedly. The convolutional layers are responsible for extracting these patterns.
ReLU introduces a non-linear component, while the pooling layer...
this decreases the spatial resolution.
Which basically means the image's resolution.
and expand the effective receptive field.
We call this the receptive field.
Then, in the later part of the network for classification, it takes the feature map...
Not the original image.
So, after we flatten the feature map,
we perform a fully connected layer.
So, we're no longer working with the original image at this point.
Instead, it's processing the high-level features extracted by the convolutional layers.
and finally, classify it.
The latter part is a bit like an MLP, though.
The only difference is that it's no longer processing the original pixels directly.
So, this means that a CNN can't understand the entire image with just a single convolutional layer.
Instead, it's a process of stacking these layers one by one.
Gradually transforming pixels into semantic meaning.
So, in the early layers, it first starts by looking at things like the edges of the image.
colors,
and textures.
Then, in the middle layers, it can start to perceive...
And through the pooling layer,
And that also increases the receptive field.
and then we can start combining these low-level features.
a convolutional kernel
This means that the area it scans effectively becomes larger.
By combining them, we can start to form things like outlines and distinct components.
And going even deeper, it gradually starts to achieve some higher-level understanding.
leading to a complete understanding of the object itself.
Alright, so now let's get to the most crucial part.
So, what does the convolutional layer do?
The convolutional layer's job is to transform local patterns into a feature map.
Its core task is to do this without flattening the image.
nor using fully connected layers.
Because if you do that, you're just following the MLP approach, and the number of parameters would explode.
But without doing those two things,
it extracts meaningful local features from the image.
So, how does it do that?
First, it uses a small matrix of weights.
we call it a convolutional kernel.
For instance, let's say this matrix is a 3 by 3.
filled with some numbers.
So, it's going to move across the image, probably from left to right,
sliding down from the top.
And at each position,
it takes the pixels within that current window
Because in our last lesson, we already introduced how images...
In fact, each of these little squares represents a single pixel.
I'm a 3x3.
Now, as it slides across the original image, we see there are three values here.
So, that's nine numbers.
And it just so happens that this convolutional kernel also has nine numbers.
So, what does it do?
and multiplies the values in each corresponding position.
and then you add up all the results.
and then summed up to create the new pixel value.
And just like that, it becomes one of the image's features.
For example, this one I've listed here is a sharpening filter.
It can sharpen the image.
So, you can see here,
So as it processes the image, layer by layer from top to bottom,
After scanning from left to right,
gradually, the image is transformed into something like this.
And this right here shows you the correspondence between them.
So, as you can see, let's take a more mathematical look at it.
So,
For example, let's take our original image.
The gray area represents our original image.
Let's say it's 6 by 6.
So, it's a 6 by 6 pixel image.
And our convolutional kernel is 3x3.
or we can also call it a filter.
Actually, it does look very similar.
It’s kind of like an overlay layer on top of our image, right?
First, I'll place it in the top-left corner.
Because it's a 3x3 kernel, right?
And in this position, there are some overlapping areas with it.
and have the two of them perform an operation,
Actually, this operation, what we understand as convolution...
The reason it's called that,
And that's exactly where the operation gets its name from.
Actually, it's not a convolution in the strict mathematical sense.
Once you've multiplied all the corresponding positions, you add up the results.
And then, you take those nine products and add them all up.
And that gives us a single number.
and that becomes the first value in our new image.
And we just keep moving it...
then to the second,
then to the third position.
until finally, it gets moved to this position.
We perform the convolution operation at each position to fill in the values.
And just like that, a new image is formed.
So, as you can see,
So, if we don't do anything special,
this resulting image is actually larger than the original one.
This means the new image is going to be a bit smaller.
This is because with every operation,
For instance, each slide only produces one pixel.
But in a situation like this, let's say you're up here,
It can't slide off the edge, right?
It can only slide completely within the image.
So that's the first pass.
So, for the second, third, and fourth positions, does that mean you can only slide it four times?
And the same applies from top to bottom.
So, we end up with a 4x4 matrix.
So, this value that we've calculated...
Actually, this result is meaningful.
This value represents the local region at the current position.
that matches the pattern of the convolutional kernel.
For instance, let's say I'm sharpening the image.
I'm detecting edges, or let's say, horizontal lines.
or the recognition of vertical lines.
Is there a horizontal line in the area I'm currently scanning?
or a vertical line.
The larger this number is,
the more it matches the pattern of the convolutional kernel.
And the smaller the number, the less of a match it is.
So, the output from this process, while it's also just a bunch of numbers,
But these numbers actually mean something.
and it corresponds to the convolutional kernel.
So, each convolutional kernel represents a specific feature.
Alright, let me show you a slightly more practical example.
Let's take a look.
So, for instance, let's take a...
a scan of a cup of coffee.
So, after scanning it...
And with just one convolutional kernel,
and gradually, it can take on a form like this.
So, let's see how it all works.
Because, as we know, any image has its RGB three channels.
They actually correspond to each other.
So, let's break down this convolutional kernel.
It continuously scans across the image.
Finally, it will combine these three images into one.
and then we add a bias.
And just like that, we have a new image.
a new feature map.
But the dimensions aren't necessarily a perfect match.
This is just a simplified illustration.
And it ends up looking something like this.
So, after processing all three channels,
Finally, the values from all three channels are summed up together.
This process, which we call convolution,
And this resulting image is the processed output.
This resulting image is what we call a feature map.
So, looking at it from this perspective,
In essence, a convolutional kernel is a tiny, tiny feature detector.
So, let me show you a more concrete example.
Some kernels might learn to detect vertical lines,
while others might learn to detect horizontal lines.
Some might detect changes in color,
or certain textures, things like that.
And that's how it works.
So for the original image, I've converted it to grayscale.
It's a pretty simple one.
I've applied two convolutional kernels.
and I'll scan it with them.
As you can see, these two convolutional kernels...
in the scan results?
This is because it has very distinct horizontal and vertical lines.
This convolutional kernel is clearly much more sensitive to vertical lines.
The horizontal lines have been almost completely filtered out.
and shapes like circles become much less defined.
This convolutional kernel, on the other hand, is clearly more sensitive to horizontal lines.
So, the image it produces after scanning would look something like this.
And using this one,
we can get a sense of how many horizontal lines are in this image.
And with this one,
and figure out roughly how many vertical lines are in the image.
Of course, not all convolutional kernels...
All of these kernels have meanings that humans can understand.
and some of them are just plain incomprehensible.
It's like how some parameters in a deep neural network might be a seven,
some are two or three.
What does that even mean?
You can't really make sense of it either.
But, well, since I can't make any sense of it,
Plus, I don't even know how many different patterns there are.
So, for each convolutional kernel, don't they have...
Let's say it's a 3x3,
So, does that mean there are nine parameters?
So, how do I set the values for these parameters?
The truth is, you don't know what these values should be either.
And this result is, in fact, what you get from training the model.
So, what about the numbers inside these convolutional kernels?
Essentially, these are the parameters of the neural network.
The ones we've trained the model to produce.
and then corrected bit by bit through backpropagation.
Now, let's take a look inside.
In fact, there are three other key concepts we need to cover.
First, a crucial concept is the size of the convolutional kernel.
So, the size of the convolutional kernel...
This determines the size of the local region the kernel looks at each time.
A common choice might be a 3x3.
or 5x5.
the larger the convolutional kernel is,
the larger the area it scans each time.
so the visible area at one time is larger.
But the thing is, the larger it is...
the more parameters it's going to have.
And the computational load will increase as well.
Nowadays, the 3x3 kernel is the most common choice.
Because they're small enough.
which makes them easy to stack.
So, let's take an example.
So this is a 3x3 one.
So, for example, you can take a look at how it scans the image.
In fact, the first time is right here.
The second time, it moves here.
and for the third and fourth, it moves down one again.
And you just keep shifting it down, one by one.
and move down one more step.
And, like I just mentioned...
So, the original image is 6 by 6.
and after it scans through,
without any special padding,
So, after scanning,
So, horizontally, we can only make four moves each time, right?
and we get a result for each step.
And vertically, it's the same, it can only scan four times.
So, what you end up with is a 4 by 4 matrix.
So, the feature map has actually gotten smaller.
So, this is the difference based on the size of the convolutional kernel.
So, what if my convolutional kernel is 5x5?
So it can only scan twice, right?
and the resulting image will be 2x2.
So it gets smaller.
But at the end of the day, the numbers we get out are all meaningful.
The second factor is actually the stride, or how much it moves each time.
So, what this means is, before, we were just moving it one step at a time by default.
Right?
moving one pixel at a time.
But in reality, I can increase the stride a bit.
So it moves by a larger amount each time.
This way, it will skip one position each time, outputting the feature from that location.
the reduction in the height and width of the feature map becomes more pronounced.
Let's say, like this.
I'm jumping two at a time.
This way, since it can't go any further.
and can't move any further.
So, we're basically just discarding this feature.
Then we move on to the second one.
Because if it moves two more steps,
it's also out of bounds.
and it can't move any further.
So, it changes.
So, if my stride is two,
it becomes a 2x2.
That's quite a significant reduction.
Right?
But for a 5x5 image,
it will also become 2 by 2.
Because it can't move any further outside the original bounds.
So, we see that my stride can also change its dimensions.
But of course, for convolutional layers in general,
our stride is set to one.
This is to get a more complete picture.
It's generally in the pooling layer that we'll set it to two.
And the next thing is padding.
So, what's padding for?
to solve the problem we just mentioned.
So every time I perform a scan,
it's now shrunk to a 6x6.
and it gets scanned down to 4x4.
So, to keep our dimensions the same size,
This is to ensure that the computation remains stable.
So, before we start this scanning process,
we can add a border of zeros around the edges of the image.
So, after adding this zero-padding,
So, let's say we have a 4x4 image to start with.
So, after I add this border of zeros,
so it becomes 6 by 6.
So now it becomes a 6 by 6 image.
And then, we just do the same scanning process as before.
so the output remains 4 by 4.
I started out with a 4x4.
So after scanning, it's still 4x4.
This is for a convolutional kernel size of three.
So, when we're making that determination,
All you have to do is pad the edges of the image with zeros.
This way, it's possible to...
so that the feature map we get from scanning the image...
matches the size of the original image.
So, for this, uh...
And later on, when we're actually defining this in our code,
we'll also be frequently setting the values for these three numbers.
So, do you know what each of these three values represents?
So, how exactly do we calculate this size?
Actually, there's a formula for this.
So, for example, the final...
For example, the height and width of the resulting image that I calculate.
what their dimensions will be.
It actually depends on the height of your original input image,
and the size of your convolutional kernel.
the stride of the movement,
All of these factors are related.
And there's a formula for this,
For example, let's say it's a 32 by 32 image.
So, if our K is equal to three...
K is equal to three,
So basically, it means a 3x3 convolutional kernel with P equal to one.
so we'll pad it with a一圈一 of zeros.
And S equals one.
So basically, it just slides across the image each time.
If we move it by one each time,
So, our output volume will still be 3x32x32.
If we keep everything else the same,
Basically, you just change that S to a two.
essentially, it gets divided by two.
Because it was originally 33 by 4.
Wasn't it 32 by 32?
So, after you divide by two,
it becomes 16 by 16.
So that's why it gets cut in half.
And this also happens during pooling.
So, how exactly does it get cut in half?
All you have to do is set the stride to two.
So, in the example we were just looking at...
Actually, we've just converted it to a grayscale image.
so it looks like it's just two-dimensional.
So, we're saying this is a 3x3 convolutional kernel.
and that'd be a 4×4 convolutional kernel.
But in reality, when we're dealing with actual images...
For instance, an RGB image has three channels.
Right?
It's not just a grayscale image.
It's made up of three images, or three channels, right?
So in this case, what about our convolutional kernel?
and it can't be a 3×3 either.
so it has to have three as well.
So for each of my convolutional kernels,
has to scan your entire image from top to bottom.
In reality, I'm scanning across all three of your channels.
Actually, I... I... I'm also corresponding to the red one.
I have a 2x3x3 one.
This demo might be showing a 4x4 image, actually.
And for the green one?
I have a corresponding one for that as well.
And for the blue one, I have a similar one as well.
So, for the feature map that I get after scanning...
So, what's inside... well, of course, for the feature map I've just scanned out,
Because I also need to use that previous image to give you a demonstration.
As you can see,
Let me give you a demonstration.
Ultimately, it doesn't matter how many channels you have,
Now, it might look like these are three separate convolutional kernels.
it's actually one single convolutional kernel.
It's just that it has an extra dimension.
It's a 3×3, but also by 3.
But after it finishes scanning,
as if it's going to generate three feature maps.
But that's not actually the case.
So, it takes the results from scanning these three feature maps,
This is a single operation.
and then combines them all together.
And after adding the bias term,
This process creates what's called a feature map.
So, That means a single convolutional kernel will only generate one output feature map.
So, it doesn't matter how many channels you have.
It doesn't matter if it's three channels or six.
and you'll end up with just a single feature map.
Alright, so how do we get more features?
all we have to do is use more convolutional kernels.
So, sometimes...
For instance, let's say we use 16 convolutional kernels.
So, how many feature maps will we end up with?
So, you'll get 16 feature maps, and that number is independent of the specific number of channels in the input.
The number of convolutional kernels you use,
that's how many channels you'll get.
these are the feature maps.
feature map.
So, in the end, let's say I used 16 of them.
ultimately, this results in 16 feature maps
and combine them all together.
This makes computations with matrices much more convenient.
And in PyTorch,
which is to say, it's a multi-dimensional tensor.
So, it's really important for everyone to get this straight.
As for the dimensions of my convolutional kernel...
Here, we use K-by-K to represent its size.
So, what's its dimensionality, then?
It actually represents the number of channels in your input.
that's how many dimensions it has.
So, it's just a simple calculation, really.
So, try not to get this part mixed up.
A single convolutional kernel can only produce one feature map.
So, as we just introduced,
regardless of how many channels there are.
So, a convolutional kernel...
It will perform multiplication and addition operations on each of the channels individually.
But in the end, all these results are added together.
And then you add the bias to get a single response value.
In other words, a single convolutional kernel will only output one feature map.
Okay, so what about the number of output channels?
In reality, it's about how many convolutional kernels you have.
that's how many outputs you get.
So, naturally, that would be the number of convolutional kernels.
This gives you the number of output channels.
Because a single feature map can only represent one type of detection result.
More often than not, we need to detect multiple features, right?
So, we just use multiple convolutional kernels.
So, it'll output as many maps as there are kernels.
For example, let's say we want to detect 16 different patterns.
So, we'll use 16 convolutional kernels to scan it.
And just like that, we've extracted 16 different features.
So, we just stack them all together.
So, it's 16 times the size of the feature map.
So, for our input...
So, for example, let's take a look at this.
So our input, for example, is a 3 by 32 by 32... so, after processing...
So what is this?
You'll be using this a lot when you start coding later on.
So, for a 2D convolutional layer, what does this '3' represent?
It refers to the number of input channels.
This represents the number of convolutional kernels.
The number four here means it's a 3x3 kernel.
Which is one, right?
Then the output will become this 16-channel feature map.
But the dimensions stay the same.
The default stride is one.
as long as you don't change it.
I don't buy it.
It's one.
We need to actually look at a more realistic example.
So, for example, what does this all mean?
So first, we have the input.
Here we have an image.
Because a color image has three channels: RGB.
But, I have ten convolutional kernels.
Right?
So, as you can see,
Each of these convolutional kernels is designed to extract a unique feature from the image.
And this process is repeated, layer by layer, as the information is passed on.
And after that, we have another ten convolutional kernels.
Another ten convolutional kernels continue this scanning process.
And finally, it concludes that this is... a cup of coffee.
Now, let's continue.
So, why do convolutional layers save so many parameters?
So by now, we should be able to understand why.
So, as we can see...
So, how many parameters are there in a single layer?
In fact, this is determined by the convolutional kernels.
So, how many convolutional kernels do you have?
And then you just add the number of biases.
So, as for the convolutional kernel, let's say its size is defined by K.
so it would be a 3 by 3.
If you have three channels,
then you multiply by three.
For instance, if you wanted to have 16 features,
Then you'd multiply that by 16.
Plus another 16 biases.
Because every convolutional kernel needs its own bias term.
So, adding all that up gives you 448.
So as you can see, this layer has only a little over 400 parameters.
Compare that to the MLPs we covered last time, which can easily run into the thousands or even millions of parameters.
So the difference is massive, right?
So, that's what makes Convolutional Neural Networks, or CNNs, so incredible.
This is all thanks to the convolution operation.
So that it allows me to, without flattening it,
instead of flatting the image.
I can still extract, uh...
the intermediate features.
all with just a small number of parameters.
So, at this point, we've basically covered the convolution operation.
And this is the most complex operation in the entire CNN.
As for the mathematical principles behind it,
For those of you who are interested, you can go check some of them out.
There are plenty of resources available online.
So we won't go into detail about that here.
So, the first thing we need to understand is the convolutional kernel.
It's just a small matrix.
And most of the time, it's going to be 3x3.
scan continuously from top to bottom,
and from left to right, scanning our image.
to capture some of the local features within this image.
It could be a horizontal line,
or a vertical line.
Or even the edges and corners. The result of this scanning process is what we call a feature map.
It records the value at each position,
and the strength of the response from this convolutional kernel.
The number of output channels is equal to the number of convolutional kernels.
And the parameters? They can be shared.
So with that in mind, let's take another look.
So, remember that architecture diagram we showed you at the beginning?
So, does that make things a little bit clearer?
At the very least, for this layer, you can see all these little boxes we've drawn,
So, these correspond to each other.
So basically, the information propagates from here, layer by layer, all the way to this point.
and the feature map becomes smaller.
So, we should have a general idea of what's going on here.
This is a typo. It should be 'pooling'.
Of course, we haven't explained how it actually gets smaller yet.
Actually, you can figure out how it changes just by looking at its state.
Alright, next up, let's take a look at some of the layers that come after this.
First up is the rectified linear unit, or ReLU.
The non-linear activation is... uh... rectification.
And that's how these layers are stacked.
So, after the pooling layer,
and it will output the final classification results.
Finally, let's look at a simple example.