Alright, we've finally made it to the video on NLP.
But we're not going to jump right into the specific details of NLP just yet.
Instead, let's walk through the timeline of NLP's development.
So, after we've covered all that,
you'll have a clear picture of the entire field of NLP.
including the Transformer.
and how it was invented, step-by-step, by standing on the shoulders of giants.
So, after the Transformer was invented,
So why didn't it immediately take the world by storm?
Even the companies of the eight authors,
Even Google didn't recognize the value of the Transformer.
So, how did Transformer then evolve into GPT?
So, what about NLP, the technology that changed the world?
It's short for Natural Language Processing.
Its core objective is to enable computers to understand, process, and generate human language.
or even use human natural language.
So, what are the most common tasks?
Take machine translation and sentiment analysis, for example.
You give it a sentence,
and have it determine whether the sentiment is positive or negative.
Information extraction.
This involves pulling out key pieces of information from a text.
Text generation.
This is actually the most common application area for AI today.
Right, like generating a summary of an article.
and interact with us.
generate charts,
answer our questions,
help us write emails,
all of which requires coding.
write a thesis,
In fact, all of these are tasks that NLP can handle.
Now, on the surface, these tasks might seem completely different from one another.
But the problem they're all trying to solve is actually the same.
It's all about how to get machines to understand and process human language.
So, this is where NLP differs from programming.
Programming, at its core, is a situation where neither humans nor computers understand each other.
So, they both had to take a step back and meet in the middle.
and invented an intermediary language.
Humans learn grammar,
Take the C programming language, for example.
and learned Python.
and wrote it in a programming language.
But the machine can't understand this programming language either.
It uses a compiler or an interpreter to convert it into binary code.
And that's how it works.
But for humans, this is relatively costly.
That's why not everyone can program, right?
But NLP, it takes that a step further.
It's incredibly user-friendly.
You just use English yourself,
or Chinese,
You just use your own natural language.
You can just talk directly to the machine.
and let the machine learn everything else on its own.
So, this means it places a much heavier burden on the machine.
But, of course, this also made things more difficult.
Compared to static programming,
But at the same time, it's also become a technology that benefits everyone.
Nowadays, you have kids as young as six or seven,
and up to the elderly in their 70s and 80s,
can all use AI in their daily lives.
and in their work.
And that's what's making AI technology so much more accessible to everyone.
So, how did NLP evolve to this point?
Actually, this is something we've covered in our introduction to machine learning and AI.
As we've also mentioned,
It all started with symbolism.
People tried to describe the world using rules.
This approach is all about using rules to express human language.
But eventually, they found this approach was a dead end. It just didn't work.
And so, we gradually moved into the realm of probability.
And this probabilistic approach led to the field of machine learning.
And then, moving on...
And that's when word embeddings were invented.
So, the consensus was that language still had to be represented by numbers.
And computers are exceptionally good at processing numbers, right?
So, they took these discrete symbols...
and placed them into a continuous semantic space.
And gradually, this led to the development of RNNs.
So, besides being able to, uh, process complete sentences...
After understanding the words,
It could also process entire sentences.
This was a huge leap forward for NLP.
But, we'll find that it still has a few minor issues.
It couldn't handle generation tasks.
and it also had some shortcomings when it came to translation.
And that's where sequence-to-sequence came in.
And this idea would then lead to the concept of attention.
But this attention mechanism wasn't the one from the Transformer.
Transformer.
but the one in the Transformer.
It pretty much brought all of this previous knowledge together.
It stands on the shoulders of giants.
And of course, it invented self-attention.
self-
Because it's a decoder-only model.
And this self-referential process, this looking at itself, was the very birth of the Transformer.
And from there, large models gradually emerged.
So, step by step, machines went from merely seeing text to actually understanding it.
and eventually, learned to generate.
So, let's take a look at the evolution of NLP.
First up is the Symbolism era.
The core idea was to use rules to enumerate every possible language construct.
So, in the early days of NLP,
This approach is quite intuitive.
Language, after all, has grammar.
You know, subject, predicate, object, verb, linking verb, predicate... all that stuff.
and so on.
Things like passive voice, and all that, uh...
Back then, the prevailing belief was that...
The idea was, as long as you could just write all these rules into a program,
and the machine would be able to understand language.
This was because language itself was thought to be something that could be formalized.
and can therefore be programmed.
And machine translation is the most classic example of this.
The first step is to perform a dictionary-based substitution.
and then re-adjust the word order within the sentence.
and perform some information extraction.
and then extract the main components like the subject, verb, and object.
And they figured that would be good enough.
There was dictionary-based translation.
And just like that, a one-to-one mapping would produce the translation.
But,
But it's not like there was no theoretical foundation back then.
So, whether it was mathematicians conducting some explorations,
Just like translation.
This was the very first exploration of LP.
So basically, language is like a code.
You feed it the source text, which contains some hidden rules for mapping relationships.
As long as you write down every single one of them,
you can convert it into another language.
So, for this kind of language, translation is basically a decoding process.
Meanwhile, linguists also provided proof of this.
formal languages and generative grammar.
These rules reinforced the belief that language could be fully systematized.
This belief
So, as you can see, the symbolic approach was dominant for a very long time.
So, language is like a code.
So, the corresponding solutions for early NLP...
The idea was to write out this 'password' in the form of a corresponding rulebook.
But gradually, people started to realize there was a problem.
I mean, language does have rules, that's for sure.
And on top of that, the sheer volume of these rules is just massive.
It was simply impossible to write them all down.
Natural language is highly dependent on its context.
And it's not just that there are a ton of rules.
and the same rules...
can actually mean something completely different in different contexts.
For example, take the phrase "You're quite the talker."
This sentence could be a compliment,
or it could be sarcasm.
You have to consider the context and the tone of voice.
and even the relationship between the speakers to make that call.
So, as you can imagine, people gradually started to realize...
There are just too many ways to express language.
and all sorts of unexpected issues kept popping up.
Context also plays a crucial role.
There's just no way to enumerate all the rules.
So basically, this whole approach just went bust.
Gradually, some NLP researchers began to turn to statistical methods.
And as you dive into machine learning, you'll start to notice something.
In fact, all sorts of statistical methods...
and there's a whole lot of knowledge in probability theory.
And this, in turn, ushered in the era of statistics.
In other words, machine learning.
They learn the patterns from the corpus, uh...
But of course, this was all driven by the context of the times.
So, starting from the late 1980s,
Then, in the 1990s,
First of all, computing power had improved.
text and all sorts of speech data.
and with that, the amount of data for NLP also increased.
People started to see language as something that could be estimated from data.
a probability distribution.
For instance, if I say, "I want to eat something today..."
So, you know the probability of the word 'hot pot' coming next,
is much, much higher than the probability of it being 'screwdriver'.
It's just because I've seen all sorts of phrases like 'let's eat hot pot today'...
Let's have hot pot tomorrow.
And I like to put beef in my hot pot.
The screwdriver is great.
use
Screwdriver, fix the chair.
A screwdriver is a machine with a cross-shaped head.
It doesn't truly understand what 'hot pot' is.
But what it can do is look at it probabilistically.
As long as it's fed enough sentences to learn from,
it will know the probability of 'hot pot' following the word 'eat'.
is much, much higher than 'screwdriver', right?
I don't have to understand.
But probabilistically, I just know what comes next.
And that's the core idea behind it.
There was even a speech recognition expert at IBM who once said,
He once said,
that every time I fire a linguist,
my speech recognition rate goes up a little.
Now, that sounds incredibly harsh, doesn't it?
But it also really reflected the reality of the situation back then.
A key shift in NLP research
So, systems were no longer primarily dependent on experts writing rules.
So, what did they rely on instead?
Instead, they use probability to analyze massive amounts of text corpora,
and treating massive amounts of text and speech data as empirical evidence for statistical analysis.
and what's more likely to come after it.
and what might have come before it.
Even though I don't understand language itself,
But from an engineering perspective, I can actually make that prediction.
And it was around this time that all sorts of n-grams were born.
and then it could predict the next word.
In language modeling,
And for input methods, there's also... uh...
In fact, the earliest input methods we used also employed this technology.
And it was also widely used in machine translation.
And there were also different RCRFs.
These include classic statistical machine translators.
This kind of dual-source, semantically driven system is what we call a translation system.
And this approach did yield some results during that era.
This allowed for the application of probability theory or, more broadly, machine learning.
And it did see some applications in NLP.
The idea is to first convert a language task into something that can be statistically analyzed.
into a probabilistic problem that can be estimated.
and then use that data to select the answer.
So, that's the core idea behind it.
But, this approach also had its own set of problems.
First of all, even though it works with a massive amount of text corpora,
It was able to count,
For example, it could count how many times a word appeared, and things like that.
So, it does recognize some words.
and how many times the word 'cat' appears.
and which words it's likely to appear together with.
But the thing is, these words are all just treated as separate entities with no real connection between them.
So, even after all that training, the model still has no idea.
So, "cat" and "dog" might be considered more similar.
whereas the difference between a cat and a refrigerator is huge.
It can only work by counting frequencies.
It didn't truly understand language.
So, as we know, the core of NLP is that you have to understand language before you can process it.
and then it can start generating content on its own.
Right?
So, from that perspective,
the statistical or machine learning capabilities were quite limited.
So, what's next?
So, the question we were asking was, how can we get computers to process language more effectively?
So, if you want a computer to process language,
But first, there's a fundamental premise we need to understand.
You see, computers can't actually understand every single word in a natural language.
or every single Chinese character.
We have to convert these words into something
into numbers that a computer can understand.
So, how exactly do we represent this? How do we turn it into these numbers?
In the data processing for machine learning,
we've already touched upon this.
So, in that case, we take some of the data and...
For example, let's say it's a category.
So, what category does it belong to?
or, say, locations.
So, for these enumerable text features, like Beijing, Shanghai, Guangzhou...
So, we use one-hot encoding for that, right?
So, why not just use numbers?
Because, when it comes to machine learning training,
For example, if you represent Beijing, Shanghai, and Guangzhou with the numbers 1, 2, and 3 respectively,
For a machine,
One is less than two,
and two is less than three.
But in reality, there's no such relationship between these three locations.
So, we can't express it like this.
So, we can't just use plain numbers.
So, what does one-hot encoding do?
So, let's say we have three or more words.
So, I'm not going to encode each word as just 1, 2, or 3.
This would imply that there's some kind of ordering relationship between them.
Instead, I use a vector for each one.
So, for example, let's say this vector is 10,000 zeros.
Let's say, a 10,000-dimensional vector.
So, which one is it?
Take 'football' for example.
So, the second one, for basketball,
The third one, the refrigerator.
and for the fourth one, there's a single one.
and the rest are all zeros.
All you have to do is see which one is a one,
and you'll know what it represents.
And that's why it's called 'one-hot', right?
Only one of them is 'hot'.
and all the rest are just zeros.
In this scenario,
So, for a computer,
As we've mentioned before,
it can then process all these texts without any discrimination.
And just like that, the text is represented.
But in the context of L2P,
Now, the sheer volume of vocabulary we might encounter...
the number of words will be far, far greater than just a few categories or locations.
Before, maybe we could get by with a ten-dimensional vector.
a 100-dimensional vector would be enough.
But when it comes to natural language,
you might be dealing with vectors that have 10,000, or even a million dimensions.
The advantages of this approach are actually pretty clear.
It's pretty straightforward, right?
it clearly expresses to the model
So, are these the downsides of this method?
First of all, its dimensionality is just way too high.
It's just way too inefficient with its information.
Right?
For example, you might have a million one-hot vectors, but you only use one of them at a time.
Then you've just wasted all the rest of them.
So, for the second point...
Actually, this is similar to what we just talked about.
The principle behind using numbers is kind of similar.
Although, it's not like they have a size or a ranking relationship anymore.
But there's no semantic meaning between them either.
So, let's break it down for a regular person to understand.
So, soccer and basketball should definitely be pretty close to each other.
And the gap between this and, say, a refrigerator should be huge.
But within their 10,000-dimensional vectors,
the distance between them is pretty much the same.
Or, even if they're different,
but it couldn't express how close they were either.
while semantically closer ones...
Semantically, they are different and more distant from each other.
This is something it just can't express.
And that's one of the drawbacks of the one-hot encoding.
So, after a while, through research, people also discovered that...
In fact, they also discovered that language expression actually follows certain patterns.
For example, if I say the word "football"...
Brazil might pop into your head.
It's the kingdom of soccer.
Messi is an incredible football player.
or something like the World Cup is happening right now.
is a term in soccer.
Of course, for our friends in China,
the phrase "refund my money" might also pop into their heads.
These associations show that words...
are not just isolated symbols in themselves.
So, what about the meaning of a word?
is often tied to the context it frequently appears in,
the context,
emotions,
or even cultural memories.
The meaning of a word can be determined by the words that it frequently appears with.
can be figured out.
So, in other words, words themselves have a certain distribution.
This is the distributed hypothesis.
It's not just a collection of unrelated things.
And this gave birth to a technique called embedding.
So, instead of using one-hot encoding for words,
or even just a numerical symbol to represent it.
Now, it's still data,
Instead, it uses a semantic space.
This is actually the technique known as word embedding.
And this was developed by none other than one of the legendary 'AI Big Three'.
discovered by Bengio and his team.
Later on, when it comes to natural language processing,
We'll be seeing a lot of Bengio's name.
So, what it's actually doing is, in the process of predicting the next word,
He started out by studying statistics as well.
and researching machine learning.
And gradually, it just naturally learned all these words along the way.
It doesn't need a separate, dedicated thing to represent it.
It uses a vector to represent the dimensionality of that vector.
and look at the space of the corresponding words.
But the thing is, it's a vector.
So it's not just a single number anymore.
It's likely a vector composed of multiple numbers.
So, its dimensionality is much lower than one-hot encoding.
Because it's not like only one of them has a number.
and the numbers in each of these positions are meaningful.
They are trained using machine learning.
And to this day, this technology is still in use.
It's just that a whole lot of new things have been introduced.
So, when we're learning about the Transformer,
You'll also often come across things like position embeddings.
Exactly, a word is a token embedding.
You'll come across all of these, and their origins can actually be traced right back to this.
Of course, once this idea was discovered...
But actually, it didn't catch on right away.
This continued until 2013, when the concept was finally proposed.
the proposal of Word2Vec.
So, what are words actually turned into?
Vectors, right?
So, what does it do?
So, it used a few techniques.
This also builds on the idea of embedding.
But it did propose two very simple training methods.
So, gradually, what else was it able to do?
Take the phrase 'I like to watch the game' for example.
and figure out that the word is 'football'.
But it can also work in reverse, using the word 'football' to predict all those other words.
So, based on a central word, you can predict the words that come before and after it.
Or, it could work the other way around, predicting the central word from the words on either side. Both are possible.
So, once this was discovered,
and it immediately took the world by storm.
And a classic example of this is...
And what they discovered was...
and between the vectors of the words it learned,
exhibit a kind of geometric structure for both semantics and grammar.
So, words with similar meanings are positioned closer to each other in this space.
while words that aren't as similar are farther apart.
Right, so after using Word2Vec...
For example, if you take the word 'king' and subtract 'man'...
and then you add the vector for 'woman', the result you get is surprisingly...
is incredibly close to the vector for 'queen'.
So, we can say she's now got her wings.
So, starting from today's, from the word... uh...
So, after the whole word-to-vector thing...
computers could finally grasp the semantic relationships between words.
This was a truly monumental discovery.
But it didn't immediately cause an explosion in NLP either.
But it still had one more problem.
So, embedding solved the problem of how to represent words.
But it didn't solve the problem of how sentences are structured.
For example, let's say we use embeddings.
Take, for instance, the phrases 'a dog bites a person' and 'a person bites a dog'.
is that the words that appear are exactly the same.
But for us humans, we can tell the difference in a heartbeat.
convey completely different meanings.
But for technologies like embeddings or word vectors,
But in reality, there's no difference.
Because the words that appear are exactly the same, right?
and the results I get are also the same.
But the meaning is completely different.
So, it's not enough for us to just understand individual words.
we also need the model to understand a sentence.
And sentences, well, they have a sequence.
So, pay close attention to this term: 'sequence' or 'sequentiality'.
You'll be seeing this a lot more later on.
So, how do we make it read things in order?
And this is actually the RNN.
It can read a sentence word by word.
aka, the Recurrent Neural Network.
This solved the problem of sequential data.
I watched a game on the court last night.
And in its normal state, it just keeps on reading.
So, as I'm reading,
Through the hidden state in the middle, I can remember everything I've read before.
As I keep reading, I'll eventually figure out who it is.
Do you know what time it was yesterday?
So, where are we now?
And all these things in front of the court are still there.
So, this meant it was capable of processing entire sentences.
This was a massive breakthrough.
But as we moved on,
Because with RNNs, they're okay for short sentences.
But when the sentences get longer,
Because it has to remember all the information that came before it.
So, when it comes to processing long texts,
For example, take the book written by the professor who is highly admired by the students.
was very influential.
and by the time you get to 'influential,' you've forgotten whether it's the students who are influential,
or the professor was influential.
or if the book was the one that was influential.
It's gotten so long I can't even keep track anymore.
So, later on, some further improvements were made to the RNN.
And that's what we call LSTM. Even though it was an improvement,
They added something called a 'forget gate'.
what information to remember,
and which ones you should get rid of.
Then, by 2014,
Then came the GRU.
It was essentially an improvement on the LSTM.
And the results were quite a bit better.
And then, what came next was the encoder-decoder.
the encoder,
and the invention of the decoder architecture.
And this is where you really need to pay close attention to the Transformer.
For those of you who are familiar with it,
Got it.
And the Transformer is a classic example of an architecture that uses this, right?
So, after 2014,
So, Ilya's team published the sequence-to-sequence model.
So, what was their idea?
This was a new concept.
So, you could say that, of course, its original purpose was for translation.
This essentially defines the encoder.
The way this decoder works is that the encoder reads in the text.
to read in the original text,
transforms it into an intermediate representation for the decoder.
and then translate it out.
Actually, this approach isn't just for translation tasks.
In fact, it can be used for many other tasks as well.
He believed that many NLP tasks...
In fact, even for text summarization, we use the encoder to process the text.
It reads through the entire article,
and uses it as an intermediate representation for the decoder.
and then decode it into a summary that's much shorter than the original text.
Many NLP tasks can be framed as taking a sequence as input.
and output another sequence.
So, this was actually the case for the early encoders.
The decoder's architecture, however, also had some issues.
it compresses the entire sentence into a single, fixed-length vector.
a single, long vector.
So, when it comes to the decoder,
can only rely on this compressed memory.
to generate it word by word.
the translation.
But in practice, this approach wasn't very effective.
Because when it's generating each word,
So, if we could just look back at the original text,
the most relevant parts, that would be great.
And that's the attention mechanism.
But, and this is important,
Now, this attention mechanism isn't the self-attention from the Transformer model.
And the Transformer is also built upon these foundations.
and some architectural inventions.
So, fast forward to 2014.
So basically, they introduced the attention mechanism into the RNN framework.
This allowed it to alleviate the bottleneck of fixed-length vectors.
For example, when we're translating a sentence,
The cat sat on the mat.
So, when you see the word 'cat'
So, when you see the word 'cat',
you'll see what action is happening right after it.
And when you see the action being performed,
You need to look ahead to see who is doing the action,
and look back to see the context in which it's happening.
But if you can't look back, well, that's a different story.
you just focus on what's most important to you from what came before.
And this is basically the attention mechanism.
In other words, we're constantly generating that first word.
So, when it comes to the word 'cat', you have to take a look, right?
There's not much to see for the word 'cat'.
Then, when it's time to generate the second word,
I need to see which words before it are more relevant.
But what if I had the ability,
So, if I look at the whole picture, I'll find that 'cat' is the most relevant to this word.
If it finds a match, it has to check which words...
So, it calculates this every single time.
This gives the probability of how relevant every word in the entire encoder is to it.
So it knows which words it should be paying the most attention to.
And this way, it gradually learns to pay attention to the preceding words.
It's no longer a fixed vector.
So, that's where the attention mechanism and...
So, when the decoder is generating the current word,
to find the relevant parts in the sentence input to the encoder.
to see which words it should pay the most attention to.
to pay the most attention to.
So, what about the Transformer's self-attention?
That's actually because it's decoder-only.
It's within the same sentence.
every word looks at every other word.
And this self-only approach is a perfect segue to talk about the earlier stages.
So, what about attention?
For the most part, in most applications,
They were all based on a typical encoder like RNN.
in the decoder's architectural structure, uh...
These enhancements were basically all about adding attention to RN.
And actually, the results were already pretty good.
Of course, you could also use improved versions of RNNs, like LSTM and GRU.
But at their core, these models were still fundamentally based on the RNN architecture.
So, as for the model,
They still have to process words one by one, sequentially from start to finish.
This makes parallel processing very difficult.
But what about even longer sequences?
problems would still arise.
So, could we treat attention as a language of its own?
So, what about the main architecture of the model?
And that, right there, is the biggest innovation brought by the Transformer.
And that was back in 2017.
Google's eight authors invented and published the paper on the Transformer.
And this architecture is, in fact, its most crucial component.
And that is, in fact, self-attention.
So, self-attention happens within the same sequence.
It allows every word to directly connect with every other word.
So, what this means is, when I'm looking at the word 'cat',
So, for instance, when I look at the word 'cat,' it's not like before.
I only look at the words that came before.
It pays more attention to me.
It pays attention to every single word in the entire sequence.
Take the word "it" for example.
The animal,
Didn't cross the street.
It didn't cross the street,
Because... and why is that?
He was too tired.
But what does this 'it' refer to?
Is it 'street'?
or animal?
It will then establish associations with all the words.
and see which one is the most relevant.
and it will find that the word 'animal' is the most relevant one.
Instead of making a choice for each word,
But the amount of computation has definitely increased.
And that's exactly why in the era of large models,
demands even more computing power.
But the first thing is, it can be done in parallel.
Because every word needs to be connected to every other word indiscriminately.
So, within the sentence itself,
Does every word need to be connected to every other word?
So, it can now perform computations in parallel.
And that's where the Transformer came in with its self-attention mechanism.
This also brought another major, revolutionary innovation.
This means that computational speed is no longer the bottleneck.
All you need is the computing power.
Before, models like RNNs had to process things sequentially.
as long as you have the computing power.
You still had to wait for each step, so all that computing power couldn't be used at the same time.
So, self-attention, along with its parallel processing mechanism,
This brought about a major innovation.
But with the Transformer,
and everything changed.
RNNs, on the other hand, had to process things sequentially.
You finish the first word, then you read the second one, right?
So, it's more of a sequential process, right?
But with the Transformer, all positions participate in the computation simultaneously.
This makes it much more suitable for parallel computing on GPUs or TPUs.
So, what this means is...
And it's not just about providing some small trick for a specific task, either.
In fact, it's combined with the training process,
and engineering.
It was innovative not only in its algorithmic architecture,
but it's also quite advanced from an engineering perspective.
This is what ultimately allowed it to become the foundation for all subsequent large language models.
the foundational architecture for models.
So, what came after the Transformer?
So, at this point,
as you can probably understand,
So, why is it that after the Transformer was invented,
it didn't immediately blow the world away.
The innovative points it used, almost all of them,
It wasn't as revolutionary as you might think.
groundbreaking
In fact, it was all built on the foundation laid by its predecessors.
Then, by incorporating engineering principles, they made some optimal choices and modifications.
It didn't just appear out of thin air.
And that's actually why, when it was first created,
Even Google itself didn't even recognize its value at the time.
So, what happened after the Transformer was born?
But it's not like Google was just sitting on its hands, either.
Instead, they continued to explore the field of machine translation.
But before that,
So basically, for all these different tasks,
essentially, each was training its own models.
And then, a new paradigm emerged.
And that's what's called pre-training.
So, what exactly is pre-training?
So, what about the model?
First, it learns general language patterns from massive amounts of text.
And it doesn't matter if I'm doing sentiment analysis or translation.
Basically, you just let it train.
So, once the training is done...
you just need to make a few small adjustments for the specific task at hand.
And this initial phase is what's called pre-training.
So, when we move on to specific tasks later on,
So, with this pre-trained model,
and just make a few small adjustments for the specific task at hand.
This makes the training process much, much simpler.
Of course.
Then came another major, revolutionary development.
So it's not about the embedding itself.
We're talking about simple embedding techniques, like word2vec.
The thing is, back then, every word had a fixed vector.
Because it needs context, right?
So, what about later on? What did we start using then?
And that's where ELMo came in.
So, what does it do?
The model will then dynamically generate these based on the context.
This makes the results of its embedding dynamic.
Take the word 'bank' for example.
So, in certain sentences, the words it gets embedded with...
it would be more closely associated with things related to banking and finance.
But in other contexts,
it's actually closer to things like rivers or camping.
The word itself is inherently polysemous.
This later gave rise to models like BERT.
This was also part of his work on machine translation.
But it brought about a major revolutionary update in its training process.
It will randomly mask out a word.
and masks out a portion of it.
and have it predict what should be in the middle.
But it was quickly superseded by Google's own T5.
Now, T5 was actually a pretty big revolution in NLP.
all sorts of different tasks.
I can solve them all using the same architecture.
Whether it's translation or summarization,
sentiment analysis,
I'm pretty good at all of them.
The boundaries between these tasks began to blur.
So, of course, what came next was the pre-training plus fine-tuning approach.
and quickly became the dominant paradigm in NLP.
And T5 also made a huge contribution.
And of course, the name that everyone's more familiar with is OpenAI.
And the 'GPT' in GPT stands for 'Generative Pre-trained Transformer'.
It stands for Generative, Pre-trained Transformer architecture.
So, when you look at it that way,
So, the meaning of these terms becomes pretty obvious, right?
So, what exactly is 'generative'?
This is a standard task in NLP.
It's about generative pre-training for text generation.
So, as we just explained,
So, 'Transformer' refers to the architecture it uses, right?
Of course, it simplified the Transformer architecture a bit.
It's decoder-only.
So, when we start learning about GPT, we'll find that...
So, with that foundation we've just covered,
we can pick it up pretty quickly.
And its training objective is also very simple.
Given the preceding text,
and have it continuously predict the next word.
For example, let's say you're given the phrase 'the development of natural language processing'.
It's gone from rules to you just constantly predicting.
and just keep going until I tell you to stop.
So, on the surface, it might just seem like it's completing a sentence.
Behind the scenes, its training process actually forces the model to learn grammar.
semantics,
or what kind of factual style it has.
and common patterns of reasoning.
Gradually, it could handle the entire NLP task as a whole.
So, it was no longer just for things like translation and summarization.
The question-answering tasks were designed with their own separate structures.
Actually, this was developing in parallel with T5.
Both of them made contributions.
compressing a multitude of tasks into a single training objective.
Once it understands things just like a human does,
you can naturally perform all sorts of tasks.
And so, it gradually evolved into a universal task interface.
Whether it's writing or answering questions,
writing code, or calling up tools,
it can handle all of them.
And in situations like this,
Language is no longer just the input data for a model to process.
It gradually evolved into...
a unified interface for human-computer interaction.
All you have to do is talk to the machine in natural language.
So, that's a general overview of how NLP has evolved.
So, to wrap things up,
You can see it's been a continuous exploration, constantly getting closer to the essence of language.
First, it all started with rules.
From writing all sorts of rules to the world of statistics.
Starting from symbols to represent things, from initial numeric encoding to later... well, my heart.
And then later, we had word embeddings.
using vectors to represent meaning.
Then, after gradually learning the sequence,
Then, the attention mechanism was introduced.
to dynamically let the model decide where to focus.
Then, after the Transformer was born,
And then, we moved from specialized models to general-purpose, pre-trained models.
And all of these were born.
So, the journey went from rules to statistics,
From word embeddings to attention mechanisms.
From specialized models to general-purpose large models.
Ultimately, NLP has transformed natural language into the primary interface for human-computer collaboration.
And that's the complete journey of how NLP has evolved.
So, you could say that up to this point,
So, with that said, we're not going to rush into what's next.
and jump right into the Transformer architecture.
Because when it comes to the Transformer, you could say...
Two-thirds of it is built on the foundations we've already covered.
It merely stands on the shoulders of its predecessors.
And then, it brought about a truly massive, revolutionary innovation.
So, if we really want to master the Transformer,
and we have to understand that this whole journey actually started way back with residual connections.
Residual connections are also used extensively in the Transformer.
and using normalization.
These are also some training techniques.
All of these are absolutely crucial for us to understand the Transformer.
So, moving on,
So, let's first dive into word embeddings.
So, how does it roughly work?