Over the past dozen or so lessons,
and have covered all sorts of fundamental concepts in neural networks.
We've basically mastered the ultimate weapon.
So, starting with this video,
we're going to start learning about
a framework specifically designed for computer vision tasks.
the CNN,
commonly known as Convolutional Neural Networks.
So first, let's talk about what computer vision tasks actually are.
So, computer vision is essentially about getting machines to understand images.
For us humans,
recognizing an image is a piece of cake.
But for a computer,
an image, in its essence, is just a collection of numbers.
Specifically, the RGB values corresponding to each pixel.
Now, what if we make some slight changes to the image?
For instance, if we change the angle,
adjust the lighting, or cover up a part of it.
To us, it doesn't look all that different.
So, it still seems pretty straightforward.
But for a computer,
the distribution of these pixels has changed dramatically.
it's no longer recognizable.
So, this really gets to the heart of the matter with CV, or Computer Vision.
is not about processing these pixels directly.
Instead, its core purpose is to extract meaningful information from that raw visual data.
to achieve an understanding similar to the human visual system.
judge and reason.
Its core tasks, some of the most common ones, include image classification.
Give us an image,
and ask us to figure out what the main subject in the picture is.
Then there's object detection, which, within an image,
like people, cars,
and traffic lights等各种目标标注出来。
And then there's image segmentation.
It separates the road, the sky, and the pedestrians pixel by pixel.
the detection of human faces,
This is something we use a lot.
OCR, or Optical Character Recognition, extracts text from images.
or even autonomous driving in cars.
and it's also used in image processing.
Here we have a picture of a cat.
So, what if we keep zooming in on this picture?
At first, you can still zoom in smoothly and continuously.
we'll start to see this kind of pixelated style.
or mosaic-like grid cells.
So, in reality, an image is just made up of a huge number of these tiny squares.
They are arranged one by one in a specific order.
And each of these small grids is actually a block of color.
And each one of these represents a color.
And we call this color block a pixel.
It stores the color information for that specific location in the image.
So, how do we actually represent this color?
Why is this color brown,
This is red,
This one's magenta or something like that.
So, how is this expressed?
We also often see that RGB corresponds to three numbers.
So, what are these?
So, let's take a look at how computers actually represent color.
In nature, there are countless colors.
But obviously, a computer can't just assign a unique code to every single possible color.
In reality, within a computer, color is defined by something called RGB.
—stands for Red, Green, and Blue.
These three primary colors are also known as the three primary colors.
By arranging and combining these three colors,
a vast array of colors can be produced.
Now, let's take a look at this diagram.
If it's just red light,
green light, and blue light.
and for this one, we adjust its brightness
That is, it ranges from 0 to 255.
This is a solid color.
So, what if we start to mix red and green?
it will actually create yellow.
And it's the same in the natural world.
Different combinations of these colors will produce new ones.
So, if we make all three colors fully bright,
all set to 255,
you get pure white.
It's kind of like how a rainbow works.
It's just breaking down the color white.
So this is how we put it back together.
If all three colors are dark,
and they're all zero
So what does that look like?
That would be pure black.
So, every color can be represented by these three RGB values.
And each of these numbers represents the brightness of its respective color channel.
And by combining values from 0 to 255, we can create all sorts of different colors.
For example, pure red would be 255,
And all the others are zero.
So for pure black, we just covered that it's zero.
and for black, it's all 255s.
that's white.
And if we look closely, we'll notice something.
Now, if the RGB values are all equal,
for example, all at 255,
or zero,
or maybe they're all 128, something like that.
So, you'll find that when these three color values are equal,
you'll get a shade of gray.
If all of them are zero,
then it becomes black.
And if it's all 255, it becomes white.
What if it's 121, 128?
It would be a shade of gray in the middle.
And that's a circle.
So, a computer can represent any color using just three sets of numbers.
So, that's how we process color images.
So, let's say for example, we're given a...
a 32 by 32 color image.
So, what does that mean?
So, it just means there are 32 pixels horizontally.
It doesn't matter if we're talking about the length or the width.
But that's not important.
You have 32 pixels horizontally,
And vertically, it also has 32 pixels.
And each of these pixels is represented by three values: Red, Green, and Blue, or RGB.
So, if we're processing an image on a computer,
a 32 by 32 color image,
it would be written as three channels.
the RGB channels.
where each channel is a 32 by 32 grid.
It's a two-dimensional array.
So essentially, it's a three-dimensional tensor overall.
or a three-dimensional array, and that's what we get.
But as I mentioned before, for gray-scale images...
That's because all three of its color channels are identical.
So, there's no need to distinguish between the three channels.
So you just give it a single channel.
So in this case, it's 32 by 32.
So, it can be represented by just a two-dimensional matrix.
Let's take a look.
Before, when we used the MNIST handwritten digits dataset,
So, it's essentially a grayscale image.
And the numbers on it,
represented by either white or some shade of gray in between.
So, its representation is a two-dimensional array.
Now, these numbers aren't set in stone;
It's just meant as an illustration to show how it's represented.
For instance, take the MNIST dataset we use.
are all 28 by 28.
That means there are 28 points horizontally,
and 28 points vertically.
And each of these points is represented by a numerical value, typically ranging from 0 to 1.
The darker areas gradually get larger and more resemble white.
As you can see, the center is white.
So it's pretty much the same.
So basically, that's what it means.
so we can just use one channel
Because the color values in all three channels are the same.
So, I can just use one channel to represent it.
that tells you how bright it is.
The brightest is 255.
So, we know that...
So that's why, when we were talking about MLPs,
Do you all remember?
and you might be wondering where this number 784 comes from.
So, 28 times 28 gives you 784.
This represents how many numbers are used for each pixel.
What about for a color image?
Now, we know that a color image has three channels.
We can represent this as three arrays.
forming three two-dimensional arrays.
So, it's really just a three-dimensional tensor.
This arranges them so that the top part is all red.
and the intensity values for the red channel,
the green channel,
and the blue channel.
And just like that, you get an RGB array.
and feeds it a three-dimensional array.
and that's how you get a full-color image.
But, for a 32 by 32 image,
you would then multiply that by three.
So that's a total of 3072 values.
Alright, now that we've got a handle on how images are represented,
Actually, when we were working with handwritten digits,
to have a computer recognize handwritten digits,
and we were already able to successfully recognize it using an MLP.
And if we then combine that with learning rate scheduling and parameter initialization,
normalization,
and other training optimization techniques like regularization,
the accuracy of this handwritten digit recognition,
We've already hit 98%.
So, what if I were to tweak this a bit?
to have it recognize whether there's a dog or a cat in the picture.
Or have it mark out the roads.
Wouldn't that also work?
But what about using the MLP approach?
Deep neural networks...
like, by making the network a bit deeper.
So, can it handle more complex tasks?
Actually, that doesn't work.
So, why is that?
What about for something like the MNIST dataset?
isn't too bad.
So, why is that?
Because it's a 28 by 28 grayscale image.
So, when you convert it into a matrix,
So, it has 28 rows in total,
and 28 columns, making 784 pixels in total.
So, when we process it,
What we're actually doing is flattening it.
rather than treating it as a two-dimensional object.
Because we're treating it as 784 individual features.
and feed it into the neural network.
So, from X1 to X784, it goes to the second layer.
and that's it for the third layer.
So, what about the hidden layer? Let's break it down.
So, if it only has 784 features, it's still manageable.
This is especially true for modern computers.
it can still handle it.
So overall, the number of parameters is manageable.
But what about images from the real world?
are far more complex than the images in the MNIST dataset.
So, let's start with something a little more complex.
just a bit bigger.
Let's say 32 by 32.
But... this time, it's a color image.
So, we multiply that by three,
That's about 3,072 pixel values in total.
if we design the second layer to have 512 neurons,
So, in the first layer, after we flatten this small image,
you'd just multiply that by three.
Because, you know, there are three channels.
So for a color image, that's 3072 right there.
So what if we add another hidden layer after that?
and it has 512 neurons,
Then, that would require roughly over a million parameters.
that's already
So, what if we make things a bit more complex?
Now, for the images we use today,
We often talk about...
that our pixel count is 1024 by 768.
Even 1920 by 1080 is considered quite large.
and this is just 224 by 224 pixels.
Now, for modern images, a small picture like this...
is far from being considered clear.
And since it's a color image,
So, after flattening it out...
that's already 150,000 inputs.
And if the second layer also has 512 neurons,
In fact, 512 isn't even that many compared to the first layer.
Multiply that, and you're already at seventy...
And just the first two layers alone would already require over 70 million parameters.
Now, for a computer,
especially back in the early days of computing.
This was completely infeasible.
And keep in mind, that's just for the first layer.
and if I multiply that by another layer...
Then it gets even bigger.
So there's just no way I can make it into...
a deep neural network.
It can only handle learning one or two layers at most.
So naturally, the features it learns are going to be very shallow.
So, what can we do about it?
But of course, we've only scratched the surface of its problems.
And it’s not just about having too many parameters.
Having too many parameters is just one of the problems.
They just make the training process much slower.
The strain on memory also increased.
And on top of that, if you have a limited amount of data,
For instance, let's say we don't have enough images.
let's say you only have a few tens of thousands of images
but when my model has over 70 million parameters,
So, with a model like that, it's pretty much guaranteed to overfit as soon as you start training it.
pretty much.
But actually, that's not even its biggest problem.
The MLP can't handle images at its core.
So, what's the real, deeper reason for this?
So, when it comes to images...
Well, even though images are represented in a computer as...
strings of ones and zeros, just like that.
We say it's 255, but that's just us humans converting it into a decimal number.
But an image itself isn't really just a list of independent numbers.
It has a spatial structure.
is related to the pixel in front of it,
is usually related to the pixels that come after it.
that come together to form a person.
They're not randomly distributed.
Right.
And also, think about an image.
In fact, there are a few typical characteristics.
This is called local correlation.
Its pattern only appears within a small, localized area.
It's a gradual transition.
For example, let's say this part here is black.
the surrounding area is also very likely to be black.
as purple starts to gradually appear,
the surrounding area is also purple.
They are related to each other.
Another one is translation equivariance.
Or, as it's also called, translation invariance.
Its position has changed,
the pattern itself remains unchanged.
For example, let's say we move these characters over here.
It's still the same characters.
And another property is its hierarchical structure.
So, we'll break this down together in a moment.
First, let's take a look at local correlation.
Take the meaning of a single pixel, for instance.
is mainly determined by what this pixel represents.
So, once we flatten it,
It loses all connection to its surroundings.
But in reality, the relationship a pixel has with its neighbors is extremely important.
Let's try to recognize something.
For example, say we have this picture of a dog.
We can tell that...
For example, when we're looking at this part here,
and we can tell right away.
This is the dog's eye.
It's what's right next to it that helps us make that identification.
Or take the dog's paw, for instance.
So, for instance, does this part of the image affect our ability to recognize the dog's eye?
Not at all. It has no effect whatsoever.
It's only related to the local area around it, its immediate surroundings.
or its nose and mouth.
and it's also connected to the global information.
or the grass next to it.
its legs,
don't really help us much in identifying the eyes.
For example, if we take images from the natural world,
And it's actually the same for all of them.
We can see right away, this is an edge.
And this one is a corner.
It doesn't matter what's next to it.
And this one, that would be animal fur.
And this one looks like it's part of a leaf.
And this right here is the wheel.
Actually, it's related to the car's window,
or this glass, this is a door handle.
realistically, all you need to do is look at the local area.
Pixels that are far away don't really have much to do with it.
But in an MLP, we establish full connections.
essentially, it makes every single pixel relate to all the others.
But in the context of images, that's really not necessary.
This leads to an explosion in the number of parameters.
So, what's the second point?
translation equivariance.
And as I briefly mentioned with that example a moment ago...
the same local pattern
appearing in the top-left corner or the bottom-right corner of an image
essentially, it's the same pattern.
Only their position has changed.
So really, it doesn't need to learn a separate pattern for every single position.
there's no need to train a whole new detection pattern for it.
For example, let's say we have an image of a kitten.
In the top-left corner of the image, we've successfully identified it.
And that it's a cat.
And that actually affects the entire image.
This is called a feature map.
We'll get to that in a moment.
This area is highlighted,
This indicates there's a cat in this region.
The rest of the areas remain dark.
This means there's nothing significant in the rest of the areas.
This can be interpreted as a filter.
For example, let's take a thermal imaging scenario.
Let's say this area has some heat signal.
Only this specific spot lights up, while other areas without heat remain dark.
So, this is what image recognition is all about.
or, you could say, some of the fundamental techniques for signal recognition.
You can also call it pattern detection, or a 'detector', things like that.
So, what about the second picture?
I just need to move the kitten to the bottom-right corner.
it's still the same kitten.
So, I don't actually need to build a whole new detector for that, right?
So, whether we call it a convolutional kernel or a filter later on,
Right, they're just all sorts of signal waves.
There's no need for that.
As long as these two are the same, it'll work.
All I need to do is detect...
In fact, you can just use the same thing to detect it.
It only needs to process this small section, and that's it.
But, if you were to use a fully connected network,
you actually have to recognize the entire thing.
and now everything in this block is different.
This results in a huge waste of parameters.
And the third is the hierarchy of high-level semantics within an image.
In fact, it's not generated by a single pixel.
Instead, they are constructed gradually from low-level visual patterns.
So, in general,
We'll also cover this when we get to the low-level details later on.
So, when we try to recognize images,
Although we aren't consciously aware of this process,
But this is what's actually happening.
At first, all we see is this vague, patchy area.
an idea of what it is.
and gradually starts to make out the textures and edges.
and then you can start to make out the different parts.
And gradually, these parts can actually be pieced together into a whole.
In fact, this principle applies to human visual nerves, which are, after all, those of mammals.
The visual nerve works in exactly the same way.
So, at the lower layers, if we process it layer by layer...
At the shallow layers, it primarily looks for some local features.
As we go deeper, it gradually abstracts the features, creating a higher-level representation.
So, if we take this cat's face, an MLP just can't solve these problems.
It flattens the image into a one-dimensional vector.
This completely ignores the local correlations within the image.
Because originally, all the pixels were right next to each other.
once you flatten it out,
so any relationship between them is basically lost.
This completely destroys the image's spatial structure.
If we truly want to process images,
So, how do we go about recognizing images?
What we truly need is something that's well-suited for images.
a network for these kinds of tasks.
one that can adapt to the unique characteristics of images themselves.
And that's exactly what a Convolutional Neural Network, or CNN, is all about.
Its core philosophy can be summed up in one single sentence.
So, why is that?
First, you look at the local parts.
and then gradually piece together the bigger picture. So, what does that mean?
Let's take a look.
Of course, this concept wasn't just pulled out of thin air.
In fact, this idea goes way back to the 1950s.
neuroscientists had actually already...
while studying the visual cortex of cats,
and they discovered a certain pattern.
You see, the visual cortex has a massive number of neurons.
But it turns out, these neurons don't just light up for any image they see.
to respond to.
It's only certain neurons,
For instance, some neurons will only respond when they encounter a vertical line.
that it will have a strong reaction.
But when it comes across horizontal lines in an image,
it barely responds at all.
So, if we were to explain this using a neural network...
So after it goes through the activation function,
basically means it doesn't output anything.
But for others, let's say, they are highly sensitive to diagonal lines.
So when you show it a diagonal line like this,
it's not sensitive to it at all.
And of course, these two researchers also made a breakthrough based on this principle.
And later on, they both won the Nobel Prize for it.
In essence, this is what's known as a local receptive field.
In other words, it also only looks at a small patch.
it only focuses on a small patch.
whether there are horizontal or vertical lines,
What kind of textures are there?
Now, this is just a simple example to illustrate the point.
and it's being processed layer by layer.
And what about this one?
This actually also influenced how later generations tackled computer vision tasks.
So, I'll start by just looking at a small patch.
and then the deeper layers will take these small pieces and combine them,
to abstract even higher-level features.
And then combine those even further.
and gradually, it all starts to make sense.
And that's pretty much how a CNN works, too.
Of course,
In the early days,
Neuroscientists pretty much always use cats' eyes for their experiments.
So, that's why in a lot of educational content about computer vision,
love to use cats as examples.
And it's not just because their eyes are big.
Or maybe it's because our real-life "Hakimi" also played a huge role in this.
and helped kick-start our understanding of neural networks.
So, what's the basic principle we use in neural networks?
It acts as a small filter,
or a small detector.
And we call this a convolution kernel.
And what's inside it is really just a bunch of numbers.
For example, let's say I want to identify vertical lines.
so that they're all the same for the vertical ones.
This is a 3x3 matrix of numbers.
We'll have it move from the top-left corner all the way over here.
and just keep letting the convolution kernel scan across it.
And with each scan, it's interacting with the image itself.
Because, as we know, every single pixel has its own...
and that number represents the pixel's color intensity.
Let's have them perform a convolution operation.
This mathematical operation is known as convolution.
So, this scanning process is essentially what happens after we perform the convolution operation.
into a single number.
So, for this number...
So, each of these convolution kernels represents a specific pattern.
For example, one might represent the ability to recognize vertical lines.
If it detects a larger number,
it will make this section appear brighter.
But if the number is smaller,
it will make the corresponding area slightly darker.
a high response
This is just like the visual neurons we saw earlier in a cat's brain.
The process is very similar.
So, with this particular feature,
Of course, we can use a whole lot of these convolutional kernels.
to scan the image over and over again.
And as we all know,
As we know, a color image is made up of three channels: RGB, right?
So, we'd basically scan through this image three times.
But in reality, mathematically speaking,
It's a computation on a three-dimensional matrix.
Actually, it doesn't even need three passes; it can be computed in just one.
But for our purposes, we can understand it as operating on the three channels,
the computation is performed by scanning through the R, G, and B channels separately.
And after the calculation is done,
So, it takes this image, an image of a little cat,
Then, in the first layer, it gets transformed into something like this.
Showing us which areas are sensitive to vertical lines.
and which parts are not sensitive to vertical lines.
So, for example, let's say...
So we can interpret this area as having no vertical lines.
this section might have a lot of vertical lines.
And we call this the feature map.
Feature map.
Of course, if we use different convolution kernels, we'll get different ones.
Each convolutional kernel corresponds to one feature map.
revealing a variety of features.
And then it's passed on to the next layer for further processing.
So basically, each of these kernels is tasked with looking for a specific pattern.
Some look for vertical lines,
some for diagonal lines,
some for edges and corners,
As for the resulting feature map,
Once arranged, these can be passed as input to the next layer.
And then, the convolutional kernels in the next layer can just keep scanning them.
to perform a convolutional operation.
So, why is this CNN model so well-suited for images?
So, how exactly does this scanning process reduce the number of parameters?
Well, the core of its design really comes down to two key points.
And these characteristics perfectly align with the fundamental features of an image.
So, for this kind of data...
Image data isn't just random information.
This is data with an inherent structure.
So, we can leverage this very structure.
In fact, they do some subtraction.
removing some of that complexity.
First, it has local connections.
So, it's not like an MLP,
where every single neuron is fully connected.
This corresponds to the local correlations in an image.
neuron
So, each neuron, you can think of it as...
Or, let's just call it each convolutional kernel.
So it's not looking at the entire image anymore.
It's just a small window, say 3x3 or 5x5.
This is called the receptive...
Which, yeah, basically means its field of view.
field, or in Chinese, '感受野' (gǎn shòu yě).
I only look at my own little patch.
I just need to scan over you, and that's it.
So, are you an edge, or a texture?
This itself is determined by the neighboring pixels.
So, as I scan the image from left to right and top to bottom,
But by scanning, I can pull out all sorts of different features from you.
Some are diagonal lines like this.
Some might look like this.
of all different types.
So, what's the second point?
Parameter sharing.
This is what's known as translation invariance, or some might call it translation equivariance.
With the very same convolution kernel,
So basically, each number in this convolution kernel represents a parameter.
So, a lot of students, including myself back in the day, might know this and also wonder...
So, for different features...
So how am I supposed to know that you're all just zeros inside?
For one, it's still one.
So what numbers should we use here?
This number is also something that gets trained by the model.
But you don't need to worry about that.
All you need to do is master the techniques for parameter initialization.
As long as you initialize it properly,
and the rest will be handled by the neural network training.
So, the thing is, the patterns these different [kernels] learn...
the patterns they recognize will be different.
But when it comes to the same convolutional kernel,
it's trying to recognize that same pattern.
So, the overall architecture we're using is no longer fully connected.
So, for all the pixels in this image,
In fact, the parameters are all the same.
Because we assume that as long as it's a vertical line,
then their features are all the same.
So there's no need for me to change the parameters.
So, as you can see, this actually reduces the total number of parameters by a whole lot.
So, different kernels are essentially looking for different patterns.
Some look for horizontal features,
some look for vertical ones,
Some look for textures.
Some look for color.
The deeper the layers go,
these simple patterns are continuously combined in the later layers.
Of course, you might be thinking...
So how do you piece all that together?
You're only looking at a small patch.
So how can you possibly see the whole picture?
In fact, this layer we're talking about is what's called a convolutional layer.
and the layer that comes after it is what we call the pooling layer.
Essentially, it's about combining and aggregating that information.
Just like gathering them all into a 'pool'.
We'll also cover this in the next chapter when we introduce neural networks.
We'll get into the specific architecture of CNNs when we cover that topic.
For now, just focus on getting a general idea of how it works.
And that's pretty much how it works.
So, as we move through each subsequent layer,
I can sense it.
And then, gradually, after pooling,
and it gets bigger.
And as it gets larger,
慢慢地, I can start to figure out what you most likely are.
This is because it extracts more and more abstract features.
So, to wrap things up, let me give you a quick summary.
So, first off, let's talk about how images are actually represented in a computer.
or possibly in color.
So, a color image is essentially a three-dimensional structure, while a grayscale one is two-dimensional.
CNNs address this by preserving the spatial grid structure of the image.
instead of just treating it as a pool of unrelated data.
So, why don't MLPs work in this case?
Basically, what it does is take an image's pixels
and the relationships between them.
that spatial structure is completely lost.
completely flattening it out.
This leads to a massive explosion in the number of parameters.
Plus, the spatial relationships are completely lost.
So, the solution is to use local connections instead.
namely, massive full connectivity.
So, what are the inherent patterns within the image itself?
So, these are the three principles.
So, for the design of a CNN...
To address this, it uses a convolution kernel to continuously scan the image.
In essence, it performs convolutions to calculate the features.
in an attempt to abstract features from it.
But these aren't features that humans can readily understand.
We're just using examples like vertical, horizontal, or diagonal lines, and edges.
In reality, after training the neural network,
and you have no idea what the features it identifies actually mean.
The point is, as long as it undergoes massive amounts of computation,
and that seems to be good enough.
This is somewhat similar to our deep neural networks.
You don't know what the parameters are either,
So, what's the deal with, say, 1e-7 in the parameters of each neuron?
But the general idea is that after all sorts of permutations and combinations,
and it'll spit out the corresponding result for you.
So why do we need CNNs in the first place?
Well, it's really about the structure of the model.
it should align with the structure of the data.
So, what this means is, it performs a local perception.
and reused the parameters within the convolutional kernels.
It preserves the image's spatial structure, abstracting it layer by layer.
In other words, we're dealing with a specific data structure.
So, our fully connected MLP has been modified slightly.
It is still a deep network,
It still processes the network layer by layer.
This is all fundamental knowledge we've covered before, right?
All of this remains the same.
It's just that, to handle this special structure,
for special data structures,
we also need to make special adjustments to our networks.
to process it.
So, with that understanding,
we'll realize that
So we really do need to design a network structure for the model.
and make some adjustments
to better recognize images.
So, in this lesson, we'll just be giving a brief introduction.
So, why does it work?
But... how does it actually work?
how it's done step by step.
How the convolution works,
and how it performs pooling.
and how it makes identifications.
So, what's that all about?
We'll save a detailed discussion of this for the next video.
so you can all understand exactly how a CNN works.