Now, let's implement the simplest neural network in code.
The reason we're adding this section
The reason is that the material we've covered so far has been mostly theoretical.
and we haven't really gotten our hands dirty with any actual practice.
you might not get that hands-on feel.
And another thing is,
Plus, I've seen a lot of discussions online about deep learning.
Some think it takes a week,
You can't possibly learn it all in just a week or two.
And another thing is, most of the time, people just can't understand it.
And it's not because you don't understand its API.
The real reason is that you don't understand the various principles behind neural networks.
The truth is, you don't really understand why it has to be written this way.
So, in this lesson,
So, let's take a look at what we've learned in the previous sections.
and how it's actually implemented in code.
So, what have we been covering in the last three sections?
So, really, everything from the perceptron to backpropagation...
All of that was just theory.
So, when you actually put them all together,
And that's pretty much everything there is to training a neural network.
All that's left is to write the code.
We've learned about forward propagation and activation functions.
and loss functions.
and we've also covered gradient descent.
and then backpropagation.
And really, this whole thing is just these four steps repeating in a loop.
And that's basically the entire process of training a neural network.
Whether it's the simplest image recognition task we're covering today,
And this holds true even for training GPT—no exceptions.
So, for today's task,
So, we're going to take these four steps and write the code to put them all together.
and show you how a neural network actually works.
Specifically, we're going to build a two-layer MLP from scratch.
Its task is to recognize handwritten digits.
And now, let's draw a number on the screen.
and have the model perform real-time recognition.
Of course, in reality, just two layers aren't enough to guarantee its accuracy.
This is just a quick demonstration for you all.
So, first things first, what we need to do in our code is...
So, here's what we'll be doing.
Let's take a look at what the MNIST dataset actually looks like.
and how to write the code for it.
First, we're going to write it out from scratch, the most basic way.
and you'll get a real feel for it.
In fact, it's perfectly normal if you don't understand all the code along the way.
If you don't understand the fundamentals of deep learning,
you still wouldn't be able to understand the code.
And finally, let's put it all together and have it recognize a hand-written digit.
Let's see how the model we trained performs at recognition.
Now, the code we've written is pretty simple, I'll admit.
But in fact, this was the very foundation of the CNN that Yann LeCun developed back in the day.
Later on, it was used to implement systems for banks to recognize the amounts on checks.
and the automatic sorting of postal codes.
and the recognition of answer sheets.
And all of these applications are powered by it.
First, let's get to know the dataset we'll be using today, MNIST.
You could call it the 'Hello World' of deep learning or computer vision tasks.
Hello world.
It's a collection of handwritten digits.
And they're all in black and white.
28 by 28.
So, for an image of this size, it can represent the digits from 0 to 9.
It consists of over 60,000 training samples and more than 10,000 test samples.
So, it's actually pretty small.
It can be run on a CPU in just a few dozen seconds.
And you don't even need a graphics card. Let's take a quick look at the dataset we'll be using today.
First, let's import the necessary dependencies.
and set up the random number generator.
and set up support for Chinese characters.
Because the format of the images we're reading in...
This format is slightly different from what we need for our deep learning training.
So, we'll define a transform.
to perform some transformations on the images.
This involves two operations.
The first one is to_tensor.
So, what does it do?
Computers represent colors using numbers from 0 to 255.
And it uses three of them to represent that.
That's the RGB system.
But in the world of deep learning,
So, we want to perform calculations using numbers between 0 and 1.
And they're floating-point numbers.
This just makes the calculations a lot more convenient.
Otherwise, uh, the numbers would be just way too big.
So, we'll use `.to_tensor()` to do this conversion.
So we'll just divide them by 255.
After we've done this conversion,
There's one more thing we need to do.
Because, by default, the images we read in...
is generally composed of the image's height, width, and the number of channels.
And since our images are grayscale,
so it probably has just one channel.
But if it were a color image,
then you'd have the three RGB channels, right?
We need to transform it so that the channel comes first.
then the height,
and finally, the width.
So that's exactly what the 'to tensor' function does for us.
And that's one more step.
and that is normalize.
So, what does 'normalize' do?
Basically, it's to standardize these distributions.
And on top of that, it uses two really weird numbers.
These numbers are constants that are widely used in the industry.
So, why do we need to do this?
In fact, this step is called normalization.
in the later chapters.
We'll dive into the reasons behind this normalization process in detail.
And sometimes it's P.
and sometimes it's by layer.
This makes the training process more stable.
and converge faster.
But it's not a must, either.
But the training process will be much slower.
Alright, so for our dataset, we're going to use torchvision's datasets.MNIST.
and download it.
We'll download the training set and the test set separately.
Alright, once the download is complete,
Of course, we're going to apply some transforms.
and we've already applied the transformations to them.
Next, let's define the data loader.
and load them into the data loader.
and split it into specific patches.
Remember when we talked about the gradient...
Remember the concept of 'batch' from when we talked about gradient descent and optimizers?
Training it all at once is incredibly difficult.
So, we break it down into some smaller patches.
This is to shuffle the data.
Basically, we just need to shuffle the order.
So, that's basically what we're doing here.
So, let's take a look.
So, for our training set, we're actually working with over 60,000 images.
and a 10,000-sample test set.
And each image is actually a...
So, the number of channels is just one.
Because they're black and white.
Both the height and width are 28.
So that's the size of it.
So, let's grab nine samples and take a look.
Let's grab nine samples from this dataset.
and plot them out.
Let's see what it looks like.
Alright, as you can see,
So, it's got a label.
or its Y-value.
So, we can interpret this as the number five.
So, what this means is that the input is a five.
Since these are handwritten digits,
And the label is zero, four.
So, it basically looks something like this. Alright.
Alright, so let's take a look at how we can write the training loop from scratch.
So, we'll just build a very basic two-layer MLP, and that'll do the trick.
So, first off, how many features are in our input?
It's 784.
So, where does this 784 come from?
That's because it's a 28 by 28 grayscale image.
So, we need to flatten it.
Because I'm going to turn it into a 784-dimensional vector.
This means it has 784 features.
So each pixel is a feature.
So, for our input layer,
already has 784 neurons.
And in between, we have a hidden layer.
And for this hidden layer, what about the activation function?
So, what does ReLU do?
First, we perform a linear transformation.
and then apply a non-linearity.
So, what about the linear transformation?
So, we just need one parameter, plus...
So all you need is one weight and one bias.
And then we move on to the output layer.
And then, we perform another linear transformation on the output layer.
Which is also a parameter, actually.
a weight.
so that it outputs a 10-dimensional logit vector.
These correspond to the ten digit classes.
But we haven't applied the softmax function yet.
So, it's not the probability for each class just yet.
So, let's do a quick calculation.
And that's roughly the scale we're looking at.
In reality, even for a simple two-layer...
So as you can see, the number of parameters is already this large.
This is actually the key to understanding when we get to CNNs.
So, why can't we just use a neural network directly?
This is the most basic neural network there is.
The number of parameters is just exploding.
And the images are so tiny to begin with.
And it's already got this many parameters with just two layers.
So why not some other numbers in between, right?
There are 128.
So why not 256 or 64?
There's no particular reason for that.
First off, we're always using powers of two.
As long as it runs, we're good.
So today, what we're mainly interested in is what the training process actually looks like.
The point isn't to fine-tune it to perfection.
Alright, to really optimize it, we'll need the knowledge we'll cover later on.
So, what we're really doing boils down to these four steps.
Regardless of the type of training,
It's always these four.
So, first, let's define how the forward propagation works.
How do we get from the input layer to the hidden layer,
and how it gets to the output layer.
Let's define the loss function we used in the last lesson.
Let's see just how big the gap is between them.
Then, we just do backpropagation and update the gradients.
So that's basically how it's done.
Alright, let's get back to the code. The handwritten version is just these four steps.
So, let's do a quick recap together.
So, our input layer has 784 neurons, and for the hidden layer...
and we used 128 neurons.
And don't get too hung up on this 128 number.
And the output layer has ten neurons.
Because, you know, we have ten classes to classify.
So, the input and output layers are both fixed.
Now, for the hidden layer, you can actually set it to have any number of neurons you want.
Alright, let's take a look at the code.
And uh, let's also set the random seed.
Alright, let's go ahead and initialize our parameters.
So, during initialization,
We also used some... rather peculiar numbers here.
In fact, these aren't just completely random numbers.
Now, as for why we do it this way...
We'll also have a dedicated chapter on this later on.
specifically about some techniques for parameter initialization.
For now, all you need to know is that you use this number.
We'll understand what 'requires_grad' is for later on.
I need you to calculate the gradients for me.
First, you need to keep track of the computation process for the forward propagation.
This makes calculating the gradient much easier, right?
So we have W1 and B1 for the first layer, and then W2 and B2 for the second layer.
for the output layer, right?
So, we're going to put these four parameters into an array.
Let's just jot down a number.
Now, let's define the learning rate.
So for now, let's set the learning rate to 0.1.
There's not much logic to it, really.
It's just a value we're defining ourselves.
in the later chapters
We'll also cover how to set the learning rate for maximum efficiency.
Let's print it out.
As you can see, we have a whole bunch of parameters here.
So, let's take a look at the process we've written.
We'll have it train for five epochs.
You can pronounce this word however you like.
Epoch.
What's that? 'Watch'?
You can pronounce it however you like.
But pronouncing it as 'epoch' is probably what most people will understand.
So, what exactly is an 'epoch'?
Basically, it means taking all 600,000 images in the training set...
to go through them all completely.
But, as we mentioned in the last lesson when we were talking about gradient descent,
as I've mentioned to you all before,
If you were to train on the entire dataset in one go,
computing the gradient again is actually incredibly slow.
So, we usually use mini-batches.
So, we can set it to, say, 128 images.
and process them as a batch to calculate the gradient once.
Alright, let's take a look at these five epochs.
So, we're going to keep track of the loss from each training session.
And, uh, let's also keep track of the accuracy for each round.
We'll do five loops here, which will make it easier to plot the results later.
First, let's initialize the starting loss to zero.
Alright, as you can see,
So, what exactly is inside our training set?
So, 'B' here actually stands for 'batch'.
So, what is this 'X'? It's our input features.
And Y, well, that's our label, which tells us the actual value.
So, the shape of X is basically something like this.
Because each batch has 128 samples, right?
It has a single channel, with a height of 28.
by 28 wide.
and 28 wide.
So Y is really just a 128-dimensional vector.
the data for that row.
Each one tells you what its value is.
So, what exactly is its classification?
Okay, so, first things first, we need to take our one-dimensional vector.
So, we need to take this image and transform it into a...
a 784-dimensional data point.
Because it's 28 by 28, right?
Now, let's take a look at the hidden layer.
So, this is the input layer.
Now, let's look at the hidden layer.
So, the hidden layer is where we perform a linear combination of the inputs.
And the multiplication of vectors is just matrix multiplication.
So, this notation right here, it's just X times W1.
and then we add B1.
And after that,
And then, we'll apply a non-linearity using ReLU.
You'll most likely have no idea what this means.
But if we have learned it,
So, we've previously covered some of the basics about neural networks.
You can tell just by looking at it.
So, what this really is, is after the linear part.
and wrap it with a non-linear activation function.
And just like that, we can get our result.
Right?
So, what is this?
And for the output layer...
So, the result from your input layer, isn't that going to be the input for the output layer?
into the input for the next layer.
So, this H here is the result we've calculated.
Then, we take this result and multiply it by the weights of the output layer.
and then add the bias.
We're not going to apply the softmax transformation here.
Because, back when we were covering the section on loss functions,
we've covered this before.
So, what does it do for you automatically?
You don't have to do the softmax yourself.
So, we just need to keep the original logits output as is.
And then, we'll, uh, set up the loss function for our network.
Because this is a classification problem.
We've already covered the section on loss functions.
So what if it's a regression problem?
So what do we use?
So, for regression problems,
we can just use MSE.
So, for classification problems...
And then, we can move on to backpropagation.
So, we won't be walking you through writing this line by line.
and that's the calculation process for backpropagation.
Because, as we specified earlier when setting up the parameters,
as I mentioned,
I need the gradients.
During the forward pass, it will just temporarily store the intermediate results.
This way, when I define the backpropagation,
In fact, it will automatically calculate it for us.
and apply gradient descent.
So for now, let's not use an optimizer either.
First, let's write out the gradient descent process ourselves.
So, during gradient descent,
This means we don't have to rebuild the computation graph all over again.
So, we just need to use 'with torch.no_grad()'.
Then, we'll take out each of the parameters inside.
So, what exactly is parameter updating?
So the parameter is equal to the parameter...
and then add its negative, uh...
The negative gradient times the learning rate, right?
So basically, it's the parameter minus, uh...
So, just multiply the learning rate by its gradient, and that's it.
So, we need to zero out the gradients.
So in practice, we calculate the gradient using just one batch each time.
And that's everything.
without moving on to the next batch.
Actually, this is to prevent the data volume from getting too large.
You can't process it all at once.
So each calculation is like doing ten calculations for you at once.
So, when it's time to calculate the gradient for the final time,
But in our case, we calculate it once per batch.
So we just need to zero it out.
So, looking at all this code, right?
So, if we understand the process of backpropagation,
and understand the process of gradient descent,
it's actually very easy to understand.
Right?
But if you're just looking at it from a purely syntactic point of view,
But you could look up what this line of code actually means.
But the code used in these three lines is actually very, very simple.
If you don't understand gradient descent, you won't be able to follow this at all.
And let's keep a record of all the historical losses.
So, how many samples did we use?
Let's add that up.
So, let's see, the average loss times the number of samples.
Shouldn't we divide that by the number of samples?
So, that gives us the average loss, right?
So, to evaluate it, we just need to run it through one more round.
So, let's see what we've got here.
So, what's going on here?
Let's run a forward pass on the test set.
Let's calculate our accuracy to see what it's roughly at.
All of this is for the plotting we'll do later.
Basically, we're just using the results we've just calculated to make a prediction.
Let's make a prediction each time.
and see what the final accuracy will be.
We can see it's run for a few epochs.
As for the loss in each round...
And as you can see, the loss is also gradually decreasing.
And our prediction accuracy is also gradually improving.
Let's plot the curve to see how it looks.
And you can see,
This shows how it changes over the number of training epochs.
So, each of these dots represents one full training epoch.
So basically, it's just running through all 60,000 data points once.
So, what's the approximate loss going to be?
And by the fifth round,
the loss is already very small.
And this here is the accuracy.
In the first round, the accuracy was around 94-point-something percent.
just under 95%.
And by the fifth round,
In fact, the accuracy has already reached 97%.
That's super high, right?
As we can see from our slides,
So, this is basically the process we were talking about.
So, what's next?
Actually, we used a specific initialization technique here.
We'll get into that later on.
So this is the code for each round of our training.
We've just gone over all of this in the code.
Now, there are a few details here.
Let me also mention this.
Do not add softmax to the output layer.
And why is that?
So, about what I was just saying...
It will handle that on its own.
So, we don't need to do that in the neural network itself.
Because at the input layer, our network only sees each feature individually.
each one is a single feature.
Right?
Our data is in a 28 by 28 grid.
But that won't work.
So, we need to flatten it.
converting it into 784 input features.
So, why is that?
So, that 'T' is actually... uh... right at this step.
So, when we're actually updating the parameters, we don't need the gradients anymore, right?
The parameter update itself doesn't need to build the computation graph.
So, this step is really just to save memory.
So, what's the point of clearing it to zero?
It takes the gradients,
But in reality, we're computing the gradient once per batch.
So, that batch is done.
so we don't need to do it next time.
So we need to zero it out.
This is something you won't really encounter in theoretical studies.
So, we need to combine the two a bit.
But that's the kind of thing you can just look up.
Another thing is, what is this 'background' line doing here?
Basically, it's calculated by tracing back along our forward propagation.
This is the chain rule for differentiation, applied backward through the computation graph.
and calculate the gradients layer by layer.
So, this is basically it.
Basically, the auto-grad does it for us, so we don't have to do it ourselves.
So, when we talk about the backpropagation process,
and all that complex mathematical derivation.
And the result we get is exactly the same as the conclusion we just reached.
So, this is really just a review of what we've covered in the last three lessons.
and apply what we've learned from the previous lessons.
So, it's actually capable of performing some simple tasks.
So, let's just rewrite the entire code from scratch.
But we were still writing most of it from scratch.
These features can make our code a whole lot simpler.
Besides, the network we have here is just way too simple.
But if we were to write out complex networks by hand like this,
the code would actually be really hard to understand.
So, how do we write that?
In reality, it becomes incredibly simple.
First, let's write a class, SimpleMLP.
We'll have it inherit from nn.Module.
So, once we've done that,
So, let's see what it does.
So, what did we do in the initialization part?
So, what we're actually doing is quite simple.
This means we don't have to manually set the parameter initialization ourselves.
It already has some default values.
But for now, we've just defined the first layer, FC1.
So, what does the first layer actually do?
So, it's basically a linear layer with 784 inputs.
and 128 outputs.
And the second layer? That's our hidden layer.
and 128 inputs.
And these ten outputs are what feed into our output layer.
Right?
And that's just because it's a linear layer, right?
So, we just need to write it out.
And that's it.
This is for the two parameters: how many... how many features we have.
the number of features and the number of outputs.
And just like that, we're done.
It's super simple.
Next, let's define the 'forward' method, which is the forward propagation process.
Alright, so first things first.
So, after we've flattened all the features,
So, for the ReLU, we're just calling its method on the first layer.
and wrap it with ReLU.
And then we'll set up the second layer.
And for the second layer, there's no activation function.
It's just a linear function.
And just call it.
And then we just return the result.
It's the same as before.
Let's set the random seed.
This is the same thing.
Let's instantiate the model.
Now, let's define the optimizer.
In fact, let's take a look.
Now, even though we've written SGD here,
But by default, it's actually mini-batch SGD.
Let's pass all the parameters in.
As for the learning rate, let's just set it manually to 0.1.
So, what's its loss function?
First, we'll import the necessary modules, and then we're ready for the training process.
For the training process, all you have to do is call model.train().
This is actually the one we just wrote by hand.
So, during that process...
So, let's see how we actually write the code to use it.
So, let's go ahead and call our optimizer.
Let's zero out the gradients.
Then, let's calculate the model's output.
Now, let's calculate the loss.
Then, we'll calculate the loss.
and calculate the loss using the loss function.
And calling `.backward()` on the loss is how we perform backpropagation.
So, once backpropagation is done,
Then, we use the optimizer, which is gradient descent, to take a step.
and step-by-step, we update our parameters.
And then we just need to add up the loss.
So, as you can see, it's done in just four lines of code.
And with that, we've pretty much implemented all four of the processes we talked about earlier.
Alright, let's print out the final result.
As you can see, the results are pretty much the same as what we got earlier.
But our parameter initialization is a bit different.
So, that's why the results might be slightly different.
But in the end, it all works out.
And besides, for every line of code in there, if you're just learning the syntax...
The syntax itself is all pretty simple.
So, it's all just a bunch of function calls, right?
So what's so hard about it?
But the real challenge is understanding what's actually happening in this step.
This is all covered in the theoretical part of deep learning.
The sheer amount of syntax is just overwhelming.
There's just no way you can memorize it all.
You can just look it up when you need it.
So, what you really need to learn is the theory behind deep learning.
Alright, let's go back to our slides and look at this table.
First off, we have the declaration of the parameters.
that we had to define ourselves.
And we also defined an array to store all those parameters.
We've written our own initialization parameters.
And basically, that's all it takes to get it done.
It's incredibly simple.
As for collecting the parameters,
It automatically collects all of them from model.parameters().
So, when it comes to clearing the gradients,
Writing it this way is actually pretty much the same.
The only difference is that with an optimizer, we just call `.zero_grad()` and we're done.
As for updating the parameters,
we also have to write the parameter update process ourselves.
But if we use an optimizer,
we're using gradient descent.
You can just call optimizer.step() and you're good.
If you use different optimizers inside it,
Its computation method is different.
Right?
We've covered some very complex topics in our discussions on gradient descent and optimizers.
the calculation process for AdamW.
But that's not the case here.
It's still just this one line.
This part here is for moving the data to the device.
Actually, if we use some devices,
a GPU or something like that.
This also allows for better support.
So, at the end of the day, there's nothing really new here.
It's just that the computations are simpler, that's all.
Alright, let's move on and take a look at our training process.
And now for the results of the training.
and use a little drawing board to test it out.
and have the model make a prediction for us.
Alright, let's get back to the code and take a look.
So, our model is now trained.
Alright, so let's put this model to the test.
So, for our first application,
Let's randomly pick a few images from our test set.
and have the model figure out what number it actually is.
If the green guess is correct,
Because we have the labels.
And we'll know if it guessed correctly or not.
This part is pretty simple.
And this is the most important part.
Alright, let's use the model to get the result.
Let's see what we get after running it through softmax.
Let's see what we get.
We just need to know which class has the highest probability.
Alright, let's see the results of our execution.
So that's a zero.
This one's a six.
As you can see,
So, the model has a 97% accuracy rate.
So, it gets the prediction right pretty much every time.
Alright, let's do a quick demo and draw one right here.
Alright, let's draw a handwritten digit.
Alright, let's test the model and see how it does.
Let's have the model make a prediction.
So, this is actually something you need to pay attention to when you're drawing.
Make sure you draw the number big and in the center.
And the strokes should be thick.
That's because the data in the MNIST training set all looks like this.
If you don't draw it very well,
the training accuracy will be lower.
So, let's go ahead and give it a test run.
If the recognition isn't accurate,
And don't be surprised if it does.
Well, the first reason is the MNIST dataset itself.
The images in it have all been pre-processed.
The digits are all centered.
Plus, the strokes are quite thick.
But our own handwriting can't guarantee that.
And second, the code we wrote is for a two-layer MLP.
And we haven't done any optimization either.
So the training itself isn't going to be that accurate to begin with.
Alright, so to run this...
So, we need to install a package.
Alright, with that package installed, we can take a look.
Let's run this code.
There's not much to say about this code.
If you're interested,
Just go ahead and run it on your own.
Alright, let's see the result. We've handwritten it like this.
So, it's probably a four.
Right?
Let's see what it comes up with.
And the probability for four is... yep.
A bit bigger.
And it's also thinking this might be a seven.
A 44% accuracy rate, huh.
Let's clear it.
Let's try predicting another one.
For example, let's say we write a three in the corner.
So, in a case like this, there's a high chance it'll get the prediction wrong.
Because it's too far off to the side.
See, it's because it's not centered.
And it's not thick enough, either.
So when it predicts a seven, it's wrong.
So, for example, we can make this a really big one.
Let's have it make a prediction.
So it's 99% sure it's a one.
So that's pretty straightforward.
Let's write a... say, an eight.
But the eight we've drawn here is a little bit weird, though.
Let's have it make a prediction.
I bet it'll get this one right, too.
Because this one still looks pretty much like an eight.
And the number eight doesn't really look that much like the others.
As you can see,
So, it's 95% an eight.
And there's also a chance it's a five.
But overall, it's still pretty fun.
Right?
So, that pretty much covers the main points we wanted to go over.
So, let's take a look back.
In fact, we've used a lot of empirical values in many places without really explaining them.
But why?
This is just to give you a heads-up that we'll be covering this later.
And that's exactly what we'll be covering in the upcoming lessons.
So, how do we actually fine-tune the model we're going to talk about?
And seeing this example should make it easier for everyone to understand.
So, all this code we're writing...
For example, let's just use the default learning rate of 0.1.
So, this is just a number we've pulled out of thin air.
Actually, we can try using different learning rates.
And as a result, we'll see some changes.
So, what is the best initial learning rate?
The network only has two layers.
So, wouldn't it be better to make it deeper?
So what if we add more layers to make it deeper?
So why won't it run?
We'll cover this when we get to CNNs and, uh, Residual Networks.
We'll also touch on parameter initialization.
Let's see what happens with good parameters.
and compare it with different, poor initializations of those parameters.
and compare their effects.
And in between all that,
We also performed some normalization on the data.
and wrote down a bunch of weird-looking numbers.
So, what's all this for?
So what happens if we remove it?
We'll cover that in the normalization section.
So, that's why when we talk about things like the Transformer,
Why is there always a layer normalization process?
So, what does this layer do?
If you don't understand the fundamentals of deep learning,
and expect to understand transformers in just half an hour.
That's just not realistic.
Because you won't have a clue what its architecture is even doing.
So, what if we have fewer images for training?
so we don't have that many.
So, what's the solution?
So, can we make the training process any smarter?
So, we can move on to learning about regularization.
Now, even though we've already covered L1 in machine learning,
and L2 regularization.
and they're just as applicable in deep learning.
However, deep learning also has a rather special technique called dropout.
So, for today's code,
In fact, it's really just a review of the deep learning concepts we've already covered.
all of it.
in just over 30 lines of code.
to get a deep learning model
and that completes one full training cycle.
In fact, whether we're talking about mini...
or ResNet,
or even GPT,
In fact, they are all pretty much trained in this way.
It's just taking our theories
and turns the theories we know into some commonly used tools.
You don't have to write it from scratch,
and implemented it step-by-step.
But at its core, deep learning is really about the mindset.
can't understand the code for models like this.
Absolutely not.
What you should be learning are the fundamentals of deep learning.
Once you have a solid foundation,
and then look at the individual functions it exposes.
it'll be a piece of cake.
So, in the next few lessons,
And we're not going to rush into CNNs, RNNs, or even Transformers just yet.
Instead, let's focus on how to train our model more effectively.
and get these concepts down pat.
and then move on to CNNs, sequence-to-sequence models, and so on.
and RNNs and Transformers will feel like a breeze.
So, in our next lesson, we're going to start by talking about...
how to set a good learning rate.