Let's dive into gradient descent and optimizers.
Let's find out how a neural network finds a good set of parameters.
So, the essence of training a neural network is really just about finding a good set of parameters.
In the last video, we introduced the concept of activation functions.
By introducing non-linearity,
This gives neural networks the ability to approximate any function.
But having that ability doesn't mean you have the answer just yet.
a model with hundreds of millions of parameters,
But to actually make it do something useful,
you first have to figure out the value for each of these hundreds of millions of parameters.
But what should those values actually be?
So, what about gradient descent?
And that's exactly what's going to help us solve this problem.
So, let's first take a look at the process of training a neural network.
Let's get a sense of where gradient descent fits into this process.
so that we can better understand it.
So, let's get into what we're going to cover next.
So, first, we need to initialize the parameters.
This can be done either randomly or using a tool for parameter initialization.
So, once we have these parameters,
Then, we use these parameters to perform forward propagation on our training data.
to calculate a value and make a prediction.
And we measure this prediction using something called a loss function.
What's the difference between the value we predicted and the actual label from the data?
With this difference,
and we call this the loss.
So, with this loss value,
we can start backpropagation.
This involves calculating the derivative for each layer.
And the vector composed of these calculated values is what we call the gradient.
So, once we have this,
we can then use this method of gradient descent to update our parameters.
This brings the parameters a little closer to their true values.
So, what does it mean to get closer to the true value?
Basically, it's just about making some fine-tuning adjustments to its parameters.
So, after this fine-tuning,
And we repeat this process.
and then we keep performing forward propagation with the new parameters.
calculate the loss,
and backpropagate to update them.
And we just keep repeating this cycle.
until the loss is close to zero.
Or, we've reached the maximum number of training epochs.
and then we stop.
Alright, so training is essentially a minimization problem.
So, what are we trying to minimize?
In other words, it's about minimizing the loss function.
And the corresponding theta is just a collection of all our parameters.
So, we use the loss function to measure how far off our predictions are from the actual values, right?
The smaller that difference is,
the more accurate our parameters are.
Sounds a lot like a math problem from high school, doesn't it?
You take the derivative and set it equal to zero.
and then just solve for it.
But modern large models can easily have tens of billions of parameters.
hundreds of billions of parameters.
So, we'd end up with a system of equations that has tens or even hundreds of billions of variables.
It has no analytical solution.
Since we can't solve it directly,
There's no way to solve it in a single step.
So, we'll just have to calculate it step by step.
Letting it get a little closer each time.
the loss gets smaller and smaller.
And gradually, the set of parameters we land on can be considered the optimal solution.
And that's gradient descent.
So, what's the intuition behind gradient descent?
And this is probably the most common example you'll see in all sorts of tutorials online.
It's like trying to get down a mountain with your eyes closed.
Picture yourself on a mountain.
So, how do I get to the valley?
So, if your eyes are blindfolded,
I wouldn't know which way to go.
The only way I can tell is by feeling the slope with my feet.
I'll take a small step forward.
to see if I'm currently going uphill or downhill.
I'll just take another step forward.
What if I'm going uphill?
I'll just head in the opposite direction.
I can, I can stick my foot out, right?
I keep testing the ground.
to see which way is the steepest.
Basically, I want to take the steepest path in the opposite direction.
And we just keep repeating this cycle.
We take it one small step at a time, feeling our way down.
And gradually, we'll find our way down the mountain.
In fact, this process is very similar to gradient descent.
So, during the gradient descent process,
We have to keep using the derivative.
So, let's do a quick recap for everyone.
So, the derivative is basically the instantaneous rate of change of a function.
Let's take the simplest example: a parabola, f(x) equals x squared.
Its derivative is 2X, and its value will change depending on where you are on the curve.
In fact, the tangent line of the derivative has a specific direction.
So, as we can see,
At the point where x equals three,
the derivative is six.
So, what does that actually mean?
So it's a tangent line pointing to the left, right?
Basically, the further you move to the left on the X-axis,
the larger the Y-value will be.
If you take a small step,
Let's say you move by 0.01.
So, what would the corresponding Y value be greater than?
Is it six?
it will increase by 0.06.
So, for example, when it's equal to two,
When X equals two,
So the slope is actually four.
So, what that means is, you take a small step to the right.
So, is it pointing to the right?
if you take a small step to the right,
So, let's say it moves by 0.01.
the value of the function will increase by 0.04.
And when it's equal to zero,
Now, this is something you all really need to pay attention to.
We'll get to point N in a bit.
Or, to put it another way, when we talk about gradients vanishing, this is what we're referring to.
So, when the gradient we calculate, which is the slope, gets close to zero...
So why is that a disaster?
Actually, this concept applies regardless of whether the calculated value is positive or negative.
We know how to make the update.
Should we go left or right?
whether it will make it larger or smaller.
So basically, you just move in the direction of the derivative.
it will get larger.
But what if we go in the opposite direction of the derivative?
it will get smaller.
But what if it's equal to zero?
So what does that mean?
move to the left,
or to the right.
the function won't change at all.
So, what happens when the gradient is equal to zero?
we won't know which way the gradient should go next.
This situation can make our calculations extremely difficult.
So, when we're performing gradient descent,
We need to avoid a derivative value of zero.
So, what if we extend this from two dimensions to multiple dimensions?
So basically, this happens when we have multiple variables in our loss function.
So, we have X1 through XN. What we'll do is take the partial derivative with respect to each of these variables.
Together, they form a vector.
And this vector is what we call the gradient.
It has a direction.
It represents the direction of the steepest ascent at the current point, theta.
So, that's what a gradient is.
So, what if we want to reduce the overall loss?
We just take the negative of it.
and take a small step in the opposite direction.
This is the direction of the steepest descent.
So, what exactly is the workflow for gradient descent?
For example, let's say we're at the seventh step.
So, we know we have a matrix of parameters.
We just want to make it smaller.
to make the overall loss a little smaller.
So, I'll subtract this... this is the gradient, right?
multiplied by a learning rate.
We'll have it take a tiny step forward, in the opposite direction of the gradient.
We can't take too big of a step.
This prevents us from going in the wrong direction.
By taking small steps, I can gradually get closer to the solution.
Alright, let's look at a quick example.
For example, when X, or X0, is equal to four.
This is actually the point we're trying to find.
So, this is actually the point where the loss is at.
But of course, what we're trying to do is get it to zero, right?
When we get to the point where the loss is zero,
So, how do we get it to zero, step by step?
For example, let's say the learning rate is 0.1.
So, when the value is four,
So, let's see, the value we get is 16.
So when we plug in four,
And the derivative of that is eight.
So each time, we have it subtract 8 times 0.1.
So that's 0.8.
So, that's it for this step. Now, we move on to the next one.
So in this step, we're going to multiply its value by 0.1 again.
And as you keep doing this, you'll notice that...
And as a result, our Y value will get smaller and smaller.
getting smaller and smaller.
Until, well, this is actually the loss value, right?
until it approaches zero.
getting infinitely close to zero.
and we can consider the current parameters to be good enough.
So, in this simple example,
We can also make three observations here.
The slower it moves.
Right?
See how big the steps are at the beginning.
In other words, the change in our loss is actually getting smaller and smaller.
This means the change in our loss is getting smaller and smaller.
So, you can think of it as having a built-in brake.
Another thing is that it's monotonically decreasing.
Each step gets us closer to zero than the last.
And it just keeps getting closer and closer.
But it's very difficult to actually reach zero.
So, the point isn't to get an exact value of zero.
Getting close enough is good enough.
In a real neural network,
And the process is actually the same.
Of course, let's just briefly touch on this.
Now, the learning rate is actually a very sensitive hyperparameter throughout the entire training process.
So, why do we pick 0.1?
or 0.01 is a common choice in practice.
The problem with this is that if the learning rate is too large, it can cause the model to oscillate.
or even diverge.
If it's too small, the learning process will be too slow.
So, we'll also cover how to tune the learning rate in a separate video later on.
Of course, in the upcoming sections,
Now, some of our optimizers actually handle the learning rate adjustment themselves, based on the principles of gradient descent.
And that's pretty much how it works.
So, with the knowledge we have so far,
and you can implement a neural network on your own.
But when it comes to actually training a neural network,
But we generally don't do it this way.
Because, in reality, this approach is a bit inefficient.
Now, this formula might look incredibly simple,
But in a real-world scenario,
The first question is, how many samples' gradients are we using?
You're only training on a single sample each time.
and that gives us a gradient.
So, how many parameters are you updating at once?
So, should you use all the samples?
And then, where do we go from there?
Imagine you're in a narrow, elongated valley.
So, what about your next step?
it might seem like the right move for now is to go down.
But in reality, overall,
This isn't because you're heading in the optimal direction.
If you're in a canyon like this, you can get to this side in just one step.
You'll find you still have to take a step in this direction.
and then you have to move back this way.
It keeps oscillating back and forth.
So, how can we avoid this?
And another thing is, how should the learning rate be distributed?
Should it automatically adjust, and so on.
So, there are all sorts of issues that come up.
So, the optimizers we're going to talk about next...
essentially, they are here to help us solve these very problems.
to make the gradient change in the most optimal way in real-time.
First, let's start with the most basic form, which is the principle we just discussed.
And this is what we call a 'batch'.
gradient descent.
And 'batch' just means a batch of data, right?
We use the entire dataset every single time.
So, after I've done the calculation,
and that means we've trained on the entire dataset.
Now, doing it this way actually has its benefits.
So, I just take the average of it, right?
So, we just use the average of its gradients.
Actually, this all started way back in 1847.
The French mathematician Cauchy, uh, while he was studying the orbits of comets,
And that's basically how he did it.
So basically, what do you do when there's no analytical solution?
You just get closer and closer, step by step.
This was actually a very, very advanced idea for its time.
So, when we want to update the parameters in gradient descent,
the model has to go through the entire dataset to complete one training cycle.
and then perform an update using the averaged gradient.
So, by now, you've probably figured out its pros and cons.
So, the advantage is that we're actually using all of the data.
virtually
So, you could say the training process is a very accurate reflection of the real data.
But the downside is, the training cost is just too high.
You have to run through the entire dataset just to calculate a single gradient.
It just takes way too long.
Plus, it lacks randomness.
it gets stuck in a saddle point or a region with a small gradient.
so there's no noise to jolt it out of there.
and that helps it get out of there.
This is actually what I was explaining to you all earlier when we were talking about functions.
If it reaches a point where the calculation results in zero,
when it's obviously not at the lowest point yet.
but when its gradient is about to hit zero,
So, in a situation like this, we're pretty much talking about gradient descent, right?
we multiply the learning rate by the gradient,
And no matter how small the learning rate is,
no matter what the learning rate is,
When the gradient is zero,
What you're subtracting is the value of the parameter.
But the amount you're subtracting is always zero.
If it's in a region that's completely flat,
So when it gets to a place like this,
it won't continue to go down any further.
it won't be able to find the lowest point, relatively speaking.
and it'll just get stuck in certain spots.
It thinks it has found a low point,
In reality, this is just a local minimum.
but not the lowest point overall.
This approach just won't work.
And this is basically the formula we saw at the very beginning.
So, what happens when the gradient is zero?
In fact, the parameter itself is the same at time T+1 as it was at time T.
it stops changing.
So, how do we avoid this?
So, to address this, we introduce Stochastic Gradient Descent.
Each time, I just use a single random sample to update the gradient.
And actually, this approach is grounded in some real-world principles.
I just have to keep doing this over and over again.
and keep on adjusting it,
and in the long run, it will converge to the true solution.
So, here's the general formula.
So, you can see that this part here, what was it in the previous formula?
Now, you don't need to get too bogged down in the details of this formula.
Just having a general idea of the principle is enough.
So, after we've calculated all the losses,
and take the average.
So, what's the situation now?
We just randomly pick one from the numbers one to N.
And we just use the one we picked.
And its pros and cons are also very clear.
The upside is that it's incredibly efficient.
Right?
And since you're just randomly picking one,
It's inherently noisy.
It might even help us during the training process,
Let's break out of the saddle point.
But the downside is that it's just too inaccurate.
The thing is,
So, during the training process, you'll find that the loss fluctuates wildly.
So, it all comes down to how lucky you get with your random sampling.
And on top of that, if you're just unlucky,
and you happen to pick an outlier.
it's actually an outlier.
this outlier data will take our gradient and...
and pulls our entire set of parameters in a really weird direction.
We'd have to train it many times just to pull it back.
But sometimes, this can actually make things less efficient.
But in reality, this approach actually makes a lot of sense.
It's just that every time, we only draw one sample.
But it did come with some pretty significant issues.
But it did inspire the optimizers that came after it.
So, what's the optimizer that came after that?
Mini-batch Stochastic Gradient Descent.
So, for mini-batch... well, the first one we have is batch gradient descent.
The second one is Stochastic Gradient Descent.
And the third one? It's a combination of the two.
So, it's stochastic, but we're just taking a small, random batch.
Doing it all at once is too aggressive,
But using the entire batch is way too slow.
So, I'll just find a middle ground.
So, each time, we randomly sample a batch—say, 32 or 128 samples.
So, we just take a portion each time.
This way, it combines the benefits of both approaches,
and the drawbacks were balanced out.
And the computation is also significantly faster.
Makes sense, right?
Plus, the oscillations aren't as severe anymore.
And at the same time, because it's also stochastic,
So, it still maintains a certain degree of randomness.
So, as you can see, it's actually incredibly useful in many ways.
So, nowadays, a lot of the time...
So, when we talk about SGD, or Stochastic Gradient Descent,
In practice, we're no longer talking about just randomly picking a single sample.
So, even if we don't have 'mini-batch' in front of it,
Mini-batch.
This also refers to mini-batch stochastic gradient descent.
It strikes a remarkably good balance between statistical efficiency and computational efficiency.
So, when we talk about SGD,
By default, the 'S' in SGD actually refers to mini-batch SGD.
Now, even though mini-batch SGD is already quite good,
But of course, brilliant minds were still constantly researching and pushing the boundaries in this field.
In 1964,
So, when Soviet mathematicians were studying the convergence speed of iterative methods,
and proposed a method called Momentum.
The core idea is that you shouldn't just look at the gradient of the current step.
Instead, you also need to factor in the momentum from the past few steps.
When the directions are aligned,
the update gets continuously reinforced.
This way, those oscillating updates are gradually neutralized.
Let's take a look at an example of an iron ball rolling down a mountain.
Now, the plain vanilla gradient descent we started with...
So, for each small section it goes down,
it has to stop and calculate the current gradient.
and then take another small step.
So it stops right here.
and it finds that the gradient is zero.
Because this area is flat, right?
It might just stop moving downwards.
It can't be optimized any further.
It figures that going left would also be zero.
and going right is also zero.
Alright then.
This must be the lowest point then.
I'm not moving.
But in reality, if you take just one more step forward...
there's actually a lower point.
But in the real, physical world,
Imagine a small ball rolling down a mountain.
But that's not actually how it works.
until it reaches a flat area.
It will keep moving forward.
Why is that?
Because as it was going down the slope earlier,
It has a certain amount of inertia.
When it encounters some small
or even over some small bumps,
so it won't get stuck oscillating back and forth here.
and it'll use that inertia to break right through.
It won't veer off to the left,
and then to the right.
Because it has this momentum,
This will keep it moving straight forward.
and it just pushes right through.
So basically, what this means is that gradient descent doesn't just consider your current gradient.
but also the gradients from previous steps.
If they're in the same direction,
I need to factor that in as well.
This way, it keeps pushing forward.
so the updates are much faster.
So, the formula for this would basically look something like this.
So, what are the benefits of this?
If the gradient directions in several consecutive steps of gradient descent are all very similar,
In fact, it also dampens this kind of left-right oscillation.
So, why is that?
Because it'll go left for a bit,
and then to the right,
But, because you're adding in the historical information,
the leftward and rightward movements will cancel each other out.
In reality, it will form a straight line going downwards like this.
For this kind of narrow, elongated valley,
So, if it actually has momentum,
the updates will be incredibly fast.
And, like we just mentioned,
It also makes it easier to get past some saddle points.
or some flat regions.
or some small, local minima.
Even if the instantaneous speed at that moment is close to zero,
But because I have that momentum built up from before,
I can still power through.
And that's the benefit of using momentum.
But, of course, this inertia is a double-edged sword.
But it might also overshoot.
It just keeps going right past it because of that inertia.
This can also cause it to oscillate around the optimal point.
But that's still acceptable.
Plus, it introduces an additional hyperparameter.
Now, to be fair, any hyperparameter is going to be somewhat sensitive.
Values that are too small or too large just won't work well.
Now, in most practical applications,
And 0.9 is a pretty good number to go with.
So, that's why in almost all subsequent Stochastic Gradient Descent training sessions,
it will come with some momentum by default.
And by default, it also passes a momentum value to us, which is set to...
So basically, this is what everyone is using now.
And for all subsequent large-scale training,
The core idea is mini-batch SGD plus momentum.
Okay, sounds like we've reached the grand finale, right?
That's good enough, right?
Right?
But, there's always a bigger fish.
And then, in 2011,
But then, some researchers started to notice something.
You see, you have different parameters.
and they actually represent different features.
So you're updating all of them with the exact same learning rate.
all set to 0.1.
Doesn't that seem a bit too simple and crude?
For example, in NLP, which is, you know, Natural Language Processing...
We know that the word 'the' appears with a very high frequency in any given text.
So, during training,
Each batch will have its corresponding parameters.
the gradient will be very large.
This makes the updates actually quite thorough.
But for a word like this, you might not even recognize it.
so the gradient will be huge,
In fact, its frequency of occurrence is extremely low.
It only shows up a handful of times during the entire training process.
the gradient will be extremely small.
So, what if we use the same learning rate for low-frequency words?
It's pretty much impossible to train.
Because its gradient is almost always zero.
Only when it does appear will there be some minor changes.
The update frequency is just way too low.
So, the idea is to have an adaptive way to adjust the effective learning rate for this parameter.
In other words, each parameter maintains its own learning rate independently.
It's not shared with any other parameters.
So I keep track of it myself, right?
In this case, my own frequency of updates is relatively low.
So, I'll just set the learning rate to be relatively large.
so I can take a big step each time.
I'm updating my parameters more frequently.
So, I'll just set the learning rate to be pretty small.
taking just one small step at a time.
This is to prevent it from overshooting.
So, what is this? It's an adaptive gradient.
So, the formula for it looks something like this.
In other words, it adds the square of the gradient from each step.
And this small value we're adding here is to prevent the denominator from being zero.
and then divide that by the learning rate.
Basically, it's taking its past gradients into account.
Of course, when we're updating the parameters really frequently,
the gradient will be larger.
So, we'll end up with a larger gradient.
This way, the learning rate becomes smaller.
Right?
Because the denominator gets bigger, right?
So, when our gradient is relatively small,
So, when the updates aren't happening very often,
In that case, the denominator would be smaller.
the learning rate will increase.
This lets it update more quickly.
So, this is essentially what we call an adaptive learning rate.
And this, in turn, influenced a whole lot of what came after.
But it does have its drawbacks.
Now, this might sound great,
The biggest problem is that the learning rate monotonically decays to zero.
And why is that? Well, let's take a look at the formula.
This value is always positive.
This way, your learning rate will eventually be driven towards zero.
And that's actually not a good thing.
And that, right there, is its biggest problem.
But it does have some advantages, though.
Basically, it means you don't have to manually tune the learning rate anymore.
And its adaptive nature also makes it particularly well-suited for sparse data.
Because it can adjust itself, right?
But its major problem is, what if the training isn't even finished yet?
and the training just grinds to a halt.
Gradually, the gradient itself will just... you know, the learning rate gets...
Plus,
But what happens is, you've basically set the learning rate to zero.
And just like that, the training process grinds to a halt.
And it was precisely this flaw that led to the development of the next method, RMSprop.
And then there are others like ADAM.
At their core, they're all trying to improve the same thing.
and only keep the influence of recent gradients.
And that was the first optimization for adaptive learning rates.
And RMSprop... well, that was after AlexNet ignited the deep learning boom back in 2012.
This led to the development of deeper and deeper networks.
and training took longer and longer.
So basically, with these adaptive gradient methods, we just couldn't make progress with the training anymore.
This would cause the learning rate to shrink to zero.
So, here's an idea for an improvement.
And that's actually the problem with RMSprop.
The idea behind it is very simple.
Instead of summing up the squares of all the gradients from the entire training process,
Because that would just make the denominator larger and larger, right?
the learning rate would eventually drop to zero.
So, it doesn't use all of them anymore.
Instead, it only uses the most recent ones, like the last ten updates, right?
In this case, it stabilizes to a certain value.
So, by using this one clever little trick,
This solves the problem of the denominator getting infinitely large.
and the problem of the learning rate shrinking to zero.
And what's interesting is,
Now, this optimization method is an old friend of ours.
It was proposed by Hinton.
But he didn't even write it up as a formal paper.
Because he felt this improvement was just so logical.
So he just mentioned it in an online course,
After he wrote it down in his slides, it just took off and became the new standard.
So, as a result, when people cited it, there was no proper paper to reference. This is how it ended up being cited.
Right.
In this section, we have this so-called 'COSER'...
Just a single page from a lecture's PowerPoint.
And just like that, the algorithm we just saw in the PPT became the new mainstream.
Let's take a look at its formula.
Now, this might look a lot more complicated than the last one.
And that's really the biggest difference.
So it's not the sum of all the squares, right?
It's based on the most recent ones.
So, what this does is, it prevents the learning rate from decaying all the way to zero.
And on top of that, it also maintains its adaptability.
So your recent gradients haven't plateaued either, right?
And what about the previous ones?
Right?
And it's also particularly well-suited for non-stationary objectives.
So, it's incredibly useful.
However, it does have its limitations.
First of all, it's just an adaptive learning rate.
It doesn't take the gradient into account, right?
For instance, which direction should it move in?
It doesn't have that.
So, this can also cause oscillations.
And on top of that, there are these issues.
Of course, it also adds another hyperparameter.
So, despite these drawbacks,
So, what it's actually doing is already happening during the training process.
It became especially popular for things like RNNs.
Especially when the loss landscape is quite rugged.
It's incredibly effective.
So, for a while, RMSprop became the go-to choice for training neural networks.
the go-to choice.
This was the case until ADAM appeared in 2015.
So, what's the core idea behind ADAM?
Then, around 2014 to 2015,
By this point, two distinct schools of thought had clearly emerged in the field of deep learning optimization.
One is the adaptive gradient approach.
And then there's the other track, which is all about improving upon it, right?
The idea is to let different parameters use different learning rates.
Then there's another method, which is the momentum method, an idea that's been around since 1964.
So, we just give it some momentum.
Both of these methods are incredibly useful, by the way.
So, since each has its own strengths,
So, why not just combine them?
And so, in 2014, it was born.
ADAM is short for Adaptive Moment Estimation.
Makes sense, right?
I need both the direction,
and I also need the step size.
So, that's basically the ADAM formula, which, you know, is just a whole bunch of math.
And then, it also applies some bias correction to it.
So, it doesn't really matter what value you initialize it with at the very beginning.
It can adapt to all of them.
So, that's why the first step makes perfect sense.
And that's why it became so popular.
It's just incredibly, incredibly useful.
So, what are its three main advantages?
First, it introduced the concept of momentum, right?
And it can also reference past gradients.
And the updates become much smoother.
and it's less likely to get stuck.
oscillations.
Second, I also want to apply this to each individual parameter.
In this case, we're still using a single learning rate for all the parameters.
So now, I'm going to do something similar to RMSprop.
for all the parameters.
assign its own learning rate to each parameter.
So, it basically combines the strengths of both.
So you could say it's incredibly versatile.
And for a very long time, it was pretty much the go-to choice.
It became the default optimizer for pretty much all developers.
But as people dug deeper, they found that the idea behind Adam was exceptionally good.
But in reality, it had a hidden bug.
This is actually an issue with weight decay.
So, in the traditional stochastic gradient descent,
that is, the decay of the weights.
So, as the weights get smaller and smaller,
In fact, it's pretty much equivalent to L2 regularization.
So, in the early days, we had Adam.
It also adds this L2 term to the gradient.
But then, people started to run into a problem.
The thing is, what this does is, it takes the regularization signal, which is supposed to be stable, right?
The regularization signal itself should be stable.
But what ended up happening was, it got scaled down along with everything else by the adaptive mechanism.
This means the effect of regularization is being distorted from its original purpose by the adaptive mechanism.
You can't do that.
So basically, you can just think of it as a bug in how it handles the weights.
This would cause the regularization to fail.
So then, in 2017, Ilya Sutskever came up with a proposal.
And the 'W' in AdamW? Well, that stands for 'weight'.
Essentially, it just decouples the gradient update from the weight decay.
So, the general formula would look something like this.
But this actually introduces yet another hyperparameter.
But the thing is, it solves the problem with Adam.
So, it might seem like a very, very small improvement.
But in the case of Transformers,
BERT,
and large language models like ViT,
It's pretty much the de facto standard.
The vast majority of models we see today,
They all use it at their core.
And we're not at the grand finale yet.
And then, more recently, around 2024, right?
And then, people started to discover some new angles to tackle this problem.
And that's where MIR comes in.
So, what's its core idea?
Basically, it's built on top of momentum.
The core idea is to treat the parameters as a two-dimensional matrix.
and perform an orthogonal correction.
It flattens out some of the singular values before taking another step.
I know, that sounds super complicated, right?
So, to put it simply, when it updates the parameters like this...
the updates will all be in the same direction.
This prevents it from moving off in a bunch of random directions.
So, to put it simply, it's just really, really effective.
For matrix-type data,
But for biases, it's not really used.
So, speaking of which, we also know about KIMI later on.
In fact, KIMI also uses it.
In fact, its efficiency is much higher than what you'd get with IMMW.
So, when it comes to training the next generation of large models,
Especially in all sorts of open-source models.
In fact, it's still used quite a lot.
So, this is pretty much the latest and greatest optimizer out there.
So, to sum it all up,
Our optimization journey,
The driving force behind every single one of these advancements is really the same question: how can we make parameter updates faster and more stable?
So, we'll start with the very original method: batch gradient descent.
This established the fundamental conceptual framework.
Basically, all the subsequent developments have been built upon this foundational idea.
And then, we introduced stochasticity.
So, 'stochastic' just means it uses a single sample.
Now, this method is certainly faster, no doubt about it.
But the problem is, it's way too noisy.
So, we compromise with a mini-batch.
So, instead of using just one,
Let's use 32.
or maybe 64 samples?
This one is incredibly efficient.
It's pretty much the default choice now.
Then, we introduced another concept: momentum.
This gives it some inertia to power through plateaus and small local minima.
Then, later on, other researchers came along.
The idea was that using a single learning rate for all the parameters wasn't a good fit.
And so, this is where adaptive learning rates come into play.
However, it had some minor issues that would cause the learning rate to decay to zero.
So, to optimize it, RMSprop was introduced.
This way, the learning rate won't drop to zero.
Then came ADAM, which combined these optimizations for both momentum and the learning rate.
And then came this one, which was incredibly effective.
So, AdamW, well, it's basically a fix for the weight decay issue in the original Adam.
and became the de facto standard.
And then, starting from 2024,
So, MIR works by considering the update direction as orthogonal to the weight matrix.
This makes the update direction more stable.
So, we're seeing it being used more and more in 2024.
So, this is basically how you use an optimizer.
So, in our day-to-day work with all sorts of machine learning tasks,
In fact, this one is the most widely used.
And another one that's actually used quite a lot is Adam.
But in reality, different fields will have different preferences.
It's not like there's a single, definitive answer.
For instance, in many computer vision tasks,
particularly on convolutional neural networks.
SGD, in combination with momentum,
But if we manage to tune the learning rate really well,
its final accuracy can often still be optimized.
it can even outperform Adam.
For a long time, the go-to choice for large NLP models has been AdamW.
But now, in 2024, Muon is making a comeback.
So, when we're doing some quick experiments and prototyping,
ADAM is the fastest of the fast.
You can often get a pretty good baseline just by using it.
In cases with sparse data, or during short online cycles,
So, the adaptive learning rate is still a really useful method.
So, for things like ad CTR prediction, these traditional LP methods also have some real-world value.
So, that's basically how gradient descent works.
So, using gradient descent is really just one way of thinking about the problem.
But in our actual practice,
we'll use all sorts of different optimizers.
to make it more efficient.
But throughout this process, we've repeatedly mentioned the learning rate.
This is an extremely sensitive hyperparameter.
Whether it's set correctly or not has a huge impact on the success of our training.
So, in the next video, we'll dive into how to actually set the learning rate.
And how do we schedule the learning rate?
Okay, that's all for this video.