Hello everyone.
Welcome to my channel.
And just like that, it's graduation season again.
First of all, let's give a warm congratulations to all the students of the Class of '26 who have successfully graduated.
and extend our warmest congratulations.
Congratulations on successfully completing your graduation projects.
your thesis defense and all the academic tasks of your university journey.
and are about to embark on a new chapter of your lives.
And at the same time,
And for all the students graduating in 2027,
are also about to enter the topic selection phase.
So, every year around this time...
I get tons of DMs.
For instance, someone might ask, "Hey, senior, is this topic doable?"
Is this topic going to be too difficult?
The professor gave us, like, dozens of topics to choose from.
I have absolutely no idea how to even begin choosing.
In fact, a lot of students are still in the topic selection phase,
and don't even bother to seriously research their topic.
So, after you've looked through the list of topics,
and just randomly pick one.
just because the name sounds fancy.
and just lock it in.
But when it's actually time to get started,
that's when you realize you don't actually know how to develop it.
can't write the thesis,
can't draw the diagrams,
don't know how to design a database,
Don't know how to do system testing.
and end up cramming at the last minute.
At best, you'll be pulling all-nighters and grinding for a solid month.
Or worse, you could end up spending a fortune and wasting a ton of time just to fix the problems.
So, in this video, I'm going to draw from my years of experience...
Let's do a deep dive into how you should actually choose a topic for your computer science capstone project.
and which ones are total traps.
and which ones are a guaranteed pass.
and which topics will show a good amount of work without being too difficult to complete.
And finally,
I've also put together a list for you all.
a list of recommended topics for the 2027 graduation projects.
So, make sure to like and save this video.
Alright, let's get started.
First, let's talk about why so many students mess up their final projects.
So, a lot of students wonder, 'Is the graduation project difficult or not?'
depends entirely on their own development skills.
But in reality, that's not the main reason why most graduation projects end in disaster at all.
There's only one reason: you picked the wrong topic.
If you pick the wrong topic,
every single line of code you write after that will be pure agony.
Let me give you a simple example.
For instance, some students might come across a 'HarmonyOS-based Smart Campus System'.
A blockchain-based logistics management system.
or an industrial monitoring platform based on digital twins.
A virtual lab for JXR
Now, these names might sound super fancy and impressive,
So, you picked it without a second thought.
But when it was time to actually start developing, I realized there were no tutorials online.
Plus, there are no open-source projects either.
And there were no ready-made examples to follow either.
technical documentation,
And these are also extremely scarce.
And you'll find basically no references to cite.
In the end, you just have to bite the bullet and push through with it.
So, the number one rule when it comes to picking a topic is...
Don't pick a topic just to show off your skills.
The most important thing about your thesis is to get you to graduation.
It's not about pushing yourself to your absolute limits.
Alright, so let's talk about the five core principles for choosing your graduation project topic.
Alright, the first principle is all about your tech stack.
Make sure it's mainstream.
So, that's my first piece of advice for you all.
So, when you're choosing your tech stack,
If you can use Spring Boot, don't go for some obscure framework.
And if you can use Vue, don't mess with some obscure front-end framework.
And for the database, stick with MySQL.
and don't mess around with some weird database.
For the vast majority of undergraduates,
So, for the tech stack, I recommend Vue plus Element Plus for the front-end.
and for the backend, Spring Boot.
For the database, go with MySQL, and for caching,
and for permission management, use Redis.
For tokens, you can use something like JWT or Spring Security. As for file storage,
Yeah, you can use local uploads.
Or, for the AI features, you could use MiniIO.
You can use the OpenAI API,
Or, you could use the API for our domestic large model, DeepSeek.
This tech stack is already very mature.
There are tons of tutorials and examples out there.
Plus, there are tons of open-source projects you can turn to when you run into problems.
and a quick search will usually solve it.
On the other hand, for some of the more obscure technologies...
For instance, developing for HarmonyOS, or using Flutter for desktop.
or Rust.
full-stack blockchain development, digital twins,
Now, it's not that you can't do these projects.
but rather, they aren't a good first choice for a graduation project.
The reason is, there are very few tutorials for these things online.
Plus, they're extremely demanding on your computer's performance.
Take the HarmonyOS emulator, for example.
Even with 32 gigs of RAM, my computer really struggles with it.
And there are no tutorials.
We can learn it step by step.
But what if your computer isn't powerful enough?
Then the only option is to spend some money.
Just to finish a graduation project,
and end up buying a computer that costs thousands, or even tens of thousands.
It's really just not worth it.
Plus, with the recent price hike in memory sticks,
Plus, a lot of computers are seriously overpriced.
So, I really wouldn't recommend you guys go out and buy a new computer.
Just use the computer you've had for the past four years of college.
Just focus on finishing our graduation project, and we'll be all set.
The second principle is that your system's features must be up-to-date.
The systems many students are building still look like they're from 10 years ago.
User management,
role management,
menu management.
And that's it for CRUD operations.
It's getting really hard to make these kinds of systems stand out anymore.
Now that we've entered the age of AI,
So, you can totally add some modern features to your system.
For example, an AI smart assistant.
AI Q&A,
AI customer service,
AI Knowledge Base
OCR Recognition
Scheduled Tasks
Push notifications
Payment Module
Data Visualization, Recommendation Algorithms, and File Management.
Online preview
Electronic signature.
Workflow approval
And honestly, implementing these features isn't actually that difficult.
But when it comes to your thesis,
This will really show off your strong innovative skills.
For example,
Let's say you were originally building a pet management system.
what if you add an AI pet health consultation assistant?
And just like that, the whole project's quality level instantly goes up.
Let's say you have a news management system.
Or, if you add an AI news summary generator,
This will make it feel really modern and in line with current trends.
So, I'd suggest that you don't let your project, you know...
be just a simple CRUD system.
Make sure to add at least one or two of these standout features.
The third principle is to keep your role design from getting overly complex.
For instance, some students design systems that include a 'merchant' role.
agents,
Operations staff,
financial staff,
Customer service staff.
And in the end, you've got a whole dozen or so roles, which might look super impressive.
But in reality, you're just making more work for yourself.
Because the more roles you have,
the more complex the permissions and menus become.
Plus, the use case diagrams and all those flowcharts will be incredibly complex as well.
And that makes the thesis incredibly difficult to write.
My advice is actually pretty simple.
For your undergraduate thesis,
Basically, you just need two or three roles.
For example, you could have an admin, a user, and a merchant, or maybe an admin and a teacher.
and student would be more than enough.
This way, you can showcase your permission management system,
And you won't work yourself to death, right?
The fourth principle is the database.
The number of tables is also super important.
Here's something a lot of people don't know.
The thing is, most professors won't actually dive deep into your code.
Because the truth is, they can't even understand your code.
So, what's the first thing they look at?
The amount of work you've put in.
So, one of the most straightforward ways to show your workload is...
is the database design.
If your system only has things like user roles and menus,
and just three business tables,
Then, at first glance, the professor will think the project is too small.
On the other hand, if your system includes features like user accounts, orders, and reviews,
favorites, messages, and notifications.
category logs, carousels,
payment records,
Audit Log
Recommendation Records
and so on.
aim for a dozen, or even 20 tables.
This will show your professor that you've put in a ton of work into the system.
So, as long as it makes sense for the project,
So, you can definitely beef up the number of business-related tables.
Of course, this doesn't mean you should just randomly pile on tables.
Instead, you should add modules as long as they make sense for your business logic.
The fifth principle is to learn how to effectively leverage AI tools.
We're already in 2026,
If you're still not using AI at all,
you're really putting yourself at a disadvantage.
Look, AI isn't going to get you your diploma.
But what it can do is help you be more efficient.
For example, generating database table designs.
help generate code,
polishing your thesis,
Generate test cases,
Generate requirement analyses,
optimizing abstracts, and so on.
But there's one thing you all have to remember.
AI is just a tool to help you.
It's not a replacement.
Ultimately, you still have to understand the implementation logic of your own project.
Otherwise, during your defense, if the professor asks you a couple of simple questions,
and you'll be completely stumped.
Finally, let me recommend some project topics for your graduation thesis.
For the AI track, you could go with Spring Boot.
and a Vue.js-powered AI knowledge base Q&A system.
Its main features include user login and registration.
file upload for knowledge base management,
vectorization processing,
an AI-powered Q&A system, and so on.
And then there's this GG Enterprise Knowledge Management Platform.
An intelligent customer service system based on large models,
An AI-based thesis writing assistant platform, and so on.
So, for these project ideas...
All of these incorporate AI and IG-related features.
This will instantly take your graduation project to the next level.
Now, when it comes to management systems,
For example, there's the library management system.
a lab reservation system, and so on.
Now, I know what you're thinking about these management systems.
I mean, they're a bit cliché at this point.
But if you add some innovative features to them,
Then it's 100% guaranteed to work.
Take a library management system, for example.
You could, for example, implement a timer.
So, you can set the timer to trigger at midnight every day to run a query.
to see who hasn't returned their books on time.
And then, we'll just generate the fines and all that for them.
For the recommendation system, you have a few options here.
You can use collaborative filtering,
or a knowledge graph for your recommendations.
If I were to make recommendations for the Class of 2027,
So, for topics that are easier to get a high score with, hmm...
So, the top-tier choice is definitely an AI knowledge base system.
IG, uh...
and intelligent Q&A systems.
knowledge graphs, and so on.
Moving on to the second tier, we have recommendation systems.
And for the third tier, we have e-commerce and rental platforms.
and projects like campus management systems.
They generally have complete features,
and a large number of database tables.
and clear innovative points.
The thesis is easy to write,
And the defense will be a breeze.
These are perfect topics for your undergraduate thesis.
Finally, let's do a quick quality check on your chosen topic.
For example, can you actually build it yourself?
Are there any reference materials available?
Are there any open-source projects available?
Is the paper going to be easy to write?
And how easy it'll be to present during your defense.
As long as you can get a clear handle on these few questions,
and your graduation project is already halfway to success.
So, if you're still not sure how to pick a topic,
Feel free to follow and send me a DM.
to get more project topic ideas.
I'll be sharing more in my upcoming videos.
and share more tips for your computer science capstone projects.
Thanks for watching.
See you in the next video!