Virtual threads were introduced in Java 21
So what problems do virtual threads actually solve?
In what scenarios can it be used
What are the differences between virtual threads and Go's goroutines?
We learned in second grade
Before JDK 21
Java only has platform threads
so-called platform threads
which means all scheduling rights of the threads
The operating system employs time-sliced round-robin scheduling
mechanisms such as multi-level queues to determine which thread executes
This makes programmers feel
The readily available resources of the operating system are virtually unlimited.
So here lies the problem
The scheduling of the operating system comes at a cost.
the operating system kernel directly schedules
causing thread switching to require entering kernel mode
This involves a complete context switch in the system
need to save and restore registers
restore the context for scheduling decisions
This overhead is relatively significant
when the number of threads we create
far exceeds the actual number of CPU cores
the operating system aims to schedule these threads more fairly
must frequently suspend and resume threads
ensure that each task can progress normally
Modern operating systems all employ preemptive scheduling
The operating system can do so through interrupts
preempt the context switch of the currently running CPU
This switching is mandatory
referred to as the preemptive multitasking mode
Here we take a tomcat server as an example
If the CPU has ten cores
then this machine can only handle ten HTTP requests simultaneously
This is clearly unacceptable
but we found that this HTTP request
most of the time is not spent on CPU computation
this HTTP request
may call third-party interfaces during processing
or querying databases like REDIS
during the execution of these operations
we naturally expect the operating system to suspend these threads
switch to other threads for execution
Of course, handling too many threads simultaneously
the aforementioned CPU resources would still be exhausted
Therefore, Tomcat sets a default value
with a thread pool size of 200
which means a maximum of 200 requests can be scheduled and processed simultaneously
Specific parameters should be adjusted according to the CPU's load type and model
make adjustments
For example, if your configuration is excellent
or if the current service is purely a request forwarding service
we can adjust this parameter higher
Doesn't that sound very familiar
Exactly
This is the IO-intensive and CPU-intensive concept that our team often recites
the configuration logic for intensive thread pool resources
So the underlying meaning of so-called I/O-intensive
This service doesn't use the CPU much.
can frequently yield CPU resources to other threads
If the thread pool's thread count limit is set too high
can easily cause the operating system to frequently suspend
resulting in degraded program performance
set too low
can also lead to a situation where threads are fully occupied
the processor is still not running at full capacity
resulting in waste
So is there any way to solve this problem?
Yes, my bro, yes
That is Java's virtual threads
The solution adopted by virtual threads is very simple
Since the operating system's scheduling
such a waste of time
Why don't we just move this scheduling to user space?
JPM can schedule threads by itself
In Java, the scheduling approach adopted for virtual threads
called cooperative scheduling
Cooperative scheduling means when a program experiences hang-ups or blocking
such as the sleep function
then the current CPU resources will be automatically allocated to
another thread that needs to be executed
Since such blocking is usually caused by IO waits
Therefore, we need to frequently perform IO waits
while the CPU remains relatively idle
In this Java code snippet
The program created more threads than the currently schedulable number of threads in the system
one additional thread
the extra thread in this case
can still run normally
When running the following code
The program can still output the new virtual thread here
This is because in the loop of other threads
the sleep function will yield execution rights from other virtual threads
yield to this new thread
But if we make a slight change
remove the sleep
rerun this code
we will find that the 'new v show si' part never gets printed
This holds true for both JDK21 and JDK25.
This is cooperative scheduling
they need to negotiate with each other
when to yield resources to other threads
This scheduling mode
The advantage is that it eliminates the need for the JVM to periodically interrupt operations
because this would incur certain overhead
The drawback is if you have 11 non-stop tasks
which means 11 threads need to run on a 10-thread CPU
then one of the tasks will continuously fail to be scheduled
So what about the virtual threads in Go? We usually call them goroutines.
It actually chose a different approach.
We know that Go's threading is based on the GMP model.
Similarly, Go also brings scheduling into the user-space program.
We usually refer to goroutines as coroutines
Here, the '协' primarily refers to cooperative.
early versions of Go made choices similar to current Java
is purely cooperatively scheduled
which means
If you run similar code in Go 1.13
the final result would be the same as in Java
fails to output
You might even get stuck with goroutines.
but when running the same code in versions after 1.14G
Goroutines can successfully output the results again
Isn't it amazing?
it's because the subsequent versions
the Go language employs cooperative plus preemptive scheduling
if a go routine
running continuously on a logical processor for 10ms
it will be marked as preemptible
that is to say
In higher versions of Go, there are two possibilities that can lead to context switching
another is blocking or hanging
the other is that it will be preempted by other coroutines if it runs for too long
To summarize
we can easily conclude
The main advantage of virtual threads is
The overhead of creating and destroying thread pools is very small
and are all user-mode operations
Therefore, in most cases
it needs to petrify virtual threads just like platform threads
Therefore, we don't need to worry about specific thread pool parameter configurations
This was typically determined based on business attributes and stress testing in the past.
determine the switching overhead of virtual threads
is also a purely user-mode operation
compared to system-level trapping
can perform a thread switch
Virtual threads in scenarios requiring frequent thread switching
performance will be better
Now that we understand this principle,
the programmer occupies a thread each time the code is executed
All asynchronous operations are scheduled on a single thread
And if you want to use asynchronous event-driven
to avoid frequent context switching by the operating system
Then you have implemented the web flocks model in Spring Cloud Gateway
That's all for this video
If you enjoyed the video, remember to like it
don't forget to coin and triple-combo