Alright
Now looking back
I vaguely remember you had a live stream call with me about two years ago
We had a live-streaming chat about two years ago
I was relatively opposed to it at the time
not really recommend you to pursue graduate studies there
Looking back now, do you have any regrets?
Do you think the gains were significant?
I think it can be divided into two parts
the experience of studying for a master's degree there
I think pursuing a graduate degree can be divided into three aspects
One is obtaining the degree
Obtaining the degree accounts for half of my motivation.
Another aspect is what I can actually learn from the school itself.
Another aspect is what I personally learned during this process.
One is self-learning, the other is what the school taught you.
From the perspective of what the school taught me,
The school didn't teach me anything.
I think this is just a one-year 'water master's degree'
I didn't learn anything
Yes, to be blunt,
Did the school teach you anything?
Don't they have regular classes?
I feel like this one-year taught master's program is just a watered-down degree.
What they learn is pretty much the same as undergraduate studies.
It's essentially just an advanced undergraduate program
How much did the entire cost amount to
the calculable monetary cost would be approximately how much
Actually, because I attended a private institution, I remember public universities should be a bit cheaper.
so I can't really provide a reference for everyone
I live in a relatively prime location in the city center.
living in a better location in the city
If I think you can live frugally
If you can also apply to public schools in Malaysia
it might be possible to cover all costs including tuition fees
200,000 per year
200,000 a year, hmm
Well, you mentioned that the part taught by the school is basically negligible.
the remaining two parts
The remaining part for me is the academic degree, which is
My school ranking is relatively low.
In the current job market, it's considered better than having just a bachelor's degree
but there's still a certain gap compared to regular domestic postgraduate graduates
there's still a bit of a gap
They might think, oh
You're a bit better than those from Tier 1 universities
This is the HR's intuitive impression.
To be honest, I pursued graduate studies just to get a job.
The reason I went for postgraduate studies was to find a job.
Some HR personnel might ask whether your undergraduate degree was preceded by a college diploma.
undergraduate or whether it was previously a college degree
Would he care more about this issue to challenge you
Well
Currently, the companies I have interviewed with
was not mentioned
Of course, when filling out the forms, there are some items you can actually leave blank.
In my case, I didn't mention my associate degree on the resume
You only wrote the degree from Malaysia, yes
Yeah, I can just list the highest degree directly. Many people do it this way.
Yeah, yes, I also recommend writing it this way if possible.
I also recommend writing it this way
Will you include the experience from those two previous jobs?
I will include my work experience
Because currently, the positions I've applied for are mostly social recruitment, although theoretically I can apply for both campus recruitment and social recruitment.
However, for campus recruitment, we currently focus more on the candidate's background after all.
for example, HR
they will definitely see this experience
What was your previous academic background and why did you work for two years before pursuing a master's degree?
two years and then go for a master's degree again
Why choose Malaysia
Do you often have to bear this kind of explanation cost?
Yes, he would ask me, for example
He would ask me, 'What was your undergraduate school?'
then I told him which university I attended for my bachelor's degree
He said why your undergraduate period overlaps with this time
Then I told him
Why I was working while completing my undergraduate degree
Then, he would ask you
Ah, vocational college, what are you? Your vocational college is like this
your diploma is like this
Some of them might not even get to the final step
You might just need to answer the previous questions
Because I didn't lie to the other party, actually I think
I just didn't mention this information
If you ask me, I'll tell you honestly
I will honestly tell you
So you believe the degree itself still adds significant value, right?
right
Right, because if I only had an adult undergraduate degree
He might directly ask about my junior college degree, right
But now it's a bit less for me.
I didn't apply to particularly large companies either
Then there's the third part,
how did you find the learning experience there
Um
Personally, I feel this should account for the largest portion for me,
I feel like I've learned an enormous, enormous, enormous amount of things
It feels like I might have done in one year nearly the equivalent of what a domestic graduate student would do in three years.
Of course, this is a bit of an exaggeration
But I was really quite busy at that time.
How did you learn it?
When I first started studying,
I still had a relatively engineering-oriented mindset
The main goal for the year was to experience the feeling of being a graduate student, engaging in academic research and publishing papers.
Additionally, there is a paper currently under publication.
Of course, these are all my own matters.
I just spontaneously wanted to publish papers
but the teachers and such
Theoretically, you don't need to publish that to graduate
We just need to provide a graduation thesis like we did in undergraduate studies.
Then what about this thesis of yours
Is the requirement high? Is there substantial content?
Is there any substantial content?
or is it just a watered-down thesis like many undergraduate programs in China
I think my graduation thesis was extremely superficial.
It was extremely superficial.
It's nothing but superficial.
the paper I published myself
I think it's pretty good
It can definitely surpass the average level of domestic 985 universities, no problem at all.
No problem
Because the average level of 985 universities is actually not that high.
So what motivated you to write and publish a paper on your own?
I was thinking about applying for a PhD at that time.
publishing a paper could provide better
you'll have a better chance of getting into a better doctoral program, but that's just one of the reasons
On the other hand, if you can really publish in top-tier journals or conferences
It's also very helpful for your job search.
So at that time, I aimed for top-tier conferences and journals, thinking
Can I publish some particularly impressive top-tier conference papers
I saw that you were talking about something in the Live before
read those papers related to distributed systems
What kind of position is Suiyi? What kind of programmer are you?
What position does the programmer hold?
So it's still backend now, right?
Yes, yes
Yeah, whatever.
Casually, do you feel that after going out and studying for a while
Do you feel it's a loss to come back and work on backend development again?
I wouldn't say it's a loss
Just for the half of it being the academic credential, I mean, I went and got it.
The academic qualification alone is roughly worth the money spent.
The salary is indeed higher than before.
And I was able to land my current job
Perhaps the postgraduate experience still holds some value.
Because our company has a preference for recruiting postgraduate students
So what did you learn by yourself? Did you study all the materials from abroad?
Did you study all the materials from abroad?
Or do you still just read...
I've never read anything in Chinese.
Hehehehehe
Ah, I never read in Chinese.
Yeah because I basically only read those top-tier journals and conferences
So, how much do those papers help you with backend-related development?
How much help does it provide for related development work?
What do you think? Quite substantial, I think.
Perhaps it's better to say it leans more towards infrastructure rather than just backend.
perhaps even leaning towards the cutting edge
but the overall mindset is consistent
These are the things we should learn.
Before reading some papers
I would naturally assume that this is correct, this is correct.
Some classmates also mentioned that there don't seem to be specific examples.
I have a lot of examples
OK, then let me randomly mention one
I'll go into more detail from now on.
It's more technical.
More technical, is that okay?
Is it a high-availability algorithm?
a cluster using the Raft algorithm
Generally speaking, this is actually something that companies will definitely use.
It's just that cloud providers have abstracted it away for us.
We generally consider reading from the primary node as strong consistency
Reading from the replica node is not strongly consistent
Slave nodes are eventually consistent.
Later, I only realized what I had deduced after learning a lot on my own.
reading from the master node is not strongly consistent
Why is the single master node not strongly consistent
There may be a presupposed assumption underlying it.
Let me take the Raft protocol as an example
as we generally refer to reading from the master node
This read operation does not involve a log commit, right?
that is, it will not submit a log entry to the follower nodes
It directly returns the query results on the master node, right?
In this scenario, there is an extreme possibility
there is an extreme possibility
your distributed system must consider extreme possibilities
For example, the master node's clock gets suspended
for example, it's hung for a few seconds
During these few seconds of suspension,
The master node itself is unaware that it has been suspended.
Possible events like STW (Stop-The-World) may cause such issues, or similar events may lead to them.
such as prolonged CPU busyness
Then anyway, its clock was suspended.
So another node just elected a new leader, right?
The previously suspended master node has resumed execution, but the client is unaware that the master node has changed.
The client is unaware that the master node has changed.
then send it to the old master node
This old master node just woke up
He says, 'Ah, but I am clearly the master node.'
so I can respond to your read request
At this point, a problem arises
everyone is reading data from the previous master node
then restore to the old primary node
Do I need to synchronize the new data over in order to restore these requests
Should it be handled this way, right?
The ultimate goal we hope to achieve is, for example,
Raft has three nodes
We want to model these three nodes as a state machine
a single-threaded state machine, right
This is what Raft ultimately aims to accomplish.
but if there are other cases, for example
A request has come in
Then you finish processing, and the second request comes in
I found that I couldn't read the first request
This is not allowed.
Specifically, regarding your earlier question about the new master node
an issue arose after the election
My client should directly send Messages to the new master node
However, the client is unaware that the new master node has changed.
then the message sent to the old master node
Theoretically, it should be forwarded to the new primary node
then the correct operation can be performed
these extreme scenarios
Most backend programmers probably wouldn't consider it
But I don't think that's necessarily the case
because many things are essentially code
This is a database with a master-slave cluster.
they will provide a method
asking you whether to read from the master node or the slave node
you would think, there doesn't seem to be any problem with reading from the master node
but if issues arise, you genuinely have no clue
you really know nothing
Right
But indeed, most business development
probably only care about whether I can read the trial read or not
you mentioned something like CPU suspension
This situation leads to a master-slave switchover, which is an extreme case
It's indeed rarely considered
Yes, yes
But it could still happen
Let me give you an example
You pause the virtual machine yourself
and then after three seconds
You press the virtual machine again to release it
Doesn't the virtual machine have that pause function
Then it can simulate similar situations like this.
Learned something new again, right?
I also learned
There might be a lot of similar cases
There are many similar examples
for example, list more than ten similar examples
what I learned during my graduate studies
Can you apply these things in your work now?
Are there any relevant requirements?
Applied in the workplace
Well, maybe, let me think about it
As for the current job,
no direct application
But I think it's more like a shift in the framework of thinking patterns
it is beneficial for my future work
So why did you choose to join this company?
What does it primarily do?
This company is considered a Singaporean one.
It's a company that's considered Singaporean
It's a foreign company, right?
Additionally, I personally prefer the 9-to-6 schedule
We never work overtime.
Let me mention another thing that significantly changed my way of thinking
Ah
At first, I would think that contributing to those open-source projects
or go to
as a committer
very impressive
did something or I think
the open-source architecture I can currently use
must be extremely excellent
until I read and studied
After reading many papers
I found that many open-source projects are quite, well, like that, and there are also many issues, right?
You have a lot of issues, right?
for example, I found in the research papers I read that
According to his statistics on open-source projects
Regarding the number of bugs in databases, about 70-80% have bugs.
Open source projects still have bugs
You can imagine our own systems
The number of bugs is probably close to 100%.
And he only investigated the bugs related to database transactions.
Hey
I remember a few years ago
You were still very interested in many open-source communities
Do you still think about making some contributions or submissions now?
contributions and the like
As for me now
I now prefer to focus on doing more meaningful things.
To be blunt
I feel like this might offend a lot of people
Most developer communities are essentially just cleaning up after others.
the core business logic can only be modified by a select few
but a large number of adaptations are required
For example, if I adapt to this language today or tomorrow
Do you think it's difficult?
My Dubbo can run on Java
In theory, it should definitely be able to run on Go.
Indeed, some people need to adapt it
But this adaptation is also meaningful
But many things are of no technical value at all.
because all you need to do is translate the code in your mind
just go through it once
This might still be considered relatively high-level work among them.
there are a lot of low-level tasks, like actually writing adapters
So this part
It can be directly handed over to current AI programming tools for generation.
That probably hasn't happened yet
Because some AI, the learning materials they use, might be
I don't know either
Because open-source projects are not like our web projects
the style is relatively more uniform
That's how I understand it.
I'm not entirely sure
Regarding the aspect of AI programming
Do you have any new ideas now
Or are there any applications in your work?
For my work, I use AI-powered code writing plugins.
So basically every time, for example, the person I chat with the most
By the end of the day, it's all about AI.
Alright, so will AI replace programmers?
including some newcomers
always feel that with AI
it seems like a lot of code doesn't need to be written by yourself
they just become the ones giving orders
feel like it's hard to grow technically into a senior developer
What suggestions do you have for them?
Those who have pursued postgraduate studies would never say such things. People with graduate degrees are generally exposed to academic content.
Those who have pursued postgraduate studies are generally exposed to academic content.
You ask AI about some cutting-edge technologies
AI hallucinations are quite severe
Current generative AI models are essentially just language completion models.
It's guessing what you're going to say
then guess how you would say it
Just ask him any question
For example, ask the most common question, you ask him
Will Redis lose data
he might tell you it won't
Why wouldn't it?
Because the internet and most people say
Redis has AOF and RDB
I have a cluster strategy
So Redis won't lose data
but 0.49 will lose data
and I've reviewed all these strategies
It will indeed lose data
Because there is a vast amount of incorrect definitions on the internet
AI will have this cognitive bias
but regarding this hallucination issue
I have spoken with some model developers
some manufacturers have also discussed
They believe that the current model conditions
In most cases, it's your own prompt
may be somewhat abstract
not detailed enough
and then lead to most of the hallucinations
What do you think about this?
I think hallucinations are just one issue
Additionally, AI lacks the ability to innovate.
Because it predicts based on what is already known
he believes is most likely to appear next
This means that even if, in Newton's era, there had already been
such powerful computing power as ours
relying on all the learning materials available in the world at that time
still cannot deduce Einstein's theory
because it lacks any ability to innovate
It truly lacks the ability to innovate and create something from scratch.
Because I believe we've now reached this point in time
In fact, many people can engage in this kind of solo development
Like many things in the past few years
a decade ago many things
Many products may require a team to complete.
Of course, because of AI tools
Then he said, and I also agree,
Perhaps it doesn't possess this kind of zero-to-one creative capability
but it's indeed capable of many things, for example
let future products handle frontend development
I used to write very slowly
Many things I even had to learn on the spot.
but with AI
It can quickly help me build up this product
can build this MVP
a product that can be quickly adapted to
So I believe now is a great era for independent development
Moreover, given the current overall employment situation
not particularly prosperous
and many people also face the 35-year-old career crisis
So I believe that there is currently a significant demand for such independent development and side projects.
The demand was relatively strong
So later on, I incubated various initiatives within the entire community
Because I think after all
Most programmers indeed only need to know how to glue together various wheels.
various wheels and glue them together
and then turn it into a car that runs well
I think the reason why AI poses such a big threat to so many people
Because most people may lack the ability to innovate and bring forth new ideas
ability
so they are very afraid
because they are just a CRUD Boy
most developers in China
It's just about one or two years
let alone two years
probably just three years of work experience
and then keep repeating, repeating for six years, repeating for nine years
repeating for 9 years
That's pretty much how it is.
then being replaced by the age of thirty-five
Why do they prefer hiring those with three years of experience?
Because in three years, your technical skills will be mostly sufficient and adequate.
But as you age, your physical stamina
Ah
various aspects of overtime capability
or considering your own salary requirements
family constraints
it's definitely a drawback
From the perspective of company recruitment
all choose three to five years
that's the reason