Hello everyone
I am Sui Yi
This video discusses the gossip algorithm.
This is the most renowned algorithm among broadcast algorithms.
It is used in and applied to registration centers
Consoredis
as well as infrastructure like CASA database and Amazon's DOMO
I found many incorrect statements about the Gossip algorithm online
are all wrong
First of all, it is not a consensus
The algorithm also has nothing to do with eventual consistency
even without any node failures
data loss may also occur
Let's first understand the broadcast algorithm
As the name suggests, the broadcast algorithm
is to distribute data from one node to multiple nodes
For example, when I package a Docker image
or distribute a Spark binary package
or even sending a Messages to the lobby in a game
These actions can be regarded as a broadcast algorithm
Among them, the most common broadcast algorithm is a node
send the value to all nodes
From this perspective, the master-slave synchronization in databases
synchronize messages from the master node of the keeper to the slave nodes
can all be regarded as a type of gossip algorithm
we refer to this one node
a broadcast algorithm that sends messages to all other nodes
collectively referred to as the gossip algorithm
However, the problem with this algorithm is
a bottleneck at a single node may occur
When a node propagates messages to multiple nodes
the deleted traffic is also the outgoing traffic from the server
The traffic of messages is always the bottleneck
after all, in the network
Both uplink and downlink bandwidth are limited
and the CPU copies the data to the network buffer in the kernel
there will also be some overhead
such as the Eureka we learned in second grade
uses this algorithm
That's why
the performance of eureka is not very good
a performance bottleneck may occur when there are too many nodes
So how can we reduce the pressure on the broadcast nodes?
a very simple idea
that is, we send messages to other nodes and then
let other nodes help forward the message
spread the broadcast message like wildfire
In this way, each node makes good use of
its own outgoing bandwidth
The execution speed of the entire broadcast algorithm will not be too slow.
So how do you choose which nodes to broadcast to?
The UNIP algorithm answers by selecting randomly
You can select in the network
send data to any node you know
Then all nodes in the cluster perform similar actions
until the entire cluster receives the message
Hearing this
The audience might wonder
Is it possible for the propagation path to form a loop?
For example, A sends to B, and after B receives it, it sends back to A.
Exactly
To prevent information from being propagated indefinitely
We usually only process the first received message
In the diagram, the red lines actually represent redundant message propagation
In addition
If the message is prematurely completed
So, are some nodes destined to never receive the message?
Here we assume that each node after receiving the message
sent to K nodes
In this graph, this K is two
Based on probability calculation
When there are N nodes in the cluster
and K needs to be greater than log n
this type of message has a higher probability of being sent to all nodes
Doesn't it sound quite unreliable?
Exactly
This unreliable protocol is actually the most commonly used broadcast protocol today
Therefore, we find that
whether it's Consul, Redis, Cassandra, or DynamoDB
the gossip algorithm they use
are only used for metadata updates and service discovery
taking Redis as an example
The data replication between master and slave still adopts the flooding strategy
which means the master node sends all data to the slave nodes
Only the service discovery part uses gossip
In other words, they possess the following characteristics
First, the overall data volume is not too large
Secondly, there's no need to ensure message reliability.
3. Requires complete decentralization
For example, when you detect a node failure
You inform other nodes about this through gossip
However, some nodes were not notified of this in a timely manner
No problem
In the next round, other nodes may still send gossip
notify this overlooked node of the latest cluster status
actually, each node at fixed intervals
randomly select a group of nodes to exchange differential data
thus most nodes missed by the gossip
can reacquire the corresponding messages
but obviously
if your data volume involves a database with millions of records
This is clearly an unrealistic operation
After all, this is essentially a full data synchronization
Therefore, gossip currently cannot be applied to
database replication scenarios
there are many aspects of the gossip protocol that can be optimized
information that needs to be transmitted
You can also dynamically set the deletion of the get value based on the cluster size.
the gossip protocol is simple and easy to use
and it doesn't require you to store all the nodes in the cluster
can work
Therefore, it is also widely used in blockchain scenarios.
When you want to create a cluster
without relying on critical components like ETCD
you might use gossip for service discovery
discovery, um
you asked me
Ali's NEO
Why wasn't the DISCORE protocol mentioned in this video
Then let me ask you
Why would you refer to something without even published papers or specifications as
something referred to as a protocol
Do you expect me to use his Java code
calculate the convergence probability of messages