Alright.
And to all of you,
I've put my materials for this pitch...
and I've also posted it in the comment section.
And you can also see what I'm sharing on the screen.
Alright, I'll get started then.
So, um, at the end of the day, I'm just a student myself.
I'm just a month or two ahead of you all.
And then, after going through this learning experience,
and successfully launched this product.
So really, today is more about having a conversation and learning from each other.
So I thought this would be a great opportunity to share my entire journey with all of you.
So, I want to show you the page I've got up today.
It's a little different from your usual PowerPoint presentation.
I also made this using Codex.
It's an interactive webpage, you could say.
And as it happened, I still had just a little bit of my quota left.
and just went ahead and built it.
So, today, what I mainly want to do is walk you through a...
It was based on a real pain point that I, and I alone, had while studying for my exams.
And then, how I gradually turned that into...
into a publicly available, launched product that I can share with all of you.
And now, let me walk you through the entire process.
including the pitfalls I've run into,
The detours I took and the methods I used.
And the name of the product is 'Shua Ti Bao'.
Its original name was Learn or Die.
Basically, 'study or die.'
Later on, during a product pitch event, I was talking with this expert, whose online handle is 'Product Meituan Sister'...
So after I'd talked it over with the mentors,
I mean, it wasn't just my product that needed to be streamlined.
my product name should also, ideally, just tell people directly and objectively what it does.
What problem is my product actually solving?
It's basically all about solving the problem of practicing tons of questions.
So, my idea was,
You need to take all your scattered study materials,
So, after you've tossed all your stuff in there—questions, textbooks, all of it,
And this whole process forms a complete loop.
and give you that motivation you need.
So, it's like, um, you're running all that information through a quality check.
And this entire process will help you get a clear picture of everything.
to help you study for your exams.
So, for everyone joining us today...
I'm guessing you're also here to learn about the Vibe Coding method.
or even create your own AI product.
And I know this is gonna sound a bit shameless, but...
Or maybe you'd like to try out my product.
Or maybe, just maybe, you'd like to follow my journey too.
So yeah, you can all go ahead and check it out for yourselves.
Alright, let's get started.
So first off, let me tell you why I decided to build this product.
And the reason was crystal clear.
So, the starting point for this product was simply the fact that I was preparing for an exam at the time.
So, on May 23rd...
I took the exam for the International Product Manager certification.
the NPDP.
And at that time, my work was incredibly hectic, so finding any time at all...
So, whenever I did manage to squeeze in some time,
any time I could squeeze in for studying was incredibly scarce.
Especially for exams like the PMP,
and the content for exams like NPDP.
Actually, a lot of the content is extracted from...
key points extracted from the textbooks.
And some of them come with a question bank.
Yeah, anyone who's actually taken the exam would know this.
But the thing is, there are some problems with that.
For instance, because the examination bodies are from overseas institutions,
like the IMA in the US, for instance.
When they translate the exam questions,
you end up with some really forced, literal translations.
So, for some questions, even if you understand every single Chinese character,
you still can't figure out what the question is actually asking.
So at this point, all you have on hand are these materials.
or pre-recorded video lectures,
Or you have, you know, those... what do you call them... question banks.
But the thing is, even these question banks aren't always accurate.
That's because they're often created by some of the top educators and scholars in the country.
and then the explanations they write for them.
Sometimes, they don't even have an answer key, let alone an explanation.
So what you need is someone who really gets you,
Whether it's an AI tutor,
or even a senior who's been through it.
to help you with quick memorization,
or walk you through the reasoning behind this part, explaining why it's the correct answer.
Or it can show you exactly which page in the textbook that question is on.
This was incredibly important to me.
something that could help me prepare for the exam quickly.
Alright, so let me start by sharing a bit about my own situation.
So, what I had were the PDFs of my textbooks saved in a cloud drive.
And on my phone, I had...
So, I had this study app from a platform called 'Xiao E Tong' for practicing questions.
And for the questions I didn't get, there were no explanations for them either.
So, I'd just take a screenshot and save it to my camera roll.
And then, of course, I also had the physical textbooks on hand.
So, it was basically all this stuff.
And then you realize, 'Okay, I need to learn something.'
It felt like I had to spread out all the maps at once.
And what's even more brutal is what happens after you've finished all those problems.
Or if you're just grinding through problems on one single app,
or just on your browser finding questions to practice.
Sometimes, the questions can be really similar.
and you forget why you even picked that answer in the first place.
What on earth is the right answer?
Sometimes you just forget, you know?
So, um, that's on top of what I was just telling you guys.
I needed someone to walk me through the logic behind this particular analysis.
So, after going through that entire process,
Yeah, exactly. This entire process... you couldn't cover it with just one single product.
or even a single phone, to tie it all together.
So I thought to myself, what if I could build a product to solve this?
my basic profile,
Then, my PDF materials,
My practice questions, or my mistakes,
and even my AI tutor, all in one place.
So I'd have to get dead serious, armed with just a textbook in one hand and my phone in the other.
and I'd be all set for my exam prep.
And so, this is how the idea for this product was born.
Alright, so today, I'm going to share my experience with you all.
So, when I was working on coding and the product,
So, where should we start? What are the key things we need to focus on?
First off, let's talk about this from a Product Manager's perspective.
It's about defining the problem clearly.
What we're doing here is clarifying the problem.
So basically, you can think of it this way.
So, let's say I come to you and tell you I want to build a product.
And then, you might go to your boss and be like, 'Hey...'
Hey, can you just handle that thing?
But that's obviously not going to work.
So, how can we know if we're on the right track?
The key is to clearly define the problem.
It's just like what I was explaining to you all a moment ago.
What was the pain point for me?
What problem am I trying to solve?
Or, let's say, when you're talking to your friend.
So, I thought, 'Hey, I want to build a product.'
So that's basically the solution we came up with.
If they get it,
Well, I think when it comes to this problem for the AI...
it's already able to comprehend it.
Or, for us as individuals,
He explained it clearly.
The second point is to streamline your solutions.
So, like the teacher mentioned in that screen recording just now, the product needs to be streamlined.
In product development, there's a technical term for this called MVP.
Which stands for Minimum Viable Product.
So, why do I think this is so important?
Basically, you need to define what you can cut out.
It's like in our daily lives,
I'm not sure if any of you have worked in the internet industry,
or just other work experiences in general.
You know, there are always these business folks who say, 'I want it all.'
And then, the product manager would come along and say, 'You know, we can actually cut this part too.'
or that we could trim down a bit.
Because what they're after is getting something live as quickly as possible.
a verifiable minimum viable product.
So, in the same way, this 'Problem-Solving Pro' is also my personal...
So, when I first started building the Problem-Solving Treasure...
Well, it all started when I saw my instructor, iCoder.
As he was teaching us,
he shared the features of his own WeChat assistant.
And the thing about me is, I'm the kind of person who really likes to...
by leveraging the capabilities of other existing products,
build other product features.
So just like with my WeChat assistant,
It can help me take a photo and then recognize the text.
to store my basic learning profile,
and the ability to answer my questions.
So, I just took his code, copied and pasted the whole thing, no changes made.
including building out the WeChat channel.
I tried to do so much more, and... it all just failed spectacularly.
This was the first step in my attempt.
But luckily, I pulled the plug right away.
I decided to build it from scratch.
So, the second step is also super important.
Alright, step three. This is, of course, the core of it all.
Basically, you just let an AI handle it.
When I was making it, I used, uh, CC—you know, Claude Code.
Yeah, and the instructors are also there to guide you.
So, it's about how to use Claude Code to do it.
Well, I had actually looked into Claude Code on my own before.
Codex is another one I've looked into on my own.
So...
Back then, I used Claude Code for the design and for the basic product setup.
And then there's CC... or, what's it called again...
As for Codex,
I usually just use it to write up some of these materials, you know.
Ah, like the materials I'm sharing with you all right now.
And stuff for WeChat Official Accounts, and things like that.
And it's a really interesting thing.
So I wanted to share something with you all as well.
So, Claude Code has a feature called Claude Design.
which is for creating prototypes.
It can generate both a wireframe and a high-fidelity prototype.
So, back when I was designing the product,
Didn't he just mention this to everyone?
I mean, that was the problem I had, right?
So, when you're designing a product like this,
Something really important to keep in mind is,
You need to know what the user is supposed to do, what they should click on, after they get into the product.
And it's all about making sure every step just flows naturally.
all the way until they log out and exit the app completely.
The entire user flow of this product is seamless.
But it's really hard to express that in words.
to spell it all out clearly.
And at this point, if you try to design this all by yourself,
Whether it's Figma or something else,
Specifically, drawing it without AI.
it's definitely going to be very time-consuming.
So, with design systems in place,
or in the case of an A.I.-powered Figma,
the prototype can be completed in no time.
And the human-computer interaction also turns out to be really good.
For example, think about the kind of product I want to create.
This means the entire user flow can be finalized very quickly.
So, you guys can go ahead and give it a try.
Once you've got the prototype sorted out,
And once you've ironed out the basic user flows,
Then you can have your Coder do the job.
everything will go very smoothly.
And you'll know exactly what to expect from them.
Now, the fourth part is actually where I spent the most time.
which is acceptance testing.
At my day job, we call this UAT, by the way.
Or, as we call it, user acceptance testing, or UAT.
So, why is that?
Because at the earlier stage, I had already made sure the core, main workflow was functioning properly.
And that's good enough.
So, if you're on your phone and scrolling right now,
or flipping through it on the web version.
and flip all the way to the last page.
You can go ahead and check out the product page.
On the whole product page now, there are actually quite a few features.
But in reality, when I first started building this feature,
weren't that many.
So, besides a user profile...
After the profile was set up, there weren't many options for adding questions either.
So the main focus is on practicing questions.
Then, for the notebook of incorrect answers, and the purely chat-based content over here, they were all very...
So it was, uh, very simple.
It's so simple, it's basically just a few words and pictures.
And all these iterative features? I didn't build any of them.
And things like feedback channels,
I didn't get around to those either.
And that's something I added after I launched the product.
and had some free time
and gradually built it out.
So, after the entire main workflow was all set up,
So I went through it as fast as I could, completely in the user's shoes.
Uh...
For instance, did I run into any issues while importing?
um, and then, when it's identifying the content, did it get anything wrong?
Then I'd switch to a different textbook.
Or did it just fail to import again?
So I went through and addressed all of these kinds of issues.
So basically, once you've gone through all these issues,
The whole product was just a prototype.
and you can get it launched. Alright?
Right, so next up, I'm gonna start from, uh...
So I'll just briefly touch on this.
So, like I was just saying,
So, I started with my own needs.
And by the way, I didn't just copy my instructor's, you know, AI assistant project.
I mean, the code for that WeChat assistant.
So yeah, that's the thing. What do you guys think?
It's best to just build it from scratch.
and when it comes to just copying other people's code...
And it's actually pretty tough, you know.
And odds are, you're just going to break something.
And for the most part, those of us who just work a nine-to-five can probably relate to this a little bit.
So, when you take over someone else's project,
You have to put in a lot more effort just to understand what the project is all about,
So, the cost for that is just a little too high.
And the third point, which I've actually just touched on,
You should really try to get the prototype and user flow designed first.
So once we've refined the product and narrowed down the scope,
So, let's discuss what other crucial features I'm still missing—those P1 and P2 level requirements.
and then we can slowly add them in.
Then, we can gradually identify any pain points in the user experience.
to get them done and fix them.
Once that's all set, we can finally launch it.
And then, I'd like to share a few things.
So, here it is. You can just take a look, and that's it.
So, there are a few things you can pay attention to.
One thing is, when the product goes live,
We need to make sure that the user experience at launch is actually viable.
So, as we were just saying,
And what I found during user testing was...
So, when I import this PDF,
Because, you know, the entire PDF might have, um...
You could have over 200 questions.
And when it tries to split them up,
it would take a really long time to wait.
And that's something I didn't take into account when I first started designing it.
And I figured users wouldn't want to wait that long on this page either.
If you exit, you have to re-import everything all over again.
So, eventually,
little by little, making this feature feel almost impossible to implement.
And while it's importing, you can go ahead and do other things on the side.
or just exit the app and do something else.
And another thing is, I can import the question bank at the same time.
and my study materials, all at the same time.
And on top of that, there's one more thing.
I don't think I've written this down here.
And there's one more thing I want to mention.
I think, when it comes to any AI product, the most important thing is honesty.
So, for my product, that's also the most crucial part.
Essentially, it's about giving the user a sense of security.
So, when I'm importing a large batch of files,
I can't just have the entire page freeze and do nothing.
The best-case scenario is to have an interactive page.
This lets everyone know that I'm actually working on it.
It's just that you'll have to wait for, like, another...
say, five or ten minutes.
And also, keep your users in the loop on your overall progress.
And I think this part is pretty important.
If you're serious about actually launching a product,
And another thing is, you know, injecting real-world scenarios into the mix.
So, once the product is actually out there,
So, what's its core competitive edge?
My core competitive edge is: it's all on my phone.
that can handle my entire exam prep process, from practice questions to the final test.
And on top of that, it's basically an AI-powered solution, right?
At the very least, you have this study coach right on your phone,
and get a complete picture of your learning progress.
For example, when I was setting up my profile,
So it knows that my exam is on May 23rd.
Then, as you're chatting with the AI coach,
Now, since I've already been chatting with it for a bit here,
And things like recording the screen, capturing questions, and so on.
it'll give you an update on your current status.
and which of your incorrect answers are still left to review.
It even gets to this point... um, you can probably get a better idea from the screenshot.
It even happens when you're just chatting with it about something fun.
It'll tell you, "Hey, don't get distracted."
So yeah, that's pretty much how it works.
It does this by understanding the context.
And then, by feeding it more real user data,
This makes the AI feel like your own personal tutor.
And that makes it feel even more real.
And I think this is a pretty key point.
a special touch, I'd say.
And so, for my entire product development journey,
You can go ahead and open it up to take a look.
So, I've pulled up the corresponding screenshots for you here.
So, I've broken down the entire product flow into six steps.
The first step is to create a study profile.
So once you're in, just register. It's super simple.
Because, um, this is also something I need to work on going forward.
So, first things first, once you've created your profile...
go ahead and add the course materials.
So, once you've entered the教材...
you'll get a set of practice questions.
You can either add them in, or you can just type them out manually.
Or you can import photos.
You can also take a photo with your phone, or import a PDF.
and have the AI auto-generate it.
And that creates a question bank for you to practice with.
And this question bank even has a validation feature.
And there's also the error notebook feature.
So, this mistake book automatically adds questions whenever you answer them incorrectly,
Or can you manually add them yourself.
And it tracks how many times you've gotten it wrong.
And what's the overall error rate?
And for the questions you get wrong, you have to answer them correctly three times,
and is removed after you get it right three times. It's these kinds of small, incremental features.
It was all built up through gradual iteration.
And then there's also the AI study-buddy chat feature.
So, what this means is that the whole thing, you know, just looks very...
It's a very clean and streamlined product line.
Okay, so that's pretty much the whole picture.
And for that, I'd also like to give a huge thank you.
So, for our...
The mentors from the AI bootcamp,
And I want to give a special shout-out to icoder and Beige especially.
And what impressed me the most was, well...
So, from what I've gathered, on our end here...
it's a team that has a really friendly, peer-to-peer vibe.
And especially, um, I'm someone who tends to be a bit of a perfectionist when it comes to product ideas.
Oh.
And so,
If I haven't figured out the entire user journey for the product, and what the first step should be,
my second and third steps, and what its future direction would be,
I honestly found it really hard to even get started.
I just went for it.
So, when I was talking to the instructors at Beige and iCoder about this idea,
And the advice they gave me was, "Don't overthink it."
The first step to success is just to get started.
So, that night, when I was talking about my needs and my ideas...
I think I had, like, five or six product ideas.
For instance, I could make a supply chain platform.
Because I was originally in the supply chain industry,
and I probably wanted to build something that wasn't so dependent on...
Well, something for generating surveys.
a platform.
But then, I'd also have to worry about issues like getting traffic from the survey and all that.
So then, I had this idea for an app called 'Shuati Bao'—a 'Drill Master' for exam questions.
Because I was in the middle of studying for an exam myself.
I also wanted to create something that's like a pet.
But then again, I had all these worries, like, what if this and that...
Or maybe there are already similar things on the market,
So, I had a ton of concerns.
But at this point,
The instructors would tell us to calm down, take a step back, and say...
But anyway,
So, building something from the ground up is a great place to start and get some experience.
And then, after putting my own judgment into the mix,
I wanted to build something real, something that could genuinely solve a user's problem.
and it felt like a small victory in itself.
So in the end, I decided to build a product that first and foremost, would solve my own problems.
And, I was pretty happy about that.
At the very least, I could get it launched.
So, after going through the product requirement phase I just mentioned,
And later on, there was even the whole website registration process.
That whole process of registering the domain name and getting it all legal and stuff.
So, going forward, I might gradually, um, let's say after you exit the current page...
So for now,
I don't have, like, all sorts of mobile verification checks and stuff like that.
This is because I'm making it openly available for everyone to use.
And later on, if I come up with other ideas or needs,
and launch it on a real app store,
And of course, I'll do my best to keep improving these features as well.
And also, uh, this part here... let me click on it... this is the admin dashboard in the back-end.
And for the long term,
So, if we stick with it in the long run,
I'll just check the user feedback.
For instance, I've already addressed a few pieces of user feedback here.
So, I've got a newly launched feature for you.
Well, I still feel that, um, whether you're building an AI product or working as a...
Once you've decided to get into this field, taking that first step is incredibly important.
And persistence is also key.
And we can all communicate with each other,
and grow together.
and go further on this journey.
and find more inspiration.
and help each other succeed.
Growing together is also incredibly important.
So I hope we can all communicate more with each other.
So yeah, let's communicate more. That's all I have for now.