find a place where i could you know when you're in the street
but hands to come
and turned out fixes to roll the sun by the
right that we see in the star
i'm going to the catch fi
i believe there's a change to come
i'll never know that we never run
more sign in the sun
the second i will look at norm
the riding in the world
don't turn the light on fogo
over the world away
i'm fire in my mind of the way with me in your
i'm forever ru
啊啊啊啊
啊啊啊啊啊
don't you know
you know
i know
i love you
you you you you you you
i say not
sorry
it's slime for another
it's not getting better
better better
can i do with myself
when we keep on up to the best day
not saying
not sorry
lime for you
looking for the matter that you
looking for another
yeah
when your heart is loving all my pain to carry
take the fall off the floor
the ghost and touch you
i want to love you
you don't have to hide
and you look when you saw me
no more festa night there in the night of the stars by
looking in the mirror
just before the darkness
the darkness
so it's just what you are in your own
everything is in the moment
outside
clap as the sun goes down
该死的放不下
when the world stop spinning around and gravity brings
you down
don't give it
we're no way too much today
and nobody seems to care
don't give him through your hands to help us
啊啊啊
啊啊啊啊啊
it turns out that this was the best thing
you ever been to me
everyone can we change in the way
you want that's so truck when you break your feat m
if you ready for love
every part of you
say you break your heart to you know
we are the world
and you will be on me on my tom
you are not alone
you're not alone
when the night has come to breaking b
and
you can only breed
what you can
i'm not alone
you are not alone
逃避
莫非这个头像有没
but
let it go
you call this part
走过的不错的一天
我的记忆而过
in a del
we are dreamers
we are dreamer
一夜寂寞
we are dreamers