In modern terms,
on a 10-year scale,
we actually believe fusion might be in physics,
for the entire human civilization,
the most impactful thing,
it is also worldwide,
from the perspective of international joint projects,
it should be the second most expensive project,
the first being the space station.
International Space Station
even after this is accomplished
by taming fusion
to use it for
propulsion in propellantless space travel
engines
it won't be smooth
there are a lot of challenges in between
each step keeps presenting new issues
And the closer you get to the real thing
the bigger your problems become
the more issues you encounter
If you haven’t climbed this mountain
and you fall down
what would you think
It would be such a pity, right
Hello
Hello everyone
Welcome to the Zhang Xiaojun Business Interview Series
I'm Xiaojun
This is a business interview show that provides first-hand, high-density information
In 2021
Sam
Altman made a personal investment of $375 million in an American nuclear fusion startup
This was his largest personal investment to date
Helium proudly claimed
Hylia boasts
We will complete it by 2028
the world's first 50-megawatt fusion power plant
Elon Musk, however, has a different view
He once said there's an endless
and inexhaustible nuclear fusion reactor above us—the sun
He believes that solar power is the fundamental solution to humanity's energy issues
However, in the eyes of many
controlled nuclear fusion remains the holy grail of the energy sector
As we advance towards AHI today
Energy will be the greatest bottleneck for the evolution of civilization.
After all, JI might not fear humans,
but it certainly fears power outages.
In this episode, I’ve invited a startup from China working on controlled nuclear fusion,
the founder of Energy Origin, Yang Zhao, to chat with us.
Compared to AI, controlled nuclear fusion is a much longer road,
a far less traveled path in the entrepreneurial world.
It almost faces one of the most complex physical challenges in human history,
one of the most intricate physics problems ever encountered.
Standing at the intersection of technology and human civilization, exploring technical frontiers
on the show
Yang Zhaobang gave us a
cutting-edge science communication about controlled nuclear fusion
As a participant in China's controlled nuclear fusion endeavor
he also provided a relatively clear calculation of how much more investment is needed for humanity to harness controlled nuclear fusion
and the financial resources required
as well as the distance we still have to travel
We also discussed what the more distant future might hold
When energy becomes infinite, our world
how will our civilization evolve?
let's progress together with AI.
Hello
Yang Zhao
Let's start by greeting the audience.
Hello everyone.
Let's kick off with some quick questions and answers.
Company Name
Energy Origin was founded in June 2021
We have completed two rounds of financing
Our current valuation is just under 2.3 billion
We are still in the R&D investment phase, so we are not yet profitable
We are currently in the R&D investment phase
You are 34 years old
Your MBTI is likely INTJ
We are currently at Energy Origin in Lingang, Shanghai
Is Tesla's Shanghai factory located around here?
I remember it was quite a distance away when I came here.
But it is quite a distance.
But it’s all in the Lingang area.
Why did you choose Lingang?
Actually, the main reason was to meet the deadline for the first installation.
We managed to build and operate it within two years.
So our requirements for the factory were quite specific.
As well as the infrastructure, like power supply for the factory.
The timeline was quite tight.
So, regarding this matter,
the areas we could choose from were quite limited.
At that time, the Lingang area,
provided us with the factory building we are in now.
It came with a very complete set of infrastructure.
And basically, the factory was ready to move into.
Furthermore, the power supply and other facilities were already well-provided.
So, this was a crucial reason at the time.
We chose this area in Lingang
Before we start this episode
We're going to talk about controlled nuclear fusion
Some key terms might be quite distant from both the audience and me
So let's start with some more common
And very important terms
To give everyone a basic introduction
First, could we cover some of the most fundamental concepts
For example, what is nuclear fission
What is nuclear fusion?
What's the difference between them?
Nuclear fission or nuclear fusion?
These all fall under nuclear energy.
The basic idea of nuclear energy is to harness nuclear reactions,
where the total mass of the reaction products is less than that of the reactants,
the total mass of the raw materials.
This mass difference,
ultimately translates into energy according to Einstein's energy equation.
It will be released as energy, right?
The difference between fission and fusion lies in
Fission uses heavier atomic nuclei
By splitting the nucleus into several lighter nuclei
This process results in the final products
Having a total mass lower than the original heavier nucleus
Such a process, yeah
Generally speaking
The material used for fission
These are elements with strong radioactivity
and a higher atomic number.
Fusion, on the other hand, is the opposite.
It involves using a few, individually lighter atomic nuclei,
usually two or so,
and making them collide with each other,
merging into a heavier atomic nucleus.
However, the total mass of the final reaction products
is less than the total mass of the initial atomic nuclei.
It still ends up being smaller
So this process is also one of converting mass into energy
If we talk about something people are more familiar with, it's fission
It’s actually the principle behind atomic bombs
And fusion corresponds to the principle of hydrogen bombs
Why do people always add two words when talking about nuclear fusion
The qualifier is controlled nuclear fusion
What would happen if nuclear fusion were uncontrolled
It would turn into atomic and hydrogen bombs
So basically, the use of nuclear energy
involves first releasing this energy
which is the first step we initially calculate
whether it's through fission
we first developed the atomic bomb
and later, we controlled the release of this energy according to our needs
in a relatively stable manner as designed
which led to the development of fission nuclear power plants
and in the case of fusion, the first application was also the hydrogen bomb
So the next step is to understand the principle of fusion reactions.
Based on our design,
according to the power we need,
according to our requirements,
and then to stably output it.
This is what controlled nuclear fusion is all about.
Next, I'll explain two terms.
One is tokamak,
and the other is high-temperature superconductivity.
Tokamak
will also be one of our frequently used terms, um
Tokamak is part of the approach to controlled nuclear fusion
one of the technical routes to achieve controlled nuclear fusion
Overall speaking
achieving controlled nuclear fusion generally involves three main approaches
such as the most common form of controlled nuclear fusion that we all know
this thing
is actually the sun
Stars
Stars rely on gravity to gather a large number of atoms
making their density sufficiently high
ultimately triggering a fusion reaction
constantly releasing energy
like our Sun, for instance
However, Earth cannot generate such a massive gravitational force
so this approach is not feasible
Therefore, humans have employed two methods
One is called magnetic confinement
The other is called inertial confinement
Within this branch
the tokamak actually belongs to magnetic confinement
in this broad category
The core idea of magnetic confinement is
to generate a specific configuration of magnetic field
to confine the extremely hot
plasma within this magnetic field
Don't let it come into direct contact with other solid devices
This is the basic idea of magnetic confinement
But what does the magnetic field actually look like
This is actually what distinguishes the different branches under magnetic confinement
Among them, the one currently most widely studied
And in terms of experimental results obtained
Has the highest parameters
And based on the experimental results we obtained,
the parameter is at its highest
and has already achieved
a technology pathway that can balance energy output and input
it's the tokamak
the core idea of the tokamak is
this technology pathway was initially proposed by the Soviet Union
first, its magnetic field is shaped like a donut
this donut shape
since it is a torus
it is a closed system
So we use such a magnetic field configuration
to confine the high-temperature plasma within this torus
and then we increase the temperature of the plasma
while continuously confining it with the magnetic field
this plasma
keeping the entire high-temperature plasma within this area
within the range of the torus I designed
to facilitate these collisions
to produce fusion and release energy
This is a basic idea of Tu and Mark, right?
Of course.
In addition to having a toroidal
or doughnut-shaped magnetic field,
it also has a toroidal current.
This is a crucial component of it.
It features this toroidal magnetic field,
and a two-dimensional axially symmetric magnetic field with a toroidal current,
creating this type of magnetic field configuration.
We named it Tokamak
Yes, the high-temperature superconducting tokamak
As I mentioned earlier
The tokamak requires a very strong magnetic field
This magnetic field is used to confine the plasma
So, how do we generate such a magnetic field
The method is to create a magnet by passing a current through it
A large current is passed through the magnet
The magnetic field is generated by the current
So, what kind of material is used to make the magnets?
This has led to several generations of tokamaks.
For magnets, they are crucial for tokamaks,
or more specifically, the most critical component in magnetic confinement systems.
Changes in the core material can impact the entire device,
as well as the design and integration of all other subsystems.
Overall,
tokamaks have gone through roughly three stages,
starting from the earliest phase.
Since everyone was just aiming to conduct an experiment
to see how the performance would be
most of the early tokamaks
used copper for their magnets
Copper, as a conventional conductor
tends to heat up during operation
because a large current is passed through it
it generates heat
so when the parameters are high
People found that a tokamak made with conventional conductors
actually can't operate for very long periods.
It's typically in the range of seconds.
After about ten seconds, it has to be shut down.
Otherwise, the copper itself will heat up,
and the magnets could even melt.
So it can only run in short pulses.
To conduct short-pulse experiments.
Of course.
Copper can be cooled at room temperature,
of course, it can also be cooled by lowering the temperature,
but most of the time, it uses water cooling as the cooling method.
So for copper conductor devices,
the engineering complexity is relatively low.
It doesn't require creating a vacuum and extremely low-temperature environment
to operate.
Compared to superconducting devices,
this is why.
In the early stages, when we were exploring plasma performance,
we used the simplest method in engineering first,
which was to use copper to build the device,
to get experimental results in a short time, right?
But as we moved forward,
with the parameters getting higher and higher,
and considering the future commercialization of fusion,
you can't use copper to build the device anymore,
or its operational lifespan would be insufficient.
And the energy it consumes itself
might be even greater than the energy you generate
So people started to think
about using this superconducting material to make magnets
This has actually gone through different stages
For example, some magnets use superconducting materials
while others use copper
But the first to integrate these comprehensively
is indeed
This is the device located in the east of Hefei.
It's the first fully superconducting tokamak.
What it means is that all of its magnetic coils
are made using low-temperature superconducting materials.
A complete tokamak.
To build a superconducting tokamak,
you need to create a high-vacuum environment,
allowing the magnets to operate within this vacuum.
Otherwise, the heat leakage in the middle would be an issue.
This kind of thermal convection
prevents heat conduction from occurring
a magnet can operate at minus 269 degrees
such an extremely low-temperature environment
and you also need to prevent heat radiation
so you create a cryogenic flask
which is a low-temperature
used to minimize heat radiation
this environment that envelops the exterior of the magnet
So a superconducting tokamak
The engineering complexity of a cryogenic superconducting tokamak is quite high
This is also around the year 2000
For example, EAST began construction in 2022
And was completed around 2006 or 2007
Later on, South Korea has a device called K-STAR
Which is also a cryogenic superconducting device
Moving forward
Moving forward,
You're talking about the one in Japan,
which recently built a new large-scale, high-parameter device,
called the GT60SA.
It's also a cryogenic superconducting device.
There are only three full-scale cryogenic superconducting devices in the world,
and this is one of them.
Although it can operate at very low temperatures,
it is capable of running for extended periods.
For example, we can see it can run for up to 1,000 seconds.
Such operational records are valid.
But a major issue lies in
If I use this technical approach to build a
commercial power generation facility,
a key parameter is that I need sufficient output energy,
the output energy must far exceed the energy consumed.
This is a power generation facility.
Its approximate size would be similar to the one currently under construction in
France, known as ITER.
This apparatus is led by the EU
with the participation of China, the US, and
four other countries making up a total of six.
The investment
has already reached 25 billion euros for this apparatus.
And the project has a long history.
Its design was completed in the 90s.
Construction truly began in 2006,
and the latest news is that it has been delayed until 2034.
So it's roughly a construction period
of about 30 years for such a facility
because it is extremely large
which brings us to a disadvantage of low-temperature superconductors
if this material is used to build a tokamak
the magnetic field of this low-temperature superconducting material has its limits
it can't be too high
or it will turn into something like copper
and it will have resistance
It can't run for long periods.
This means the device has to be built on a massive scale.
To achieve a significant positive energy gain.
As a result, the construction time would be exceptionally long.
The costs would be extremely high.
And when it's finally built,
The cost per unit of electricity could be over a hundred times that of coal power.
It's a scientific research facility.
Not a practical solution in our view.
If your goal is to be cheaper than the cost of rockets,
and even much cheaper in the future,
then the technical challenges of this path are very significant.
How to reduce the cost by a factor of 100 or more,
So after 2018,
there was a new idea,
We use a new type of superconducting material,
This was actually after 2015,
around 2018.
It's only recently been achieved in engineering
industrially, the mass production of high-temperature superconducting materials
The advantage of this new material lies in
its operation at low temperatures
its critical magnetic field strength is much higher than that of low-temperature superconductors
it can be more than twice as high
at least double
The benefits of a high magnetic field include
the ability to construct
Under the same performance conditions
For example, under the same energy gain conditions
I can reduce the size of the device by two orders of magnitude
This essentially means
That the construction cost is also reduced by about two orders of magnitude
Because for any custom-made equipment
The mass or volume largely determines the cost
So this is using high-temperature superconducting materials
Compared to low-temperature superconductors
They are all superconductors
and the operating temperatures don't differ much
roughly from 4K to 10K or 20K
which is about -269 degrees Celsius
to possibly -259 degrees Celsius
the temperatures are all very low, indeed
but the magnetic field strength
the critical magnetic field strength is completely different
significantly enhancing the magnetic field strength
Then we can significantly reduce the size of the device
The benefit we gain
is that the final cost of this device
or in other words, the cost of electricity generated by fusion
can be significantly reduced
ultimately reaching a level comparable to that of coal power
and in the future, when production scales up
it could be an order of magnitude lower than coal power
So, high-temperature superconductors and low-temperature superconductors are both material names
Then use these two different materials to build the tokamak device
The high-temperature superconductor has a smaller volume
and a lower cost
Why can it be less expensive
with a smaller size
This actually stems from the past six or seven decades
of fusion research
where researchers have used hundreds of devices
and conducted thousands of experiments to summarize this rule
I aim to achieve a sufficiently high energy gain
Energy gain refers to the ratio of output power to input power
It's the energy produced divided by the energy consumed
This is called energy gain
It means it doesn’t just break even
If the critical value equals one
That’s breaking even
When you want to build a power station
You need it to be much greater than one
For example, ten times.
Your output power is ten times the input, right?
After all, there are losses during the actual operation, right?
So, when it comes to energy gain,
it's actually determined by a physical parameter,
known as the triple product.
Simply put, it's the plasma density multiplied by the temperature,
multiplied by the confinement time,
these three numbers multiplied together.
So it's called the triple product
When these three numbers are multiplied together
Under a relatively very complex unit
To reach ten to the power of twenty
Then the first principles of physics can tell you
Regardless of the method you use to achieve it
Using Dao and Chuan as the ingredients
When this triple product reaches ten to the power of twenty
It's roughly Q at one
Of course, if you're just a bit higher
within the magnitude of 21 to 22 powers
the energy gain Q can go from one to infinity
and it can grow very quickly
similar to an avalanche
once it crosses the break-even point
it will tweak the parameters a bit
and its energy gain multiplier can increase significantly
so what does this logic tell us?'
If you want to boost the energy gain,
you just need to improve the triple product.
Because the triple product determines the energy gain, right?
Over the past six or seven decades of research,
it has been found that the most effective way to enhance the triple product in engineering
is either to make the device large enough,
or to make the magnetic field strong enough.
These are the two methods.
Isn't it the product of temperature, density, and energy confinement time?
Right, shouldn't one of these three values be changed?
These three values can't be directly altered.
It's like a device that's set up.
The outcomes are determined by its performance characteristics.
Or even greater.
Which value can be changed?
Actually, they all have an impact.
And a key feature of the product of three is:
If you solely increase any one parameter,
Most likely, the other two parameters will also decrease.
And this will affect the overall performance of your device.
The total performance of the product will decline.
So, the optimization you're actually doing is on this product.
You're optimizing the result of this product.
And this result is closely tied to the parameters of the device.
It's related to many parameters of the device.
It's a fairly complex system.
And we don't have a good theory for the heterogeneity principle yet.
to derive what it's actually related to
so the final approach is through thousands of experiments
then we fit out such a calibration rate
because different devices have different sizes
they have different magnetic fields
the plasma will have different shapes
the plasma current will have different magnitudes, and so on
there are many parameters
and people have summarized some basic rules
For tokamaks,
different technical approaches
have different scaling rates.
For tokamaks,
the triple product is proportional to the magnetic field to the power of 3.5,
and proportional to the linear dimensions of the device.
Although in physics, the larger radius,
it is roughly equivalent to the linear dimensions of the device,
proportional to the linear dimensions of the device to the power of 2.5.
So what does that mean?
If I can double the magnetic field strength,
I can roughly reduce the linear dimensions of the device
to about 30% of its original size.
And we know that for a device,
a custom-made piece of equipment,
the cost is actually proportional to its volume,
which means this 30% cubed,
resulting in a reduction to about 2% of the original cost.
So the key is to increase the magnetic field strength.
This can reduce the size and cost.
Right, exactly.
We actually touched on this earlier.
Another key term is the Q factor.
It essentially refers to energy gain.
If it’s one, then it’s break even.
There are generally two key metrics.
One is greater than one.
It's more than ten pairs.
More than one.
It's a fundamental point.
Otherwise, you're less than one.
It's definitely a power-consuming device.
But actually, you were just more than one.
It's also a power-consuming device.
After all, there will still be losses in the energy conversion process.
So generally speaking,
A fusion power plant
Its design varies depending on the size and scale of the power plant
The design range is roughly from Q equals five to
Q equals thirty
You can design a fusion power plant within this range
Right
So it's much greater than one
Generally, it's an order of magnitude larger
So everyone considers this project feasible
The general standard is set at Q equals ten.
Now, the highest level globally is what Q value?
This figure represents the highest record.
It's the highest Q value achieved by a tokamak.
This was back in the 90s.
In the 90s,
it was equivalent to using a knife.
The experiment wasn't conducted directly with a knife.
I used the raw material of a knife for the experiment.
However, in physics,
there is a widely recognized method
which is to assume I know the properties of the plasma in this experiment,
and I also assume that half of the experiment involves knives,
and the other half involves penetration,
rather than all penetration.
The only difference is caused by the collision process,
the energy emitted,
the scattering cross-section would be different.
This is a very micro aspect of physics.
It measures things with great precision.
Yes.
Then, it can deduce from a series of experimental results that
If it becomes 50%,
50% penetration,
What is its Q value?
The highest equivalent penetration record from experiments is
Achieved on the GT60U device in Japan.
What we achieved is a Q value of 1.25
which is still relatively low
just barely passing the threshold
over the past couple of years
not a long period
using the inertial confinement method
by firing a laser at a target to create a channel
we managed to get a Q value of 1.5
of course, this directly involves cutting and penetrating to achieve the core reaction
So this is the highest record achieved in the real Tokamak experiment.
It actually involves inertial confinement.
This was accomplished on the NFNF device in America.
Achieving a Q value of 1.5, right?
And on a global scale,
it reached 20 to the power of 20.
The triple product of 20 to the power of 20 I just mentioned,
for a Tokamak at the 20 to the power of 20 level,
there are roughly three devices in total.
As mentioned, there are four of these GT60U3 devices in Japan.
In the U.S., they have the TFT2 and D3D, or D3D, facilities.
The UK also has a JET device.
All these facilities operate at levels close to 10 to the power of 20 per shot.
This is largely due to developments in the 1990s.
At that time, we achieved very high parameters with tokamaks.
Parameters,
approaching break-even or a Q value of 1.25,
which already surpasses the break-even point in experimental parameters.
So, globally speaking,
the next one we aim to build has a Q factor greater than ten,
which led to the ITER project,
However, with ITER,
it has taken a very long time,
decades of negotiation and planning,
above, we covered some key terms,
and next, we can introduce,
the history of controlled nuclear fusion.
We can go into more detail on this part, okay?
At the beginning, we gave an introduction to
the basic process of nuclear reactions.
In essence, it involves the reduction in mass after a reaction
which is then converted into energy.
This is described by Einstein’s famous equation.
It’s the process of releasing energy.
When it comes to fusion,
initially, people started with hydrogen bombs.
It was roughly about 70 years ago
that we first harnessed the power of nuclear fusion
with the detonation of the first hydrogen bomb
After the hydrogen bomb exploded
people began to wonder
how we could take this weapon-level
uncontrolled
state where the energy is released upon detonation
and transform it according to our design requirements
For example, if I need 500 megawatts of power output at this moment
I can release 500 megawatts
If it's 11 gigawatts, I can scale down to 1 gigawatt
According to my design requirements
to release energy in a controlled state
This process has actually been ongoing for about 70 years
over this period
I think it's important to explain this to everyone
As you mentioned at the beginning
One of the crucial equations in Einstein's theory of relativity
is the famous equation E equals MC squared
This equation tells us
that if something has mass
it inherently contains energy
For nuclear reactions, for instance
what you can observe is
that before the reaction, there's a collection
like atomic nuclei, for example
After the reaction, it turns into some other atomic nuclei.
However, we will notice that
if during this reaction process,
the total mass of all the products after the reaction
is assumed to be less than the total mass of all the reactants before the reaction
when added together,
then according to the mass-energy equivalence, we know that this decrease in mass
means that energy must be conserved, right?
so it will be converted into the kinetic energy of the reaction products.
So this is the process of generating energy through nuclear reactions.
Because the materials before the reaction are heavier,
they add up to a greater mass,
while the products after the reaction are lighter.
But to conserve energy,
the hydrogen nuclei after the reaction,
must ultimately conserve this energy in the form of kinetic energy.
This reaction process,
is essentially like two initially low-energy entities coming together.
After the collision, it transforms into a new product.
And each product carries a significant amount of kinetic energy.
This is Einstein's intelligent equation.
Mass and energy can be converted into each other.
Yes, it illustrates the process of a nuclear reaction we have predicted.
And C stands for the speed of light, right?
C represents the speed of light.
The speed of light is an extremely large value, isn't it?
So even a very small loss of mass
it would generate enormous energy
uh, moving forward
since people mastered the hydrogen bomb technology
the focus has been on how to achieve controlled nuclear fusion
right, as I mentioned earlier
in general terms
on Earth
you either use inertial confinement for controlled nuclear fusion
or magnetic confinement
In fact, inertial confinement
includes, for example, the one mentioned earlier in the U.S.
which achieved a Q factor of 1.5 in the NF facility
the NF facility
and its counterparts domestically
such as the SG device at the Ninth Institute
they are essentially conducting advanced nuclear weapons research under the global nuclear test ban
including some advanced nuclear weapons studies
as you can see on the U.S. National Nuclear Security Administration’s website
He wrote it the same way, right?
Because this methodology
is essentially not suitable for civilian use.
It requires a lot of lasers,
in an extremely short period of time,
to irradiate the target nucleus in a highly synchronized manner to compress it,
to trigger a nuclear reaction.
So, it can't maintain a stable state for the experiment.
And we also know
Actually, converting electrical energy into laser energy
involves a significant loss
with the conversion efficiency being less than 3%
So even though we see a Q of 1.5
which is the ratio of fusion output energy to input
the input here refers to the energy of the laser
and doesn’t account for the end-to-end process
the conversion from electricity to laser is not considered
That’s why these two factors are important
One issue is that it cannot run stably.
It can only operate in short, pulsed bursts.
The second reason is the extremely low conversion efficiency of the laser.
So, when people work on inertial confinement, they don’t consider it for civilian use.
It’s not used as a power generation method.
It’s a technique for researching high-efficiency nuclear weapons.
How long it can sustain is a concern.
The reaction time is roughly at the nanosecond level.
Its reaction time is roughly at the nanosecond level.
Ten to the ninth power seconds
This is a reaction process
That's so fast
Why can it be used for military purposes
Actually, the nuclear reaction process is also very fast
The actual explosion process of a hydrogen bomb is also very quick
What other advantages are there
In terms of requirements, this inertial confinement
For example, early nuclear weapons
For example, a hydrogen bomb
has a very low combustion efficiency
What does that mean?
Let's say I have a large block
of material that can be used for the reaction
but in reality, the nuclear reaction
through Einstein's famous equation
only a small portion of it actually releases energy
most of the material doesn't actually participate in the reaction
It doesn’t meet the reaction conditions, or the reaction stops.
Inertial confinement is actually one method.
For example, can we increase the reaction rate from 1%
to 2%,
to 80%,
or even higher,
so we can fully achieve the nuclear reaction.
This allows us to release the maximum amount of energy with the minimum amount of fuel.
All of these are part of inertial confinement.
There are some questions we can look into.
Including the processes under high temperature and pressure in a short time.
During the fusion reaction,
what kind of processes it goes through,
and how to improve its reaction efficiency.
These are all questions of inertial confinement,
studied in a controlled environment.
The advantage is that, compared to a hydrogen bomb,
it is, of course, more controllable.
More predictable
a more convenient environment for research
Right
If our ultimate goal is not to conduct scientific research
not to develop weapons
but to generate electricity
then our primary method is actually confinement
this method
I just introduced the sub-limit as well
Different shapes of magnetic fields
correspond to different methods of magnetic confinement
which is a branching technical pathway
Among the many technical pathways for this confinement
the tokamak actually achieves the highest triple product
which is the physical parameter we just mentioned that determines energy gain
and it performs better
than other technical pathways
by at least two orders of magnitude
even by a factor of four
In the 1960s, around that time
the Soviet Union actually came up with the idea
to use this doughnut-shaped magnetic field satellite technology
This tokamak approach
and they actually built the first device
and found that its performance was really good
better than
other technologies being concurrently researched
The performance is significantly higher
This roughly started from the late 1960s to the 1970s
People focused their main efforts
On a global scale
On the development of tokamaks
The reason
Is its performance
Appears to be better than other technological approaches
Significantly better
So, this technical approach is a consensus.
The technical approach
has been agreed upon globally.
Including, in fact, across the world,
like the two major research institutes in China before,
such as the Plasma Institute,
and 585,
all the large facilities built in the past are tokamaks,
and the several high-parameter devices in the U.S. are also tokamaks.
Including why the world's largest device
ITER is also a tokamak
It's because it has the most researchers
With the most experimental results
And it has actually achieved
Experimental parameters close to 10 to the power of 20
How many tokamaks are there globally
More than 100
People are constantly building tokamaks with higher parameters
and continuously achieving better results
which attracts more funding
step by step
as I mentioned earlier about the 1990s
when there were three, even four tokamaks worldwide
the tokamaks had already reached a performance of 20 to the power of 20
which led to the ITER project, right?
throughout this process
It was really just a process of
from the early stages
everyone was just trying to verify this magnetic field configuration
to see how well it could confine the plasma
so the simplest engineering approach was used
which was to build the tokamak with copper
this was the earliest phase
most of the
and indeed, almost all of the tokamaks
They are all made of copper.
Then, moving forward, it's around 2006.
Like China's EAST device,
it was the world's first fully superconducting tokamak device.
So, from the era of copper tokamaks,
we transitioned to using superconductivity for tokamaks.
Because if you want to generate power in the future,
it has to be a superconducting device.
It generates less heat and can operate for extended periods.
Let's go back to what we mentioned about 2018.
Our second-generation high-temperature superconducting materials
could then be produced on an engineering scale.
Initially, MIT, in collaboration with CFS, proposed
a device called SPARC.
The goal was to match the performance of ITER,
with the magnetic field doubled,
and the size reduced to 2% to 3% of its original volume,
and the cost was estimated to be around 2.5 billion euros.
It dropped to one billion dollars.
That's about it, generally speaking.
Fusion
Especially magnetic confinement tokamaks
The development history has been a process like this.
By last year
That is, in 2022
From the beginning up until now
High-temperature superconductivity
The tokamak technology route has actually always been just an idea
until last year
when we built the world's first
fully high-temperature superconducting tokamak
which is the device downstairs, the Honghuang 70 backup unit
for the first time in engineering
we validated high-temperature superconductivity at a full-scale facility level
the tokamak is not just a concept
it can be built in engineering
It can also truly run experiments
and the operating parameters are quite stable
What concept should we use?
Let me give you an analogy to make it easier to understand
It's like assuming all ships were once made of wood
We, of course, started in the United States
Later, we were the first to propose it domestically
We say if you want to build a truly high-performance
for example, an aircraft carrier
You definitely need to use steel as the raw material.
But no one has ever built a ship with steel.
The Honghuang Qilin is essentially the world's first one.
To draw a parallel,
the first fully steel-built ship.
What are the challenges?
When you change the primary material,
when you use wood,
you don't consider welding techniques.
Have you considered the issue of rust prevention?
And wood naturally floats on water.
But steel sinks when placed in water.
True, though ships all rely on Archimedes' principle.
The buoyancy principle allows you to float as long as the displacement is large enough.
You can always manage to stay afloat.
But when you change the main material,
the entire design of the ship,
and the entire manufacturing process, changes completely.
And before it actually hits the water and runs,
no one can be one hundred percent certain that after it goes into the water,
the ship won't leak,
won't sink,
it won't sink when it's in motion.
This is why we built the device named Qilin,
it's not a high-performance vessel,
but it's the first one,
a complete device built with new materials.
It proved that this core material
is viable for building a complete device.
And I let it hit the water.
I let it move forward.
I’ll bring it back.
Just let it operate normally.
It’s stable.
All the system interfaces are fully connected.
And you verified that the size can be smaller.
The cost can be lower.
Regarding this matter,
we have to be frank, it's not right.
This actually needs to be verified in our next device,
the HL-170, to confirm it.
Because you need to reduce the size,
lower the cost,
while still meeting the same performance requirements,
for example, matching the parameters of ITER.
We aim to achieve a Q value greater than ten.
Then we'll compare the cost and size.
This is the goal for the next device.
Not the current device with a value of seventy.
It's not a high-parameter device.
We're talking about high-temperature superconductivity.
Many believe it's a viable technical path.
But it has never been verified before, right?
Back in 2018,
It's MIT in the U.S. and the company CFS
who initially proposed this technological pathway
because when you talk about a technological pathway
the first question is whether there's a material available now
high-temperature superconductors
this material was actually discovered in the lab
back in the 1990s
but it took time for the material to move from the lab to the point where it could be
for instance, mass-produced in lengths of hundreds of meters or kilometers in industry
It was a considerable period of time
roughly after 2015
and even up to 2018
that we truly achieved mass production on a hundred-kilometer scale
which made this raw material
usable in industrial applications
Based on this second-generation high-temperature superconductor in mass production
the material has become
a viable option for use
People working on fusion would think about this.
Could I use this material to build a
tokamak device?
So the initial idea was proposed around
2018 or so.
We proposed this around 2021
in China.
Yes.
But turning this idea into an actual device
The first truly operational all-superconducting
tokamak device
which is our Red Light 70
We completed the construction of this device in March last year
after starting in late February
and we successfully ran it for the first time in June
with all systems operating as designed
and achieved the first plasma ignition
This is where it ties into your entrepreneurial journey
Why did you decide to start this venture in 2021?
I understand you have a strong interest in the technological approach.
Why did you choose to pursue this through entrepreneurship?
Actually, at that point in 2021,
one thing we could see was,
the first assessment was to determine the extent of the dramatic changes.
The basic conclusion at that time was,
if humanity were to use fusion power generation without considering costs,
it was definitely achievable.
For instance, a device like ITER
has a long construction period
but its design
many aspects were finalized in the 1990s
so it is quite conservative
and follows very traditional physics principles in its design
it’s hard to go wrong
I think, unless we make some relatively
basic engineering mistakes
Let's get it done.
This isn't a tough task.
It's not that it's too difficult; it's bound to happen.
It's just a matter of how long it will take.
And how much it will cost.
It's a project involving a coalition of six or seven national teams.
This is quite complex.
Because at that point in time
At that point in time
When it's a project with a scale of over ten billion
a 25 billion Euro fund project
it would be a huge burden
for any country
and it is also
considered the second most expensive project in the world
from an international project perspective
what is the most expensive space station?
the International Space Station
When your capital reaches tens or even hundreds of billions
in euros or dollars
or even a scale of hundreds of billions of RMB
this collaborative approach
an international collaborative approach
becomes a potentially viable method
Right
Of course, at the beginning
it actually started in the 90s
Everyone has already seen what fusion can achieve.
With a Q value greater than 10 to the power of 21.
This parameter has been achieved by several devices.
So, it was initially proposed by the Soviet Union and the United States.
This ITER project,
which was a proposal by the two superpowers of the time,
to work together and see if they could achieve
a truly meaningful device for engineering purposes,
with a Q value greater than ten.
This is the Ito Plan proposed at the beginning of the 90s.
Of course, it was during Reagan's era.
Later, the Soviet Union dissolved.
The project was then led by the EU.
The facility is located in France.
Initially, it was the Soviet Union.
The United States proposed this project.
Later, the EU took the lead.
And then there's China.
the United States
along with four other countries
have been collaborating on this project
all the way up to now
is there a risk that it will be outdated by the time it’s completed?
this is actually the current situation
it has indeed been caused by the excessively long duration of the project
you see, a truly Q greater than ten device
people believe the earliest one might be the one in the United States
The spark device for high-temperature superconductivity
began construction in 2022
and might be completed by 2026
although they claim it will be ready next year
Let's go back to the initial question
In 2021
the general consensus was that fusion
is scientifically feasible
even if we disregard the cost
In terms of engineering feasibility
there is a solid foundation and a wealth of experience accumulated
So, what exactly is missing for commercializing fusion?
What do we need?
The key point
is to reduce the cost of electricity from fusion
In other words, what does commercializing fusion mean?
This is something we are very clear about within the team
It's when you bring the cost of electricity down to the same level as that from coal power
You've commercialized it.
The day you reduce the cost per unit of electricity to below that of coal power,
by an order of magnitude,
you can essentially provide energy
even two orders of magnitude more abundant.
This is what we call the state of energy freedom.
So, the basic criterion is the cost per unit of electricity,
and regarding this matter,
our view back in 2021 was that
Perhaps the technological path of high-temperature superconductivity
can significantly reduce the size of the device
and cut its cost by two orders of magnitude
making us feel that this is feasible
Do you think it marks an engineering turning point?
Yes
Due to the transformation brought by new materials
it has reduced its cost
by more than two orders of magnitude compared to thermal power
to be on par with thermal power
because of the significant cost difference
using this incremental approach
like reducing costs by 10% today
and 20% tomorrow
you might not even achieve the goal
it's a very long process
such changes often require some
for instance, material innovations or new technological advancements
This leads to a significant reduction in costs.
Then you scale up.
And bring it down another order of magnitude.
That's a different story, right?
So back in 2021, I felt that this was something important.
Our goal is to reduce the cost of fusion power to be
On par with or even lower than that of coal power.
The value our company provides
Is in the process of ultimately achieving fusion power generation.
Everything that can consistently improve cost-effectiveness
and reduce the cost of fusion power
is what we all need to do
which is why we initially discussed the overall design of the device
We definitely build our own devices
from the design and manufacturing of magnets to their final testing and operation
we do it all ourselves
These are all key factors that significantly impact the cost of your device
including the subsequent steps
We've basically developed all our core subsystems in-house, right?
Because, in terms of improving cost-effectiveness,
even a small change in your design,
can make a huge difference in cost.
Your core subsystems,
they affect the interfaces of all other systems.
If you make even a slight change in its design,
the entire setup would change significantly as well.
And if I can turn my costs into
the cost of raw materials
that is to say
all the knowledge and information were figured out by my team
I can truly transform a device
its cost is reduced to
the further upstream you push, the more likely it is
the cost of raw materials is lower
yes, that's why we decided to completely handle the design ourselves
core subsystem
You go through the process of designing and producing it yourself.
Including the final debugging and operation.
Because only when you turn this device into something that is not a black box for you,
When everything is transparent,
Will you know what your new goal is.
For instance, achieving higher parameters,
Or when I optimize its cost,
I know which systems need to be adjusted.
What system do I need to adjust?
The optimal value of each system lies in identifying where it performs best.
In 2021, we figured out what we wanted to achieve.
That’s when the project really came together.
At the beginning, there were just four of us.
For the static aspects, Brother Dong took charge of the overall coordination.
He was responsible for the physical design.
And the subsequent experimental operations.
One of our most critical systems at the start was the magnet.
We did all the processing ourselves.
Leveraging the right pig for the job
Of course, this is also about how we manage our team
The financial requirements are also quite high
For instance, adding a domain name
Initially, it was four of us working on this
Why we chose to do it as a startup
For example, not using the most efficient methods
What I was just thinking about is this
The challenge we face now is to solve problems in the shortest time possible
Achieving fusion at the lowest cost
A rapid and significant change in cost-effectiveness
This is fundamentally something a startup is well-suited for
Even when it comes to industrial products
It’s like what SpaceX is doing for everyone
Because in terms of organizational attributes
The shortest decision-making process
The most efficient way of getting things done
To move something from the lab to real low-cost production
The large-scale application process
This is what commercial companies excel at
Rather than what universities or research institutes are best at
So when the fusion issue
Shifts from addressing scientific and engineering feasibility
To addressing commercial viability
The most suitable entity to tackle this
Is actually a startup company
This is how we identified our goal
Now we know
what kind of team you need
and what organizational structure to use for this task
We started working on this around 2021
Could you tell us about your background first?
I have a background in physics
with a Ph.D. from Peking University’s Department of Physics
and my research was in theoretical physics at Stanford
What was your specific area of focus?
What I do is actually more fundamental physics.
I work on quantum gravity.
I do string theory.
Including the intersection between quantum gravity and quantum information.
These are foundational physics that are quite distant from our world.
Right, right.
This was mostly during my doctoral studies.
At Stanford, I mainly focused on these areas.
It's very fundamental physics research.
You've been fond of physics since you were young, right?
I was also admitted through a physics competition back then.
Let's start from my undergraduate years.
That's when I truly started to understand it.
Including what kind of problems physics solves.
And I also really enjoy using the simplest approach,
the most basic assumptions,
the minimal methods,
to understand the complex real world.
This process
is a way of looking at the world, I guess
what kind of problems is physics trying to solve
what problems in the world
that's quite broad
this problem is rather
it really encompasses so much
but it mainly focuses on
issues related to matter and information
For a long time
in fact, people have been thinking along the lines of reductionism
that if I break down a system into small enough pieces
fine enough
and if I treat these smallest parts like Lego bricks
and understand the physical properties of these building blocks clearly
I should be able to have a very fundamental
and very precise description of the world
This is why people have been thinking this way for a long time
For example, from the study of macroscopic objects down to atoms and molecules.
And we keep going deeper.
We've reached the level of fundamental particles in our research.
Even when we work on string theory,
we continue to explore even smaller scales.
Such as the study of strings.
Later on,
people also realized during the process,
that this pure reductionism
This idea isn't quite right either.
Because when you consider the scale,
for example, when you study a macroscopic object,
and you use a highly granular method for the research,
in reality, it spans several orders of magnitude in scale,
theoretically, the most fundamental theory should work,
but in practice, you can also directly at the macroscopic level,
find a phenomenological theory that can describe it directly,
which can more effectively help you explain the current phenomena.
And more accurate too
Rather than using a fundamental theory
To explain the errors across several orders of magnitude
The errors would actually accumulate significantly
And it's even difficult to perform direct calculations theoretically
Right
So this leads to issues with complex systems
Including what people often refer to as emergence in AI
This concept actually originates from physics
Everyone finds that when the scale changes,
it might operate on a different scale,
some characteristics that weren't crucial at the original scale,
suddenly become very important,
becoming the dominant features.
This is what happens when working with complex systems,
people are essentially changing their perspective,
rather than necessarily pursuing the most fundamental scale theories,
to conduct this research.
What we just went through was an introduction
to how physics aims to provide the world
with the simplest possible
explanation for all its phenomena
and in the process of research
we have moved from the large to the small
and later discovered
that perhaps we should directly describe phenomena at different scales
the direct phenomena themselves
Find the corresponding theory that describes it
This is also a more effective method
So gradually, there will be different scales
And then different physical phenomena
And different scenarios
It has branched out into various fields of physics
Which part of artificial intelligence is a physics problem
In the early days of deep learning
Including the Nobel Prize
It also awarded the Nobel Prize in Physics
to the field of deep learning
because it shares some similarities with certain systems in physics
but at the time, those working on AI made an analogy
which led to what is known as the Boltzmann machine
which was then applied to AI systems
as their model
I actually think that the development of AI is primarily driven by computer scientists
and those working in AI who are advancing this analogy
It might be in terms of perspectives
or perhaps some insights from analytical tools
I don’t think it’s primarily driven by physicists
or that it shouldn’t be considered a physics discipline
theoretical physics
it’s not accurate to say it’s at the top of the scientific hierarchy, is it?
there is such a notion about the hierarchy in academia, yes
because it is relatively more abstract after all
especially when dealing with high-energy physics
Or rather, it deals with very fundamental physics.
Its subject of study is quite abstract.
And the tools required are not very intuitive.
So people tend to form this impression.
But in reality, no matter which field of physics you work in,
Your goal
For instance, is to truly explain the phenomenon,
Or even to engineer it,
To actually create it.
It's not just a theory
but something that can become a tangible reality
the difficulty is roughly the same
so I think this hierarchy is more of a joke
controlled nuclear fusion is largely a physics issue
the majority of it is a physics problem
to what extent is it a chemistry issue
we don't actually deal with chemistry that much
that's what we're talking about here
Pretty much everything about it is physical.
This includes the reactions in your atomic nuclei.
The state of plasma.
Reactions in atomic nuclei.
It essentially boils down to nuclear physics.
The performance of plasma.
Predicting its state is a matter of plasma physics.
Including using superconductors to make magnets.
To build a device.
This involves superconductivity
which entails a lot of electrical aspects, such as Maxwell's equations
Our approach to materials is
that we use a bit more
since you're dealing with new materials
and even different materials are used in various components, right?
But we don't directly conduct material research ourselves
We just look for materials that have already been studied by others
and then we select them
Then apply it here.
Then consider its structure.
Its heat dissipation and other issues.
When you want to pursue controlled nuclear fusion.
Generally speaking.
Actually, this idea was considered early on.
We studied physics as undergraduates.
We have a foundational understanding of the physics in various branches.
We still have some concepts about it.
Back then, I did consider
what studying physics really means
for the future of human life and development
what might have a significant impact
That was a question I pondered back then
Given the knowledge at the time
and even now
I believe something that is bound to happen in the future
and will have the greatest impact is
It might just be fusion, you know.
When I say the near future, I mean relatively soon.
100 years from now,
it's hard to say.
But in the present context,
on a 10-year timescale,
we actually believe the most significant changes could be in physics.
For human civilization as a whole,
it could be the most impactful event.
For me personally,
even when I was doing physics research,
I tend to enjoy a certain type of work,
you know, this kind of work,
whether or not I do it,
someone will eventually do it,
this historical,
inevitable trend of development,
is the most appealing thing to me.
Among these things,
actually changing the entire energy supply structure through fusion,
I can even provide energy
on a scale several orders of magnitude higher than what we have now.
This matter,
I believe this is a massive transformation for the development of humanity,
a huge change,
I can't think of a bigger transformative event.
So even after this is achieved,
By taming fusion
we can put it to use
to
develop this type of propellant-less space travel propulsion system
engine
instead of the current chemical rockets
only then do I think it truly becomes a meaningful endeavor
a concept of commercial space travel for interstellar exploration
so that's what this is all about
It represents a significant shift in both energy supply and propulsion for humanity.
It's a massive change for human development.
It was a huge transformation.
It was something I thought I'd never see in my lifetime.
During my undergraduate years, I thought to myself,
If there's any chance, I'd like to be part of it in my lifetime.
I wanted to be involved in this project or something similar.
Besides controlled nuclear fusion, what else could be in the 'once-in-a-lifetime' category?
What other groundbreaking developments are out there?
There are so many things we can do.
Is this the top priority?
Including up to now.
Regarding my understanding.
From a physics perspective.
I think this is the most impactful event.
And it’s something that is bound to happen.
Of course.
There are other things as well.
For example, quantum computing
is also a clear trend
and then there's artificial intelligence
which is something that will definitely happen
we're talking about general AI, right?
of course
take artificial intelligence, for instance
it might not be the most relevant thing for someone like me who does physics
it's not what I'm best at
There are many events in history that are bound to happen.
But some things might benefit from my involvement.
It could potentially shorten the process.
Something that would take 10 years might be reduced to 5.
A 20-year project could become a 10-year one.
In that case, you would make a significant contribution to its advancement.
However, there are also things that might not be suitable for you to do.
Whether you take on the task or not,
it’s something to consider carefully.
There's not much of a big impact.
So, you shouldn't get involved in this, right?
So, this is, for something like AI,
at least for me,
it might not be where I can make the biggest difference,
in this field.
But it’s definitely a direction that history is bound to take.
Including, which do you think are the jewels in the crown of the global science domain?
You've got me there again.
Let me think.
There are actually quite a few.
Such questions are very common in the field of science.
Since I work on fundamental theories, you see.
People are actually quite curious about, for instance, the quantum description of gravity.
That is, at the truly microscopic scale.
What exactly is the behavior of gravity?
Rather than a classical theory.
This has been under investigation since Einstein's time.
Those working on string theory
haven't fully figured it out yet
including the big shots in cosmology, like dark matter
and what exactly is the dark energy that causes the universe to expand
is still not well understood
there are many fundamental physics questions
that the community is eager to understand
but at least for now, whether in theory or experiment
our understanding hasn't reached that level
So, to be more specific
like everyone is constantly researching new materials
there are countless examples
for instance, things we now take for granted
like mobile phones
semiconductors
these were actually from the 1970s and 1980s
when the cutting-edge research was in solid-state physics
working on semiconductor theory
These people found that this material predicted what would come next.
Then, after several decades of engineering, it turned into chips, right?
So, a lot of what we see now is a significant amount of
For example, condensed matter physicists
Or solid-state physicists
They are researching many new materials
Very cutting-edge materials
Gradually, in the future, will become part of our daily lives as
Various applications and objects, right?
So these kinds of issues are actually quite common.
It's just that people's perception of the impact varies.
It might differ from person to person.
Why did you decide to pursue controlled nuclear fusion?
So, you finished your Ph.D., right?
I believe you graduated in 2017, correct?
What have you been up to since then?
From 2017 to 2018,
you actually spent a year in the United States.
I was reflecting on that time.
Because I felt that back then,
I just thought that if something like fusion was going to happen eventually,
it had to be achieved through entrepreneurship.
But right after graduation, I didn’t know what to do.
To be honest,
I spent a year thinking about it.
If I were to start a company,
what would be the first thing I should do?
I returned to China around the end of 2018.
Then I joined my previous company.
It was Jinjiang.
After returning to China at the end of 2018,
of course, Jinjiang Venture Capital invested in our company.
Yes, you are now working on ER at Jinjiang Venture Capital, right?
The first window was also set up correctly, yes.
After leaving in late 2018,
I started a company that combined artificial intelligence with music education.
A company
roughly did
At that time, there were already many AI startups, right?
Yes, that's right.
After all, it's hard to find startups directly related to string theory
indeed, it's hard to find
Exactly
My research direction in physics is string theory
Yes, in the field of string theory
There isn't such a startup project, right?
So at the time, I thought, given my technical background,
I could push from the technical side to the application side.
Then I found a good fit with music education.
I ran the company for about 3 years.
Around the time of 2021,
we also went through the rapid changes in online education,
a period of very swift transformation.
From 2021, I started to think about it.
At that time, I felt that moving forward would lead to
a massive change, something that might happen in my lifetime, yes.
But I also went through a period of entrepreneurial experience.
So I started to think about it.
Ultimately,
whether this fusion can start at this point in time.
If not,
what are the reasons?
What do I need to push forward?
If it's possible
then why not start doing the right thing now
So at that point in 2021
it took about half a year
initially, the planning might have been longer
I think in considering and researching this issue
it can't always be something for the distant future, right
if it really comes down to it
my current research indicates that now is not the right time to do this
What's the reason?
It needs to be turned into a checklist.
Right.
You never thought about becoming a scientist, did you?
I did.
But right after graduation, you chose to work in ER.
And then you decided to start your own business.
Exactly.
Back before graduation.
I might have thought about it.
I was considering either starting my own business,
or possibly becoming a scientist.
Because working on something that might not be done as well or could take longer if someone else did it,
is something I find particularly valuable.
Yes.
And whether it’s developing some new theories in research,
or creating a new methodology,
it all holds a lot of value for me.
Or some new achievements in research
Or I can promote it through a company
Something that truly didn't exist in real life before
These things to me
The sense of personal accomplishment might be stronger
After graduation
I decided to first understand what entrepreneurship is all about
To get a clearer idea of how to do it
I felt that if I really want to make this idea of fusion happen
You're likely just pushing this within the academic circle.
It's not very likely, though.
Can you tell me about your previous entrepreneurial experience?
Or about teaching entrepreneurship?
I think this is actually an old scholar's common saying.
But before you have firsthand experience,
you might not have such a deep understanding.
When it comes to entrepreneurship,
especially something significant,
I think it's definitely a choice that needs to be made.
You are indeed very committed.
And it might be the only thing of its kind.
Yes.
Not something you can just do casually.
Or something you might only dive into if you're interested.
Otherwise, in the process of entrepreneurship,
On one hand, as everyone has said, there are many challenges along the way.
Can you stick with it?
On the other hand, the most important thing is
that you might have other options
other alternatives
especially when you encounter difficulties
whether you would give up
the current endeavor
this is particularly true for startups
I think especially for founders
it's a matter that needs to be thought through clearly
When you're in a favorable situation
things tend to go smoothly anyway
so you just do it
But of course, starting a business isn't always smooth sailing
So from the very beginning, choose something
no matter how challenging it is
you might feel that you can commit to this cause
and stick with it
rather than just adding to what's already good
This is a crucial matter during the early stages of entrepreneurship.
Yes, clarifying the original intention is important.
Then we came back to working on controlled nuclear fusion.
Hehe, yes, that’s right.
Then by the beginning of 2021,
Did you visit many research institutes
and suppliers?
That was part of the research process.
Yes, exactly.
How did the process of the survey go at the time?
What industry conclusions were drawn from it?
Not quite.
At the beginning of the survey,
what we actually wanted to understand was
that
if we were to promote controlled nuclear fusion domestically,
whether we would be constrained by talent,
technology, and raw materials.
The research results show that
the raw materials and key suppliers
are the suppliers you might need to use
there's generally no significant bottleneck
if we choose the high-temperature superconductivity technology route
we won't
it's unlikely that anyone worldwide will
it's all quite new
we can draw on the traditional knowledge that has been accumulated
Most of it is publicly available academic material
So, when it comes to the technology itself
There’s not much risk of being held back
I won’t be
Neither will anyone else
We’ll just have to start from scratch and figure it out
When it comes to talent acquisition
This issue is even less of a concern
Especially since the core of this matter involves research
But what's more important is the engineering implementation.
And in fact, China has a significant advantage in engineering teams.
There are indeed some benefits.
The basic judgment at that time was that
There wasn't a logo,
There's nothing stopping you from starting now.
And it's a very fast and positive feedback loop.
There's a lot of experience and knowledge accumulated in the process.
This experience and knowledge
And then it can be used to iterate into the next generation of products.
That's right.
So it's not like there's one crucial point.
You've nailed this key point, yeah.
Or others can achieve it using this key point.
No, that's not the case.
There are a lot of these intricate issues.
Each issue needs to be addressed one by one.
These are the kinds of ID issues.
Then, in such a case,
and his initial investment is also relatively
the capital is quite substantial,
so he has a strong first-mover advantage in this industry.
Talent is scarce,
in other words, you might have to cultivate everyone yourself.
Knowledge is accumulated on your own,
and the positive feedback loop is very fast,
and each generation of capital is also substantial.
For a startup company,
once you have a leading advantage,
the second-place player in the same field,
basically faces an insurmountable first-mover advantage.
So, it's better to act early rather than late.
In 2021, the controlled nuclear fusion industry in China,
what stage was it at back then?
At that time, only the Plasma Institute of the Chinese Academy of Sciences in Hefei,
and the 585 Institute of China National Nuclear Corporation in Chengdu were involved.
These two national teams are the main drivers.
It's still primarily a state of research institutions.
Startups haven't emerged yet.
We are the first to focus on commercial nuclear fusion.
A startup with the goal of commercializing nuclear fusion.
So at that time, indeed, everyone was in the dark.
At least in China, no one had realized.
There was such a thing.
We were among the earliest to propose this idea.
One person, one team.
What kind of industrial chain does this industry have?
Actually, it's in a very early stage right now.
You can set up a device.
There are different ways to do it.
For example, many universities and research institutions.
They are also working on these small devices.
Or devices for their own research purposes.
In fact, they are all research-oriented devices.
It might be outsourced to other research institutions
or organizations
to help you assemble a device in this state, which is correct
similar to assigning this subsystem to you
you ultimately deliver a complete subsystem
but the supplier on their side might also be a research institution
our approach is actually as I mentioned
we don’t want there to be any black boxes in the design and construction of the device
during the process
So, we are in a state of fully independent design.
Then, the core systems are manufactured in-house.
This means you directly engage with raw material suppliers.
After you have the drawings ready,
you can send them out to various machining suppliers who are in a highly competitive market,
or welding suppliers,
and just let them get to work.
For us,
most of our upstream partners are raw material suppliers.
including some highly competitive startups
welding
manufacturing suppliers
including some electronic components
mature mass-produced components
I think our current state
is still very much in the early stages
even the industrial chain hasn't really formed yet
so there's a lot to be done
Especially with our way of working
It's all Ziyun
Your first generation product was called Honghuang
How did you come across Qi Ling?
Why did you name it Honghuang?
Honghuang, in Chinese mythology
It represents a very early and abundant state
Of course
This state is a very chaotic one
It has a lot of energy
But in fact, it's in a very disordered state
Right
I think what fusion is doing is also something like this
You take a lot of things that are originally very disordered
Of course, the energy is enormous
And transform it into electrical energy, right
So the process of this reaction inside the device
Is actually one full of energy
And it's in such an unnecessary state
So we categorize this series
We name them all Honghuang
Seventy is actually its key parameter
Yes, it's the parameter for its large radius
We have this seventy centimeters
We simply call them Seventy
How the first generation product was constructed
And what its significance is
What exactly is the process of building such a device?
How many people are involved?
What do you do in your work?
I've visited your place before.
Ye Yuming took me there about half a year ago.
Got it.
Downstairs.
It's downstairs.
We started working on this project from the very beginning.
Just the four of us
It was just the four founders until the device was built
It grew to be a team of about 100 people
Over the span of two years
Let's start by giving an overview
Standing at this point in time
What processes does the design of a device typically go through
First, you start with the physical design
What is the core goal you want your device to achieve
And based on this goal,
it will transform into a plasma state,
this is the target I aim to achieve,
the most critical physical parameters for me,
what state it needs to achieve,
these are a few physical designs,
based on these physical designs,
for instance, your plasma needs to reach this level of performance,
the next step is conceptual design
Each of your subsystems needs to achieve certain parameters
to ensure that the final physical parameters
meet the goals of your physical design.
For example, how strong does your magnetic field need to be?
What shape should the magnetic field take?
How do you maintain the plasma in a vacuum environment?
What does the structure of your vacuum chamber look like?
What are the operating temperatures of each subsystem?
Including when to add materials to the system.
It's about inflating
When are you going to diagnose it
To check its current operating status
When are you going to do the control and so on
Based on the physical parameters you want to achieve
You will design each subsystem
Its core objective needs to be designed
Its operating conditions need to be designed
Its interfaces with other subsystems need to be designed
Otherwise, the subsystems would conflict with each other
and we wouldn't be able to integrate them
How many subsystems are there?
If we roughly divide the primary subsystems, there are about ten
Actually, the true secondary subsystems
each of what we call systems
there are probably over 30
After completing the conceptual design
it then gets transformed into this physical objective
Every system has a design concept
which is feasibility
basically whether this thing can be made
Once we reach this point
the next step is the concept of engineering design
for example, how much flow rate I need
what temperature
what flow rate for a low-temperature system
but how do you implement it in engineering
Then you really need to go into the low-temperature system
with its distribution valve boxes
liquid storage tanks
refrigerants, and so on
all the engineering equipment is fully designed
So at this point
once you have the concept for each system
you need to design it into something that can be used for manufacturing and processing
or to select and purchase the equipment
This is the engineering design methodology
to produce the drawings
to specify the technical requirements
This is the third step of the engineering design
After completing the engineering design
we move on to the manufacturing phase
Sometimes we provide the drawings to external manufacturers like Giga
or such manufacturing suppliers
and also to welding suppliers for the fabrication of tanks
vacuum pressure vessel
let them manufacture it
and supply us with some components, like magnets
we process and manufacture them in another facility ourselves
we manufacture the physical parts ourselves
right, exactly
you buy steel
buy resin
buy high-temperature superconducting tapes
ultimately process it into
the magnet as you designed
and finally deliver it to the installation site
to be distributed to
various subsystems
now we start the processing phase
following our design plan
and process it all out
after the subsystems are processed
Then it moves to the acceptance stage.
Each subsystem needs to meet the design criteria at the subsystem level.
Can it satisfy your design specifications?
If it can,
then it’s accepted.
If it can’t,
the necessary adjustments or rework should be carried out. After the subsystems are accepted,
we move on to the overall assembly phase.
We need to install the different subsystems together.
Then it becomes a complete tokamak.
You can see the device downstairs.
During the assembly process,
of course, there's also testing.
After installation, we integrate and fine-tune the entire system.
Once it's installed,
we check if it can operate according to my design requirements,
within my design parameters,
and it reaches the final experimental operation state.
I will aim for the initial design goal
Can I achieve it
For example, can low-density plasmas be ignited for these purposes
This year, we hope to achieve a thousand-second level
Steady-state operation
Can we progress from the initial design to step-by-step refinement
From design to manufacturing, assembly, and final operation
It's essentially the acceptance process
To see if the constructed item meets the standards
Did it meet your initial design goals?
He completed the entire process.
Throughout this process,
each stage actually requires different skills.
But during the early design phase,
our approach is generally to start with the requirements,
then read through the literature,
review textbooks,
and start from the most basic formulas to derive the solutions.
Identify the core and crucial parameters
Then refine them based on these parameters
Gradually refine the process for engineering simulation
For instance, the structural forces designed
Can they meet the material requirements under various conditions
Can the heat from your hand be dissipated properly
Can the electromagnetic performance
Be consistent with the magnetic field in your design
Is the magnetic field aligned with your design
A large amount of engineering simulation
Then, for some parameters that are not accurately simulated
We conduct process experiments
For example, if a part is quite large
I would first make a small sample
This small sample
Does your simulation match the experimental parameters
Is it within, say, a 10%
20% prediction range
Now, after believing in the experiment and simulation comparison,
I trust the simulation model.
Then I can further extend it.
And then I can proceed to build larger components, right?
Throughout this process,
I continuously read literature,
conduct simulations,
and compare experiments with simulations to gain confidence in this model.
Then, I move on to construct the complete magnet for the actual subsystem.
So, the design phase generally follows this process.
How long did the design take?
We don't follow the approach of freezing the design and then moving on.
Otherwise, you definitely wouldn't finish in two years.
There's a lot of parallel work involved.
If you're talking about the final design,
most of our design work up to the engineering design completion
should have started from March 2021.
We started working on it back in March 2021.
We started designing this device
all the way until the end of 2021
at the beginning of 2022
we had largely completed the engineering design by this point
but in fact, we continued to make adjustments during the manufacturing process
it took almost a year
and by the end of the year, it was ready for implementation
actually, it was in the second half of 2021
that we had already begun to lock down some of the earlier designs
A similar system was initially put into production
So from the second half of 2021 to the end of 2022
This year was the manufacturing phase
But around May 2022
By October, assembly had begun
I didn’t need to complete everything before starting the assembly
Some components could be assembled as soon as they were ready
So from September to October 2022
I made a mistake
It wasn't in 2021
It started in March 2022
Not in March 2021
The entire timeline is pushed back
Yes, March 2022
From March 2022 to December, the end of the year
The design phase was at the beginning of 2023
So you started your business in June 2021?
Yes, that's right
I got the time wrong.
It started around the second half of 22.
Specifically, in September.
And it continued until the end of 23.
That period was my manufacturing time.
In September of 23,
it went on until February of 24, which was my assembly time.
After the assembly was completed,
it was March of 24.
Around June of 24
is when I'll be running and debugging
Is this process going smoothly?
Definitely not.
There are a lot of issues in between
Each step keeps running into problems
And the closer you get to the physical state
The bigger the issues become
The more problems arise
Let me put it this way
The higher the cost of making changes to fix issues
The best time to make corrections is actually during the design phase
It just takes a bit of thinking and writing
Of course, the impact of his modifications is also the greatest
The earlier it is, the greater the impact
As time goes on
You will encounter more and more detailed issues
A multitude of practical engineering problems
You need to address every issue.
By the time the physical product is delivered,
you actually have the least room for changes.
Once the problems come to light,
the pressure to resolve them is at its peak.
How many designers are there?
By the end of 2022, there were probably around 40 people.
You don’t have many people left by the time the design phase is nearly over.
Around 40 people.
Of course, we continued to design afterwards.
By the end of 22,
around 40 people,
forty to fifty people,
I don't quite remember.
What kind of background is this?
There's no physics, no physics.
Actually, there weren't that many people,
because at that time, there were a few doing theory.
There aren't many people doing experiments yet
Most of them are engineering staff
Including structural engineers
Cryogenic engineers
Vacuum engineers
We need to develop our magnets in-house
There are a lot of engineering personnel working on the magnet manufacturing process
Actually, up to this point
There aren't that many people solely focused on physics research
There might be around twenty people.
Yeah, but the engineering team is quite large.
During the process,
what were the most challenging issues you faced?
It took a long time to resolve all the issues.
There were a ton of problems every day.
Did you ever feel like you couldn't figure it out?
Not really, I didn’t have that feeling.
The hardest part was not knowing what went wrong.
When you encounter a problem
there are also many things you can't directly measure
you can't measure them correctly
you have to guess the cause of the problem
this can be quite challenging
and it can be quite frustrating
because your initial guesses might be incorrect
you make adjustments but find no improvement
but when you finally guess the problem correctly
Once you have a solution in mind
and there are signs indicating it might be right
you start to feel more at ease
these are the ones he can definitely resolve
it just takes some time to get them sorted out
I think this process
is all about continuously solving a multitude of problems
and a lot of things aren't actually because we haven't done them before
not only we haven't done them
This thing might not have been done anywhere in the world
So you can't have very precise theoretical predictions or calculations
Many things
You're estimating some of its upper or lower limits
For example, with this thing
Its upper limit is also acceptable to you
Your engineering can meet the requirements
Then you believe that the design of A is actually stable, right
Because you don't know exactly what that value is
You might not guess it right.
You can't calculate it accurately.
So, in many situations where information is incomplete or imprecise,
you need to make some judgments and decisions.
Then you need to push the matter forward.
How to estimate this range,
How to,
guess the possible parameter range within this scope,
and if this range is narrow.
Alright, then.
Let's proceed with this design width.
What methods can we use to prevent anomalies?
To ensure your design supports operation within this parameter range.
You'll need to address many such issues.
Ultimately, the design should match your expectations.
But it would be better if they were different.
How the performance goes on site is a major concern.
Minor issues
What do you think is the longest one?
We built the toroidal field coils for our first tokamak device.
There are 12 magnetic coils.
When we were constructing the first full-scale prototype.
Of course, if it’s completed,
it might just be the first official one built.
All the previous steps went smoothly.
Because I conduct quality inspections after each step.
To assess whether the performance has changed before and after each step.
Is everything going as expected?
But when we got to the final process,
we noticed a drop in performance.
It was significantly lower than we anticipated.
Can this actually make it into the real world?
Can it be installed and used?
Although there has been a decline in performance,
it still maintains a relatively good level.
And what exactly is the cause?
Which step in this process caused the issue?
Because the final step doesn’t seem
particularly complicated.
But the result was a performance degradation.
So at that point, we analyzed it extensively.
We looked into all possible causes.
And the final decision was
that the magnet wasn’t installed on the official equipment.
We decided to use it for subsequent testing and inspection.
The analysis of the causes
is still not entirely conclusive
but we suspect that some vibrations during the manufacturing process
may have caused mechanical damage
Of course, we have since implemented anti-vibration procedures
throughout the entire process
whether in manufacturing
or transportation
this has been addressed in all stages
So, there was no such issue with any of the subsequent magnets.
We think this is probably the right direction.
But we're not sure which step is the problem.
The manufacturing process.
The transportation process.
Or even if it's our manufacturing.
Or someone else's manufacturing.
We just don't know.
You have to address the entire supply chain to fix this.
And this matter,
after all, it involves the delivery of a complete magnet,
there was an issue with the previous step.
So, you have to do it all over again.
Of course, this is a process validation piece, right?
But if it's done well,
it is full size,
we might use the full-size version as the official key,
but it wasn't used in the end.
So it results in the need to build an additional one for the entire project
It's essentially in this state
Actually, there's nothing particularly dramatic
You just notice a drop in performance
Then you analyze the cause
After analyzing for a while, you're still not entirely sure
In the end, you address the entire production
All the internal and external suppliers involved in manufacturing
All of them adjust according to the speculated cause
Looking forward to the second one succeeding.
The second one succeeded.
Then you can rest easy.
What made you feel the worst?
I'm not someone who experiences big mood swings.
Of course, encountering difficulties during the process can affect your mood.
But overall, I don't experience major emotional fluctuations.
Yeah, so it's okay.
It's just that I encountered some challenges.
Your mood might not be great
but you found the solution
so your mood will improve
What is the purpose of activating the plasma state
What does the visualization look like
Initially, the vacuum chamber
since it's a vacuum environment
you pump the experimental gas into it
it's actually dark inside
It's neutral gas
you use some ionization methods
such as electron guns or injecting microwave power
to make some of the electrons in the neutral gas escape
transforming it into a plasma state
with only a small fraction of electrons ionized
in this process
you also ensure that, for example, the magnets
and all other systems operate according to your settings
In the end, you'll see inside this chamber
most of its area will turn into plasma
and it will emit light
just like in the photos we took
and the shape of this plasma
matches the design of the satellite with the magnetic field
the satellite that combines magnetic fields and currents is basically consistent
so the startup of this device has been achieved
the first tokamak's
At the very beginning, you need to start with a neutral gas
where atoms and electrons are mixed together
to transform the complete neutral gas into a plasma
you generate the plasma
and thus, you activate the device
then gradually increase the parameters of this plasma
so it transitions from the neutral gas, which is dark
and then it turns into something close to what you've designed
a plasma satellite
This process marks the achievement of the first plasma.
For any fusion device, the first plasma
means that all your systems
have met the design requirements,
and when they operate together, they reach the design conditions.
After that, it's a step-by-step process to push for higher parameters.
This may require additional equipment.
This is the process.
The key metrics need to reach certain levels.
For example, the Q value
This has nothing to do with the Q value
Even the Honghuang QL-70 device has little to do with the Q value
We are not a high-parameter device
It can't achieve a meaningful Q
Its parameter multiplier is roughly 10 to the 17th power
This parameter is four orders of magnitude lower than 10 to the 20th power
So, Honghuang QL-70 doesn't provide very high scientific parameters
Objective
It's about the parameter performance of the font type.
It's just the first class of font types.
It verifies the performance of the engineering project.
All of my systems,
especially my magnet system,
according to my design plan,
can initiate the plasma,
can get this device up and running,
even though it's for a short time.
It takes just a split second
The scale of time where it flashes and then goes out
He demonstrated that building a complete device with this material
is actually feasible from an engineering standpoint
So we look forward to seeing the vacuum inside the device
captured by the camera when the plasma is ignited
For instance, the density of the plasma
We can measure that it meets the design requirements
That's the first point
The text T has already sparked panic.
What does bullying mean to you?
Honghuang Seven Zero
I think it can be explained from two aspects.
I believe the significance of Honghuang Seven Zero for the entire fusion field
is to prove that using this extremely difficult-to-process material
is because high-temperature superconductivity is a very fragile property
and is easily damaged during processing
which can lead to a decline in performance.
a material with poor machinability
using this material in low-temperature and strong magnetic field environments
and various heated conditions to operate
whether it can actually be manufactured
if it can be manufactured, whether it can be activated
whether it can function
these are all unknowns, right?
so for the entire fusion field, Honghuang Qiling
essentially proved that using such a difficult-to-machine material
It's capable of building a complete device
and conducting experimental operations
Of course, for our team internally
its significance goes beyond just building it
the world's first full high-temperature tokamak
and our approach is a hundred percent self-designed
the core systems are manufactured in-house
the entire assembly process
we participate in the experimental process ourselves
The entire process is self-directed
including the upgrades for phase two
even the assembly process is entirely self-handled
done by our own team
so it’s crucial for the team
it involves learning
accumulating experience
and preparing for the development of a highly advanced
parameter device in the future
I need to master a large non-standard device
solving the complexity of its system
when dealing with a highly complex piece of equipment or apparatus
it's not just about each individual parameter
the parameters of each specific system are quite high
it's difficult to manufacture
there's a major issue
which is whether all these systems can work together
whether they can actually be assembled
Can it run?
Can it meet your standards?
What are the mutual constraints?
These things actually happen during the bullying process.
We've accumulated a lot of experience in this area.
As I said before,
When your entire system isn't a black box to you,
You can confidently say,
When I want to upgrade this device.
Or when I’m planning to build the next device
I need to modify something
When subsystems conflict with each other
I have to give up something
I need to keep something
When the entire construction process has mutual influences and interferences
How to coordinate everything properly
These issues are all discussed at the level of system complexity
The greatest value Honghuang Qilin brings to this team
So, essentially, we're talking about the true 0 to 1 process on a global scale.
Designing and building a high-temperature superconducting tokamak.
We are the only team in the world, yeah.
Others haven't managed to build one yet.
You guys say that...
The domestic production rate of the Honghuang Jianlin exceeds 96%.
What about the remaining 4%?
The remaining 4% consists of some imported low-temperature equipment.
For example, some low-temperature pumps.
There are also some low-temperature chambers
as well as some sensors
of course, there are also some domestic alternatives for these
but indeed, there are some imported devices
their stability
engineering parameters
the guarantee of parameters remaining unchanged during operation
are all handled better
so we use them in some critical systems or key positions
We will still use imported equipment.
Just these few.
I remember you started with a Three-step Development Strategy, right?
Could you elaborate on that?
Initially, in 2021 and 2022,
we began to assess the commercialization of fusion.
During this process,
we have three very important devices.
The first one was actually the Red and Yellow Kylin we planned at the time.
We call this device the prototype.
It's used to verify the use of this new material,
a high-temperature superconducting material, to build a complete device.
To see if it's actually feasible in engineering.
It's a validation of its engineering feasibility.
This device was delivered last year, right?
The second device is our Honghuang 170.
This device,
it can achieve a tenfold increase in energy output.
and globally
the most cost-effective way to achieve such performance
this is to verify
if using this technology
it can actually produce a fusion device with costs comparable to coal-fired power
a fusion device
under these cost conditions
whether it’s possible to achieve
for example, a fusion performance parameter of Q greater than or equal to ten
If possible
we could actually build a demonstration power plant
with its core technology
and the cost, which I've been emphasizing
it's now a commercializable technology
we hope to start from now
within 3 years
by the end of 2027, to have this facility constructed
this is our second milestone
Once this device is built
and operational tests are conducted
if we achieve the results as designed
such as a Q value greater than or equal to ten
then we believe the technology is sufficient to support
the construction of a fusion demonstration power plant
which would be our third device
we aim to achieve this between 2030 and 2035
with an electrical output capacity of about 500 megawatts
a medium-sized thermal power plant scale
a demonstration fusion power station
of course
the third device will be a commodity for us
it will be a product
we will sell it to domestic owners building fusion power stations
it could be these nuclear power owners
or if I were to do it myself
it would not involve
It could be state-owned energy enterprises in some regions
state-owned enterprises might be potential clients for us
we serve as the core equipment supplier
we sell to these nuclear power plant owners in Tokamak
The cycle is quite long
spanning from 2021 to 2035
roughly a 10 to 15-year timeframe
Yes, that's right
it's only then that the first commercial product will be available
Didn't you guys just release a groundbreaking magnet?
This is also a landmark achievement for you.
It must be crucial for the Honghuang 170, right?
It's a vital component.
First, focusing on the magnet itself for today,
it currently has the highest magnetic field strength in the world,
among large-bore magnets.
The previous record was set when high-temperature superconductivity
was first proposed for the tokamak technology.
The American company CFS and MIT
back at the end of 2021
developed a magnet called TFMC
and they achieved 20 teslas
just over 20 teslas
you are now at 21.7
we've improved this parameter by nearly 10%
it's less than 10%
right now, there are only a few places in the world capable of producing such large-aperture magnets
A team of over 20 experts
including our team and the CFS team from the U.S.
As we've been saying
we use this material to generate the magnetic field
the parameters we have now
should make it the magnet with the highest magnetic field strength in the world
the stronger the magnetic field
the lower the cost
and the smaller the device
What does large aperture mean?
Because our final plasma
needs to be placed in the center of the magnet
and we need to install a lot of equipment inside
including vacuum systems
to enclose the plasma
so the magnet I'm talking about
actually has a large central hole
a hole on the meter scale
The reason for this emphasis is
Many high-field magnets
typically have apertures of millimeters or centimeters
with a very small hole in the middle
Because most of these particularly high-field magnets
are used for material experiments
For instance, I only need to place a small material sample inside
to provide a high magnetic field
and then measure its properties
So this scenario is quite different from our fusion setting.
It might be a magnet with a centimeter or millimeter aperture.
Ours is a meter-scale aperture magnet.
When the central aperture becomes significantly larger,
the entire design,
including the manufacturing complexity, becomes much more challenging.
After all, when the center is small,
you can achieve high magnetic fields,
by winding many, many layers around the outside.
And it's relatively small in the middle
So it's a circular magnet
It's an object that experiences fairly uniform force
When it's like our D-shaped one
It still has an irregular edge
The central aperture is on the micron level
You also need the highest
If you want a very high magnetic field
Then you need to balance it out
It needs to account for the forces involved
as well as the heat generated during the process
Everything has to fit within certain dimensions
and the current density needs to be high
So how do we balance the forces
thermal, and electrical
to achieve extremely high parameters in all three areas
This is the challenge that large-aperture magnets need to address
How did you manage to achieve such high performance
Tesla has the highest magnetic field.
That's correct.
Actually, in principle,
to achieve a very high magnetic field,
you need a large current.
You generate a strong magnetic field with a large current.
So, the simplest idea would be,
for example, if I have a requirement for an endoscope,
it's about the requirements for the larger environment.
So, I will wrap it with enough superconducting material
this superconducting wire
then I will pass a sufficiently large current through it
which will always create a very strong magnetic field
but in this process, you will encounter new challenges
for example, when the magnetic field is very strong
and the current is also very high
physics tells us
the force experienced is actually quite significant
This means your Ampere force is equal to the magnetic field times the current.
So, when your current is strong,
and the magnetic field is also strong,
the conductor will experience a significant force within this magnetic field.
When this force is substantial,
what do we do?
Generally, people think,
I’ll add a lot of structural material,
like using a lot of steel, for example.
I'll go and bear the force
That works
This will create a problem
If you add enough structural material
You can distribute the force
But the current density of your cross-section will decrease
Because most of the cross-sectional area can't conduct electricity
It's the structural material, right
This actually contradicts our design
We not only need a high magnetic field
but also a high engineering current density
The advantage of high engineering current density is that
we can, for example, achieve the same magnetic field
with a higher engineering current density
which means the cross-sectional size can be smaller
Engineering current density is the current passing through a unit area, after all
Right?
Once the total current is fixed
The higher the current density
the smaller the cross-sectional area of mine
which ultimately allows my device to be built smaller
since I won't need such a large area
to support this current
I can build a much smaller area to support this current
The superconducting magnet is not only the magnet with the highest magnetic field
it is also the magnet with the highest engineering current density
both parameters are achieved simultaneously
This allows us to miniaturize fusion devices.
I mentioned this goal just now.
When the current is high,
the magnetic field becomes stronger.
Not only does this pose a significant challenge in terms of force,
but also, when the current is very high,
it generates heat.
As we all know, this is Ohmic heating,
which is proportional to the square of the current.
Then multiply by the resistance.
For example, when we were at 22,
when we were approaching the 22nd measurement,
the single-strand current was around 20 kiloamperes.
What does that mean?
It means that a resistance of about one nanoohm generates nearly one watt of heat.
For low temperatures,
a watt level of heat generation is already quite significant.
And it requires that under such a high current,
You need to consider the entire magnet.
It's impossible for everything to be superconducting.
You will still have some joints.
These connecting components.
They will also generate heat during the process.
If you want to keep the total heat generation at the hundred-watt level,
You need to manage all these connections,
Even the resistance introduced during installation,
Must be controlled at the 100 nano-ohm level.
That's 10 to the power of 100 times 10 to the ninth ohms.
It's about your control over the hot blood.
You need to achieve a very low resistance.
And in this case,
to dissipate these hundreds of watts of heat,
you need to specifically design within the magnet,
channels for heat dissipation,
and supply the cooling helium to
the areas where it might overheat.
Right
to ensure this magnet
operates stably at your design temperature
in this process
as I just mentioned
my magnet, to achieve high engineering current density
is already at a premium
so you can't fit in much structural material
and you also need to dig out some holes
Optimize your fluid
Ensure your cooling system is effective
So when you're balancing the thermoelectric process
You need to evaluate the design
To push the dimensions of these three components to their limits
And ensure stability
This way, you can design a high magnetic field
With a high current density magnet
This is what the design process entails
It essentially pushes all the parameters to an extreme edge.
an extremely challenging state
Only then is the design just barely completed.
After the design is completed,
whether this thing can actually be manufactured is the question.
The thing we just mentioned,
when you design it, everything is perfect,
these conductors, right?
there are no engineering flaws in your design.
It won't degrade in performance during processing, right?
You need to assemble these superconducting tapes,
these frameworks with very complex structures,
connect them together,
assemble them together,
with winding in between,
insulation,
joint fabrication,
a series of procedures.
The final performance remains unchanged
in order to deliver it
all the process development involved
is actually a very challenging task
during this process, you have a lot of research
for example
it's like, for instance, a critical step is
I need to use this metal
to integrate the superconducting tape with the framework
Otherwise, if they are two separate pieces
you actually have a pretty bad hand
you need to melt them together with metal
similar to toasting bread
how does the temperature in your oven climb up
how long to pause and many other detailed parameters
when to add the metal
when to melt it into a liquid
and when to cool down
Every detail and parameter at each step
will impact your final performance.
If the temperature is too high,
the performance of the superconducting tape will degrade, right?
And if the temperature is not sufficient,
the process won’t work properly.
Right?
These are the kinds of intricate issues involving hundreds or even thousands of IDs.
Very detailed problems.
It's something you need to face every day
And only when you actually put this into practice
Can you truly believe it
That this set of process parameters is actually feasible
Yeah
This is about making the magnet reach such a high level
Of parameter specifications
You've roughly gone through the process from design to manufacturing
The issues that need to be addressed
It's like the heart of the Red-Yellow 170 or something.
It's actually part of the Honghuang 170.
There's a very critical system.
It's the toroidal field, called the TF coils.
There are 18 of these toroidal field coils.
These 18 coils are assembled on the 170.
The maximum field strength is about 23 teslas.
To fully validate this,
I can create a magnet under 23 teslas conditions.
So today, I'm actually using a magnet
to achieve a parameter close to 23 teslas
which serves as a thorough validation
from design to manufacturing process for the 170 tesla toroidal field magnet
It won't go straight to 170 teslas
but using the design and manufacturing techniques for the groundbreaking magnet
the processing methods
we are definitely capable of producing
the 170 tesla epoxy-impregnated anti-magnet
Because the font parameters are actually not as high as this one.
It's also a verification.
Yes, it's a verification.
So, from today's magnet to the Red Yellow 170, how many steps are left?
Are there also subsystems that need to be verified?
Yes, there are many for Phoenix 170.
If we look at it in terms of 9 to 10 primary subsystems,
three of the primary subsystems are the most expensive.
The magnet system has been mentioned.
The heating system is a system.
The power supply system is also a system.
These three costs combined make up roughly 90% of the entire apparatus's
hardware costs.
Among these systems, the first prototype
is similar to today’s 170 gliding range.
It represents the first process for the magnet.
It's like a prototype for the prediction model.
The heating system is the same.
The first transmitter
we also need to develop and design ourselves
to achieve the performance targets in development
the power supply is the same
yes, all of it is done in-house
of course, there are many smaller systems as well
like diagnostics
these cryogenic systems and other components all require validation
the basic logic is as follows
We were just talking about a device
from design to delivery
there's an initial physical design concept
followed by the engineering design, right?
We're pursuing the high-temperature superconducting tokamak technology route
including the design of our device
in the physical design phase, we opted for a relatively conservative approach
similar to the design methodology used 30 years ago in ITER
this design path
We don’t want to take physical risks.
We don’t want to take scientific risks.
We all use methods that have a lot of experimental evidence.
This physics serves as the foundation for our design.
In other words,
if you use these formulas and parameters for the physical design,
as long as your engineering parameters meet the design specifications,
the final performance of the plasma can be achieved,
with a very high probability.
Because my approach to physics is quite conservative
very traditional
as long as the input parameters for these formulas
the engineering parameters meet the standards
satisfy my design requirements
that's all I need
so I focused on this device
the final plasma
for example, whether it can achieve a Q greater than ten
From a complete system perspective
what was once a physical risk has turned into an engineering risk
When it comes to engineering risks
it's still divided into two subcategories
The first one is
the parameters of this decoration project are all very high
so can we actually build subsystems with such high parameters
This then becomes
each subsystem has its own design objective
Can I get a device or a sample for prediction?
A prototype to prove that I can deliver this subsystem?
Just like today's magnets for the TF sliding field magnet.
Hmm.
I managed to create a magnet that might even exceed the parameters of my final device.
One with even higher parameters.
If I can do this, I can definitely do the one for the final device.
I’m sure I can pull it off for the final device.
The same logic applies to my other systems as well.
I don’t need to wait until I’ve built the entire device.
to be able to verify it.
I can make it work.
the first prototype of each subsystem.
as long as I can achieve the same engineering parameters.
I believe I have the capability to deliver it.
each subsystem, that is.
This is how we handle a system that’s incredibly complex.
a goal
it has been transformed into a set of high-parameter objectives for subsystems
and the first prototype of each subsystem is used for validation
I have the capability to make it happen
This is his approach to transformation
Of course
There's another thing
that is, can you manufacture all these subsystems I just mentioned
can you integrate them
will the performance remain the same after integration
Sure
Regarding this matter
We have actually had extensive practice and validation on the Honghuang Qiling device
We have thoroughly tested how the subsystems of this device work together
What the interfaces look like
If there are conflicts
Whether to adjust A or B, and how to make those trade-offs
What risks they might encounter during the assembly process
What risks do they face during the process?
When is the best time to conduct and address these risk assessments?
During the development of the Z70 process,
we have accumulated a wealth of experience.
Why can't we directly develop the Honghuang 170?
There are two aspects to consider here.
Firstly, the Honghuang 170 is a very costly project,
with a 3 billion Euro facility in the EU.
So, when we started the business a few years ago,
So when I first started my business a few years ago
I don't think I have that kind of
ability to directly secure such financial support
Your team of four who have never worked on a tokamak
I think it would be nearly impossible to secure such a large amount of funding
that's almost an impossible task, right?
Of course, on the other hand
still
a team that hasn't worked on a tokamak
how can you have the confidence to build such a device
Building the world's highest parameter device is correct.
So during this process,
we set up
for example, we first built a device with lower parameters,
like the Honghuang Qilin device,
which might cost about 150 million RMB,
and we ultimately spent approximately 120 million RMB,
to create this device,
we demonstrated our capability in systems engineering.
This complex apparatus
was entirely designed in a very short time
and delivered it
The gap between this low-parameter apparatus and the high-parameter one
lies in what exactly?
It’s that the parameters of each subsystem become much higher
For example, the highest magnetic field of 70 is 3.1 Tesla
while for 170, the highest magnetic field is 23 Tesla
Right
Such a high magnetic field
A change that's roughly ten times
I will work on a subsystem
For example, the Sky Magnet
This system can achieve around 22 teslas, right?
Then I can validate
That I have the capability to produce 170
Through the validation of this complete device
And the most critical part
The most challenging
and the most expensive subsystem to verify
Of course, we will also be validating other subsystems
Ultimately, to prove that I have the capability to build the 170
Then I can secure the funding needed to build the 170
We will then work on the 170
From the inside out
Whether my team has the capability to build it
And in terms of financial support
Because your team has this capability
that's why everyone trusts you and provides you with this kind of funding
to get this device completed
How's the fundraising going?
We are still in the process of raising funds
Yes, it's a substantial amount of money
and investors can't expect a short exit timeline
I can only say that it is indeed a cycle
a rather long-term project
And as we mentioned, the first commercialization
Our product is expected to be around 2030 to 2035
There is indeed such a development cycle, right
So the patience required for funding is quite high
There are four fully superconducting tokamaks operating globally
Could you comment on the other three
The other three are all low-temperature superconducting devices
One of them is the EAST in China that we just mentioned
The device in Hefei
One is a device from South Korea called K Star.
The other is the JTE60SA built in Japan.
Since ITER is a cryogenic superconducting tokamak device,
while building ITER,
several such devices have been constructed around the world,
to verify at that point,
for example, whether cryogenic superconducting can be achieved in engineering,
and what issues might arise during its operation,
as well as the engineering challenges during long-term operation.
So these are the three devices for ITER.
They are all about cryogenic superconducting.
They provided a lot of insights into the feasibility of construction and operational stability.
They have offered a wealth of experience.
Of course, this is also due to their superconducting devices.
For example, the EAST device in China.
It particularly achieved a 1000-second run this year.
This is a long-pulse operation.
It's also a new world record.
Because only superconducting devices can operate for extended periods.
Other devices can't do that, right?
So, for these long pulses and steady-state operations,
it's like controlling them ourselves,
these tasks,
all these devices are constantly pushing the boundaries and setting new world records.
These are some of the ongoing processes.
From your tests, what advantages do you think high-temperature superconductors offer?
And what specific advantages does low-temperature superconductivity ultimately provide?
I think everyone can see this.
The advantage is the high magnetic field, which leads to a smaller device size.
This, in turn, results in lower costs.
This is quite straightforward.
Basic physics can explain this.
So I don't think there's much disagreement on this.
The benefits are quite apparent to many people.
Why are we the ones pushing for this?
Or perhaps the only ones in the country pushing for it.
Because it's so new.
As I mentioned.
The processability of this material,
under such high parameters,
whether it can be designed,
and if designed, whether it can be manufactured,
all these are uncertainties.
They're all risks.
So it falls into a typical high-risk, high-reward approach.
It might be that you can't figure it out.
It could be that you encounter some
issues you never anticipated.
But only by completing it
can you truly verify it.
That's why we started pushing this project from 2021.
Including the world's first Red Yellow Kylin,
fully high-temperature superconducting,
and the work we've done on it.
The strongest magnet created using high-temperature superconductivity
This happened in March this year
Everything else is quite new, right?
So I think regarding this matter
There was no consensus on whether it could be achieved
We were the earliest and have been fully committed to pushing this forward
So the new record, as well
The latest achievements in this field, as well
Have all been driven by our team
It's like this.
I don't think it's as simple as everyone assumes it can be done.
It won't bring any benefits.
I believe this isn't something that can just be assumed to work.
The benefits, if any, should be clear to everyone.
But whether it can actually be achieved,
or how long it will take,
or who will accomplish it,
remains a question for many teams.
We have a strong confidence in this matter.
We believe we can definitely make it happen.
And our team has faith in itself.
It should be completed soon.
So we've managed to achieve these goals.
How much can the cost be reduced?
And how much smaller can the device be?
For example, achieving the same performance as ITER, with Q greater than ten.
The device's volume is roughly only 2% of ITER's.
It's about 50 times smaller
The cost is also roughly 50 times less
That's about 2.5 billion euros
From our perspective, it can be done for 400 million dollars
So it's also several dozen times less
So the red one at 380 has a higher magnetic field?
It's higher
Yes, it could be around 23 to 29 Tesla
What other metrics are different?'
The device will also be larger in size.
So the 380 model is about twice the size of the 170 model.
Nearly twice as large.
Therefore, the linear dimensions of the entire device are about twice as big.
The volume might increase by roughly ten times for the 23 layers.
The magnetic field is also stronger.
It goes from about 23 Tesla to 29 Tesla.
It serves as a demonstration power plant.
While the 170 is still an experimental device.
So I won’t bother with building
like those water cooling systems that run for long periods
or the systems to channel out the generated energy
I won’t be setting up any of these water cooling systems
This is a way to minimize costs, right?
But for 380
as a power station
all these things need to be done, right?
So its size will have to be expanded
So, 380 is a complete
capable of operating for long periods as a demonstration power station.
While 170 is just an experimental setup
designed to achieve experimental parameters in the shortest time possible
at the lowest cost.
How much would it cost for 300?
Our goal
is actually to set the price of 380 at about
1,000 watts.
40,000 to 50,000 RMB
this level
what does that mean
it means for a 500-megawatt facility
the cost is roughly between 200 to 250 billion RMB
we need 200 billion RMB
just recently
we have built the fourth-generation low-carbon demonstration reactor in our country
which is the high-temperature gas-cooled reactor
It's roughly 1,000 watts for between 400,000 to 500,000 RMB.
And we believe that if the first fusion demonstration power plant
can achieve this cost,
because my raw materials are non-radioactive,
and the reaction products also do not have long-term radioactivity.
I have significant natural advantages over fission power plants in terms of raw material availability,
as well as safety and waste disposal.
There are substantial inherent advantages.
So we believe that when the construction cost is the same,
This power station could be quite appealing to nuclear power plant owners.
It might have a significant appeal.
That's our goal.
The first power station is expected to be around 1,000 watts.
The construction cost is estimated to be between 40,000 to 50,000 RMB.
I'm referring to the construction cost, mind you.
Oh, because your facility is a...
What's your design target for the power output?
But what you're really comparing is the cost per kilowatt.
It's about the cost
The total cost is estimated to be around 20 to 25 billion RMB
Just the basic cost
We estimate it to be between 10 to 20 billion RMB
Between 10 to 20 billion RMB
And then adding 3 billion for the additional 170
So in total, it would be around 20 billion RMB
The third device, Honghuang
380 is actually one of our products
It's us who will sell it out
We serve as the supplier of the equipment for this product
To sell it out
So for us
What our team needs internally is
Actually mainly to set up the device 170
Roughly 3 billion RMB, right
But doesn't the 380 also require costs
But this cost is for me to sell it out
You need to sell first
and then produce
which means producing first
and then selling
there will definitely be people with this demand
I will customize according to their needs
it's a product like that
so we still need 3 billion
that's right
I don't need more money.
So are you planning to raise all the funds at once now?
We are raising funds in batches.
Is the technical approach different from SAM's investment in Helium Energy?
Not really.
Helium also uses magnetic confinement.
But their magnetic field satellite is linear.
Ours is more like a doughnut shape.
They are called long linear types.
It's called FRC, Field Reverse Configuration.
It's a long-range anti-satellite device.
According to the academic materials that have been made public,
the current highest-spec long-range anti-satellite device,
is roughly three times as powerful.
If I'm not mistaken,
it's around 10 to the 17th, not quite reaching 10 to the 18th yet.
So it's still about 10 to the 20th short.
It's four orders of magnitude off.
So we feel this is a scientific approach
a highly risky technical route
Let me give you an analogy
Suppose I'm building an airplane
I currently have experimental data for flights from zero to ten meters
Then I extrapolate this data to ten thousand meters altitude
To design an airplane
You might very well, in the process of extrapolation
Fail to realize that the air gets much thinner
The temperature is dropping, and these things are happening.
So you use the experimental data from zero to ten meters.
It's roughly three orders of magnitude.
What you design might ultimately fly there.
But it won't take off, right?
So this is the issue when you only have
For example, experimental data up to the 17th power.
You need to extrapolate to the 20th power.
You face the same problem.
Because you don't know
whether from the 17th power to the 20th power
if there might be some new
or the new physical processes we just mentioned
introduced into your equations
which might not have existed before
If there are
then the current extrapolation design might fail
Of course, if we have very good luck
No new physics has been discovered
Some even suggest that new physics might be beneficial to you
That would be even better
But to me, these all fall under scientific risks
It's even uncertain whether an answer to this question exists
So we believe that such endeavors are more suitable for research institutes
Or universities to tackle these scientifically risky questions
They used to be more radical in their approaches
We think that is not the case anymore
The scientific feasibility has been validated.
So why choose this direction?
The result we can see is that
There are many fusion companies in the U.S. as well,
it's almost unheard of for two fusion companies
to have exactly the same technical approach.
As I mentioned, the first-mover advantage in fusion is incredibly strong.
There aren't many people in your field either.
Every project requires a substantial amount of funding.
So the second place on the same technical track
is actually quite hard to exist
Therefore, on a technical track
you might invest in the first one
which takes all the talents
including the funds for self-cultivation
and everything else
So it's not a monopoly due to competition
but rather a monopoly due to talent
The capital monopoly
leads to the first place having a much greater advantage over the second
so there’s no reason to support the second place anymore
on the same technological path
unless you switch to a different technological path
it requires too much money
right?
and there aren’t enough people
you can’t attract better talent even as the second place
Because the best people have already been recruited by the top company
You
have to tackle the issues that the second place needs to address
The leading company might have been working on them for two years already
So they still have an advantage over you
Their overall technical talent
and the funding cycle is a very rapid positive feedback loop
So on the same technical path
You won't see two identical companies
So, what do the other fusion companies do?
They follow different technical approaches.
For example, CFS initially focused on high-temperature superconducting tokamaks.
Other companies might work on long-pulse satellites,
or spherical tokamaks,
or stellarators.
Basically, they explore other technical routes.
CFS and its approach are also different.
GF is similar to yours, right?
A bit more similar
Right, right
Hi, it seems that this store is also SAM's only personal investment besides AI
Yes
What do you think is the relationship between nuclear fusion and AI?
The basic logic goes like this
First, AI is definitely in an exponential growth phase
Rapidly developing process
Well, a fundamental law of physics tells us
It's anything that grows exponentially
it will continue to grow
until it hits a bottleneck
for example, in the short term, people might think of some bottlenecks in AI
like the bottleneck in computing power, right
or the bottleneck in chip size, right
and then the bottleneck in data
if these issues can actually be addressed, for instance, if production capacity can keep up
if data can be generated
So moving forward
I think the real significant bottleneck
is the bottleneck in energy supply
This issue
involves very high requirements for infrastructure
If it becomes a major electricity consumer
it already accounts for a few percent
If it were to reach several tens of percent
it would mean a much larger scale of energy supply is needed
Actually, when it comes to energy
the demand is always there
as long as you can provide the energy
it will definitely be used up
Yeah, right
the key is whether we can provide that much energy
but the core logic of being able to provide this energy
is whether the cost of your energy can come down
if the cost remains the same
You actually can't provide any more energy.
Because it doesn't generate any profit.
Right, only when your costs can significantly decrease.
Can you then increase the supply of energy on a large scale.
And we believe that as long as you can increase the energy supply,
It will certainly be used up quickly.
Right, exactly.
Like computers,
You never say your computing power is too much.
The supply capability far exceeds the demand.
As soon as your performance improves,
there will definitely be an application
that will fully utilize the new capabilities of your computer, right?
So it's the same with energy, right?
We believe that AI will certainly, in the near future,
become a bottleneck due to energy constraints.
Of course, we can already see many large-scale
data centers.
Actually, its power consumption is quite significant.
The U.S. also supports renewable energy.
Companies supporting fusion,
These are mostly internet or AI companies.
They are also preparing for the next step,
Especially regarding the provision of infinite energy.
They are laying the groundwork for it.
I think, conversely,
AI plays a crucial role in nuclear fusion.
AI is also a highly effective process for reducing costs and improving efficiency in nuclear fusion.
In particular,
AI plays a significant role in fusion,
with several major contributions.
First, during the operation of the device,
it can quickly and accurately provide real-time AI-driven
control methods.
and accurately provide a real-time AI-driven
Such a control mechanism
Because the real-time requirements for control are actually quite high
Traditional models have a significant computational complexity
So very complex models
Cannot be used for real-time control
But now, with the acceleration of AI
Including the simulation of these very complex physical processes
Through the equivalent simulation by AI operators
And algorithms that have a very short computation time
Such algorithms are crucial for the real-time control of my final device
It actually makes a significant difference.
Including a couple of years ago,
DMI used a tokamak in Europe,
completely relying on AI for its control,
and within a very short time,
it was able to achieve this with very few iterations.
Previously, it took people a lot of time,
accumulating through experiments to achieve the same results with experimental satellites.
So, the first thing AI did was
Real-time control of the device is highly beneficial.
Secondly,
it can actually replace these diagnostic tools.
Many of these advanced diagnostics
are quite expensive.
And the development challenges are significant.
This logic is somewhat like applying AI to image processing
or the medical field,
enhancing your diagnostic capabilities.
You might not need to build a high-cost hardware device
but an AI-based algorithm
can provide you with a more accurate or higher resolution
diagnostic result.
So, the use of AI in diagnostic systems
is also a major research direction now.
It brings cost reduction and efficiency improvement.
Another area is plasma simulation,
if our simulations are precise enough.
In principle, we don't need to conduct experiments.
But of course, your implementation and your simulation
will have some discrepancies.
For instance, what you envision is an ideal device.
But during the manufacturing process, there might be a few millimeters of deviation.
A few millimeters can make a difference, right?
Assembly can also introduce such discrepancies.
There's a hole.
Which wasn't present in the ideal model you originally designed.
These things could potentially affect your use of first principles.
There's a gap between the simulation of ideal models and real-world scenarios.
If I can use some of these AI models,
I can use real experimental data as input,
to train such a model,
for a facility that has already been built,
to simulate and modernize it.
I don't need to extend to other facilities,
just for this facility, my predictive capability is strong enough.
It can significantly reduce
the number of experiments needed to finally obtain
the parameters I want
because originally you might need to conduct 100 experiments
but now you might only need to do two
and in your simulation environment
you can already achieve good predictions
so many of the intermediate experiments can be skipped
and you can move on to the next phase of experimentation
Right
So it's based on a faster and more accurate
prediction of plasma
which significantly shortens the iteration cycle of your experiments
Exactly
So I think AI has a significant impact on fusion
overall, it reduces costs and boosts efficiency
reducing the time cost
and reducing the financial cost
Its application scenarios include control,
diagnosis,
and experimental operations.
These areas can benefit significantly from it.
Now, does AI have the capability to make such an impact?
Over the past few years,
the most influential has been DeepMind.
These works include two papers published in Nature.
Alright.
Using purely AI algorithms
to control plasma on a device in Europe
and the performance is well-controlled
So this is just the initial work
We believe that more and more devices in the future
including our own device
we are also replacing some of the control algorithms with AI algorithms
to achieve better experimental results more quickly
So have you collaborated with any AI companies or something like that?
I believe this will definitely happen in the future.
For now, we don't have that yet.
For now, it's still a team-developed state.
This is because the interfaces are very complex.
Handling everything internally would be more efficient.
K Chain claims to build the world's first nuclear fusion power plant by 2028.
You're talking about 2035, right?
That's building a fusion power plant by 2028.
This is indeed a very ambitious goal.
And within our team,
we don't fully understand it,
from a theoretical standpoint,
why that approach works,
of course, the company has released very little information,
they rarely share their thoughts publicly,
many people do support them, though,
but there's very little academic content,
so it's really hard for us to make a judgment.
For instance, there might indeed be some physics we haven't considered.
Some of them have a very unique understanding of physics, that's true.
But it's based on the information that's publicly available to everyone.
And the principles of physics that we all know,
given the knowledge that we all have,
we don't fully understand this technical approach.
How they ultimately achieve this energy balance,
and break-even issues,
overseas, like CFS.
And there's also attachment
And there are also some companies in China
Including your company and Xin Huan Junning, among others
What do you think about the current landscape and theater of fusion research between China and the U.S.?
What are the differences in progress?
The basic situation is
Indeed, both China and the U.S. are developing very rapidly
And the main efforts are concentrated in these two places
Whether it's the investment in fusion
And the progress has been good
it's all been very fast
these two markets are naturally segmented
What does that mean?
It's highly likely that China's fusion technology
won't rely on the U.S. to help us achieve it
so China definitely needs its own team
to get this done
and the U.S. can't do it either
It's highly unlikely that such technology would be imported from China.
To help them build the fusion power plant.
So he has his local team working on it, right?
So this is true both in terms of demand,
The scale of funding available,
The pool of talent,
And the supply chain and technological reserves,
These two aspects are most likely,
To be the earliest places to achieve fusion.
And they should all have their own teams working on it.
This is our basic assessment, I suppose.
Of course, speaking of the current situation,
the majority of commercial investments
still occur in America or Western countries.
Regarding the total funding amount,
the fusion sector has raised nearly 6 billion dollars.
Speaking of the U.S.,
there are probably around 40 startups in the West.
Exactly.
There are probably fewer than ten startups in China.
That sounds about right.
Quite a few less.
In terms of companies,
it should be around 10 billion RMB now.
this is the total scale combined.
I haven’t evaluated the specific details,
but the plan is for 10 billion RMB.
This figure is around several billion dollars.
Our assessment is that
both China and the United States
are most likely to be the earliest to achieve commercial fusion.
and everyone is relatively independent in terms of technology,
you don't know how others are doing it,
and others probably don't know how you're doing it either.
Everyone is working on their own,
and the technical approaches may differ.
The technical approach is actually quite similar.
First, you have a lot of production companies in the U.S.
Like our technical approach,
it's largely consistent with the CFS technology route.
For example, there are also some startups in China,
which might be largely consistent with HELION’s technology route.
It’s very likely that the leading companies in the U.S.
will have corresponding companies in China.
Are you modeled after CFX?'
ZFS was established earlier than us
and when we started this company
we also assessed high-temperature superconductivity
and the tokamak route
as the fastest path to commercialization
So in terms of the overall direction
we chose the tokamak
we opted for high-temperature superconductivity
this is the same as CFS
Who in the country is similar to him?
I remember there are two companies working on FRC.
One is in Chengdu.
The other one is in Hefei, I believe.
Are you suggesting that your costs will be half of what it takes for financial autonomy in the U.S.?
It's also more compact.
How is this achieved?
Most likely, the Chinese team will make it more cost-effective.
Actually, it's the same with AI today.
This is our team's goal
which includes our values
which are extreme efficiency and seeking truth from facts
and our goal is actually 170
to create the world's lowest-cost
most cost-effective
device that achieves Q greater than or equal to ten
Actually, we've been working on this from the design phase
including the overall design of the entire device
The selection of raw materials
The choice of suppliers
Including the selection of our process routes
Are all aimed at achieving this goal
So we are, within our understanding and design
Constraints
Aiming for the lowest cost direction to design the 170
And based on the entire construction process of the 70
We focus on the cost of each subsystem
There is a very clear
a highly detailed nanny model
to optimize the entire system
the final design outcome
is roughly a 3 billion RMB
such a device
ultimately, we're not quite sure
why it costs 1 billion USD in the U.S.
they haven't disclosed their application details
This is just the level we've optimized to.
We also feel that further optimization would be quite challenging.
To achieve such a low cost.
As I mentioned,
your overall design is the lowest-cost design.
And we use components that are readily available in the market.
Our suppliers are highly competitive.
There's a lot of overcapacity in the market.
Otherwise, it would be relatively monopolized.
Or only one or two companies can do it
Which gives them significant bargaining power
And we’ll be using a lot of self-developed components in the long term
So we can just buy some materials
Right
So by this method
From design to manufacturing, to process, and finally to experimental operation
We are always aiming for the lowest cost in optimization
The final design will be
It might be the most cost-effective device in the world
capable of achieving this level of performance.
How challenging is it to generate the first kilowatt-hour of electricity from nuclear fusion?
To produce the first kilowatt-hour under conditions similar to those of coal power plants
is indeed quite challenging.
And this task
we estimate, will be achieved by the device between 2030 and 2035.
The Red Team's goal is to reach 380.
Exactly.
Of course, if cost is no object
I think, well, even Yi Te could achieve it
What are the most challenging issues?
The three zero-level problems you mentioned
When it comes to power generation
There are a few gaps
First, you need a power generation device
And of course, Q needs to be sufficiently large
For example, Q needs to be at least ten, right
You need to demonstrate that your output power is significantly greater than the input power.
And you need to achieve this with the plasma,
and be able to stabilize it, right?
That’s the goal of 170, then.
And for the second point,
we need to address the issues at 380.
It’s not just about stabilizing it for a short period of time,
but ensuring it remains stable,
for a very long duration.
A long pulse is needed to achieve high parameters.
This means
that the engineering stability of each subsystem
and the thermal stability of the entire device
as well as the stability of control during long-term operation
all require very high standards.
Right.
You can't afford any system
for example, one that can't run for five hours on its own.
Then the entire system definitely wouldn't run for five hours, right?
Each subsystem might just shut down.
So, when it comes to long-term stable operation,
it's crucial for the ultimate realization of fusion,
like fusion power plants, which might operate for weeks in the future,
such a device needs to be capable of sustained operation at that level.
This is a hurdle that needs to be overcome.
The current state of the art,
is around 1000 seconds at EAST, right?
This is a challenge even at 10,000 or 100,000 seconds.
This is the second point.
It involves long-term steady-state operation.
The third point, from our perspective,
is the true commercialization of fusion.
Its raw material actually needs to be used for power generation.
Not for cutting, um,
because Chuan is a first,
it is a highly regulated thing.
But using uranium can produce hydrogen bombs.
So, whether it's regulation,
or the cost,
they are both extremely high and challenging.
The consequence is,
the cost of electricity generation will definitely be high.
And the regulatory requirements are very stringent.
Therefore, in terms of design,
or safety protection,
There are also very high additional costs
and regulatory requirements are also placed here
If the construction period is long
you will eventually convert everything into the cost per unit of electricity
Right
and sulfur cannot exist stably in nature either
so you need to generate electricity and deal with this issue simultaneously
which also increases the difficulty of many projects
how to handle it
Production
During the fusion process, the neutrons produced are used to bombard lithium-6
Then it will produce tritium
So, after producing neutrons, one tritium is consumed
But during the process, you need to produce more than one neutron
Then use these neutrons to react with lithium-6
To produce more than one tritium
In that case, the tritium breeding ratio needs to be greater than one
One is consumed
It generates more than one, um
Then you collect the generated strings
And send them back to the raw material for processing
This is what the ship factory does
If you use a knife to pierce
You need to set up a piercing factory
And continue to produce piercing during the operation of the equipment
First, send the piercing back into the equipment
But what we actually aim to do is build a power station for the knives
I don't actually need a ship.
There's plenty of seawater for human use for billions of years.
So, I just need to use the material as a raw material.
Then proceed with the fusion reaction.
So, I won't set up a ship.
And the entire facility, including supervision,
including the cost side,
I don't even need to consider setting up a factory.
This is what we believe to be a truly scaled commercial power station.
Actually, we need to address the Dadao issue.
It's Dao Dao.
Actually, the reaction is an order of magnitude more challenging than Daochuan.
We haven't achieved it yet.
Right.
Now, it's about 20 to the power of one.
In reality, it still needs to be achieved by Daochuan.
While Dadao roughly needs to reach 22 to the power of one.
From generating the first kilowatt-hour to becoming a mainstream global energy source.
How many goods do you think need to be bridged in between?
Our judgment is that we can make an analogy, right?
Like the first fission demonstration power plant back then,
to when it actually became commercial,
fission reactors took about 10 years,
I think the time scale is roughly similar.
The first fusion demonstration power plant,
to when it becomes a commercial power plant,
it might be a similar process.
Your production stability
has reached a level where
it could potentially run 24/7.
Once commercial nuclear fusion is achieved,
what impact do you think it will have on the current energy market landscape?
How significant do you think this impact will be?
Can you estimate the scale and influence of this impact?
We believe that the cost per unit of electricity would be comparable to that of coal power.
In that case, it could serve as a significant part of the energy mix.
Thermal power, for instance, provides this energy.
But this impact is actually quite limited.
However, when your cost per unit of electricity is significantly lower, for example, than that of thermal power,
like an order of magnitude lower,
then you might completely transform
the way humans use energy.
That’s right, from our perspective.
If your cost per unit of electricity remains much higher than thermal power’s,
then there would be no significant impact.
Where do you think that pivotal turning point will occur?
Will it occur?
Yes, it will.
This is very confident.
It will happen, right?
Like your first fusion demonstration power plant.
For example, if you achieve the current design of 380.
It might cost around 40 to 50 cents per kilowatt-hour.
It would still be more expensive than coal power.
But when you reach this level,
you're almost at that turning point.
Because the cost of your first demonstration radio station is always high,
but everyone can see that
your costs are almost on par with coal power.
And you can clearly predict that
when I scale up production,
my costs will be significantly lower.
At this point, it will become a
From a commercial perspective
it should be a major turning point
many people might start to request this
I'll build multiple substations
Looking further back
I actually think an earlier turning point
might have been the construction worldwide
of the first device where Q is greater than or equal to ten
or even not necessarily equal to ten
Q is greater than or equal to one
such a fusion power plant
with a similar cost
whether it's 170 or
Spark or
this technology pathway with a cost comparable to coal-fired power
to achieve this goal
from our perspective
is akin to the impact of ChatGPT on the AI field
Before ChatGPT emerged
people might have thought of AI as a useful
tool, for instance
image recognition
speech recognition
a tool for proliferation
but after ChatGPT came along
and even to this day
we still haven't achieved general artificial intelligence
However, the dissection of GPT's outcomes has led people to believe
that a consensus is forming among many
that general artificial intelligence will become a reality in the future
Regarding this consensus in the field of fusion
we believe it is highly likely on a global scale
that a technology pathway with a cost similar to that of coal power
will result in the construction of a device with a Q factor of ten or greater
We think it might also be the spark
or the construction of a device like our 170
It might lead to a consensus like this.
If a drastic change could be realized,
and energy became infinite,
how would the world change?
When energy can be used at an extremely low cost,
a civilization would certainly become very different.
For example, many issues,
such as whether food still needs to be grown,
or if it could be industrially synthesized, right?
So your main cost is actually the cost of your energy.
If your entire energy supply is very cheap,
a lot of what you have now might be produced by natural processes.
These products
can all be achieved through artificial synthesis.
And now, for example, we're also considering
like traveling beyond Earth,
you have a significant amount of energy loss, right?
That might be possible when energy is very cheap.
You don't really care about this matter.
You can provide enough energy to generate it.
To carry out interstellar colonization.
Like the most fundamental things.
It will exhibit higher intelligence.
Absolutely.
There will certainly be a lot of these on the demand side.
New ways to utilize energy.
Traditionally, the numbers might not add up.
But now you'll find that this can actually be done.
So, what kind of applications will emerge in the future?
It's really hard to predict.
But if the energy structure changes,
human civilization will advance by leaps and bounds.
So I think this is
probably a transformative change for civilization.
How much would it cost to achieve scalable controlled nuclear fusion?
What I mentioned earlier was the cost of each facility.
I don't really have a clear visibility on this issue.
a clear view
I think it will be when the first fusion demonstration power plant
like the 380 power plant is built,
that we might have a better understanding of what issues a commercial power plant
still needs to address,
and we will have a clearer picture.
And during the scaling-up process,
the rate at which costs will decrease will become clearer.
There will be a drop of one order of magnitude within a few years.
He has a fairly clear understanding of this.
Looking at what happens after 380 does seem a bit far off now.
What are the main issues you're thinking about these days?
Of course, they all revolve around making this happen.
The issues that arise from it.
I think a major part of my daily thoughts and actions revolve around
how to quickly build up
and enhance the capabilities of the entire team.
Because there weren’t any ready-made people
and what they were doing was all very new
so what this team needed to do was
to think of the team as a machine
with a lot of strong fundamentals
ambition
a sense of responsibility
and great stress resilience
people who are very smart
But he won't do that.
And then after joining the team,
it takes a very short time to become
possibly the best in the world in a certain field.
This is the team itself, as a machine,
the inputs and outputs that create such a team,
this is actually the thing that takes the most time on a daily basis.
Of course, a good team,
good soldiers are forged through battles.
Actually, it's not like you cultivated him.
He developed through the numerous projects you worked on together.
Everyone was responsible for their own tasks.
And from first principles,
starting at the formula level,
the process I just mentioned,
running simulations and experiments based on formulas,
building it up step by step,
you managed to get him through it.
Then the team has this capability.
So, how do we optimize during this process?
How can we use a more correct approach?
Even if you might also do this task,
success could be due to good luck.
And some incorrect coin flips,
ended up with heads, right?
But how do you really systematically ensure that he does it correctly next time?
Or consistently maintains the right state when doing it frequently?
So, how do we think about this problem correctly?
How do we formulate the right questions?
How do we eliminate unnecessary tasks?
You need to focus all your resources on
the most critical few issues.
Then, use the most efficient methods to get them done.
This is actually about training the team to consider every specific action they take.
These are the questions that need to be addressed.
And use this standard to continuously hold the team accountable.
I need to continuously raise my own standards
I have to identify areas where improvements can be made
In this way, the organization as a whole benefits when I bring in
new members with a strong foundation
who will quickly integrate into the team after a short period
and possess exceptional programming skills
becoming top-tier in their specific field
parameters that others might deem impossible to achieve
we can accomplish swiftly
So this is something I think is worth spending time pondering over,
whether it's about doing tasks,
it's the thing that takes up the most time,
and it actually integrates into every day's work.
It's about solving a problem,
not just how to solve it,
but also thinking about the problem itself,
why it happened in the first place,
what could have been done differently at the time.
This issue might not have occurred.
Why wasn't this done at the time?
What information was insufficient back then?
Or was there something that wasn't considered?
Or was it the team's capability?
Why was it inadequate at the time?
Can we systematically address this in the future?
This is an issue that can be resolved at the policy level.
Or does it require a higher level of awareness from people?
People have a higher capacity for thought.
Is it about raising the ceiling or the floor?
The floor is actually easier to address.
Establish clear rules and regulations.
And enforce them strictly.
Raising the ceiling requires your team to recognize the importance.
First, there's still a significant gap between what we call 'good'.
What exactly is the cause of this gap?
Is it due to mental inertia or inertia in action?
It's due to a cognitive bias, thinking that it might not be possible.
But without considering it from an experiential perspective,
people might think it can't be done,
without carefully examining it,
or analyzing it from a fundamental standpoint,
whether it's due to insufficient effort or other reasons.
At the time, there was an instinctive judgment,
that it might not be feasible,
or that it shouldn't be done.
So these things happen every time we encounter a problem
We try to delve deeper
And ultimately, we aim to make the entire team
Not just me, but the whole team is engaged in this
How many people are there now
150 people
Now, his team, compared to AI companies
Or internet companies
Do they have the same organizational structure
But now the number of people might be more similar to Company I.
First, I think it definitely doesn’t resemble an internet company, right?
Because, in fact, the workforce in the internet industry,
there is actually a fairly ample supply of talent in the market.
Right, right.
And the level of specialization for each position is quite high.
Well, it’s not that high here.
We might work on this system today,
and confirm that system tomorrow.
As long as your basic skills are on par
Start learning first
That's how it's done
I feel it's not quite like working at an internet company
But it might be more similar to working at an AI company
Or some companies that are on the cutting edge of AI research and development
It could be more similar
Everyone is learning on the go
And doing things as they learn
But AI companies might just focus on the software aspect of it.
There’s still a huge difference between software and hardware development.
However, the initial cost of training is really high.
And it can’t be changed, right?
But the normal process of making modifications,
is actually relatively quick.
But once you invest in hardware,
it’s a done deal, ha ha.
So it’s a company that deals with physical products.
There might be a significant difference compared to a pure software company
In this regard, there can be quite a substantial difference
And any minor mistake can often lead to real issues
Frequent accidents usually happen in the small, unexpected areas
It's not about the core parameters or major problems
It's just something that was overlooked
A screw
A washer
A nut
It caused the entire System A to malfunction
and then we started to renovate it
It's a project with very high standards
It's not a scientific experiment now
Right?
You have to get it done
This task
relying solely on scientific understanding
or scientific knowledge alone is definitely not enough
It really took a lot of effort
As I just mentioned
You asked what difficulties I have
I solve a large number of problems every day
They are all engineering issues
Do you publish papers?
Not many
Why not, the key information is what matters
There isn't much time to publish so many papers
Now, it's all about presenting the results well.
Do you read papers?
There are many that can be read.
I read a lot.
Which days are the most important?
In this industry,
First, it is the world's largest fusion project.
Its resources are also comprehensive.
And there's a lot of peer review involved.
Many people are working on this specific IT research.
So, generally speaking, the materials for ITER.
Especially the design documents for ITER.
Its FDD,
Final Design Report,
These documents,
FDR, right.
And there are many DDD design documents.
All of these are well worth considering.
After all, when everyone was designing ITER,
a lot of effort was indeed invested,
and many details were carefully considered.
It also received the most funding,
making it the most expensive project.
Right, exactly.
The data for it is also relatively easy to find, right?
Because it’s publicly available, right?
So the data for Intel is
It's really worth a detailed study.
Then there are the already constructed ones, including superconducting devices.
And some high-parameter copper devices.
Their design data.
Their experimental operation data.
The design and manufacturing data of subsystems are also very valuable.
Although our materials might be different,
And our design objectives might vary,
But understanding why people made these designs is crucial.
What trade-offs did they make during the design process?
What were the discrepancies between the design and the final product after manufacturing?
And why did these discrepancies occur?
These are all crucial experiences to accumulate.
So, I think the first category of things is to study the existing constructions
related to the devices you are working on
and their documentation as well as the final experimental results.
Of course, ITER hasn't been built yet
but its documentation is also very valuable.
It's all about being very specialized in specific fields.
When encountering an issue, look up resources to resolve it.
Specific problems are abundant, aren't they?
There are some articles on CFS.
There are also articles on CFS.
CF Spark is also a very valuable reference tool.
However, there aren't many articles about it.
But there are still some, though not as many.
But some of its designs
These also have considerable value for reference.
Do you find every day quite fulfilling?
Not really in Lingang.
Every day is quite fulfilling.
There are a lot of issues every day.
A lot of work to be done.
In terms of daily life, this feeling is
Relatively simpler.
That's pretty much how work and rest go.
Sure
It's pretty similar to when I was doing my PhD.
Is the turnover rate high?
Do you mean the team's turnover rate?
Yes, because they actually have to give up a lot of their life here.
Here's the thing.
People who are willing to come,
have already made up their mind to make those sacrifices.
Alright
So, in fact, this is a two-way selection process.
We've been working on this for quite some time.
If it doesn’t have the basic patience,
it definitely can’t do this job.
But the team’s turnover rate is actually not low.
Mainly it’s during our probationary period.
We are quite strict in our selection process.
As I mentioned, this organization
actually filters out those we believe have a solid foundation.
People with strong abilities
but not very extensive knowledge
can be rapidly cultivated into top talents in a specific field
but this process is certainly not a pleasant one
it will definitely be very stressful
and there will be a lot to learn
if during this adaptation period
everyone isn't highly motivated to make it happen
they might not be able to persist through the process
So they just left
Yeah
So, this actually happens quite often within the team
Those who stayed
Especially those who really put in the effort to get things done
The delivery system and its components
These people have a strong sense of achievement
The ones who truly stayed in the team
Are all very capable individuals
So, your life with me is on the 2.1 line, right?
More or less, what time do you start and finish?
I usually start work around nine in the morning.
And in the evening, it varies, but mostly around eight o'clock.
But when we have experiments, it can be a bit tougher.
It’s not always predictable.
Sometimes it could be an all-nighter.
But other times, it’s quite normal.
As a commercial company
What is your goal?
The first commercial goal for a business company in the short term
is to sell a device like the 380
and actually build a demonstration power plant
not just experimental facilities like Qilin and 170
All these are preparations to sell the 380
After all, the core of a commercial company is to commercialize it
and to develop a scalable fusion power plant
to become a supplier of such equipment
Sure
The second step
As I mentioned, the device like the 380 model
its cost is still higher than that of thermal power
Once this device is up and running
we need to think about how to reduce the cost to our target
which is an order of magnitude lower than that of rockets
Right, what design optimizations are you making
and what raw material cost reductions are you aiming for
Which tools and equipment can reduce costs
And then, after scaling up production
Your costs can decrease by an order of magnitude
Do you have more goals
Less is also less
Speaking of fusion power generation
It means achieving a cost that is an order of magnitude lower than coal power
I think this is also very important
And a very meaningful endeavor indeed
But if we look further ahead,
we talk about continuously improving the cost-effectiveness,
reducing costs,
that’s one aspect.
But looking even further ahead,
we might explore using this kind of labor-free propulsion method,
which we think is a very interesting direction,
but its complexity actually surpasses that of power generation,
Ha ha, right.
So, it's about doing something truly meaningful
like commercial interplanetary space travel
We believe there's a real opportunity for this in the future
But the prerequisite is to first figure out the fundamentals
Do you have any criteria for selecting investors?
The first round should be for miHoYo and Hongshan
The future rounds should be for Holland Chi
The second round should be for speed skating and
Two internet giants
Right, right, right.
Support for the overtime work in two internet companies.
Um
Actually, I don’t think we have much luxury in choosing investors.
Yes, those who are willing to support this project.
There aren’t many investors to begin with.
Of course, if there are options available.
Like during the first round, for instance.
We did have quite a few investors willing to support us.
In this range, then
we definitely opt for more patient capital
willing to
not overly focus on short-term gains
such capital allows us a longer research and development cycle
like miHoYo
looking to the future
Sequoia and BlueLake
these are all funds with a good level of patience
This was something we cared about quite a bit in the early stages.
Now,
At this point,
the scale of funding we need is also quite substantial.
Right?
For instance, if we split it into two rounds,
this round would be around 1 to 1.5 billion RMB.
That’s the funding requirement we’re looking at.
There aren’t many who can provide such a large scale of funding.
So we are still actively seeking such funding.
The lead investor, right.
I haven’t had the chance to yet.
It’s a luxury to be able to choose investors.
This is a long-term endeavor.
It truly requires a lot of patience.
Indeed, whether from an external perspective,
the patience of investors,
or from our team’s internal perspective, to undertake such a long-term project.
And it's all about overcoming challenges along the way
It also tests one's patience
Your skills need constant accumulation
Constant updates
Continuous learning
There's no way to wrap it up in a short time
You just have to keep pushing forward
No
You always need to keep improving
I think it's comprehensive.
People, technology, and funding all require a lot of patience.
We hit a snag once.
It felt insurmountable.
It hasn't happened yet.
If you look back,
Actually, you realize everyone was quite bold.
Initially, the four of us knew nothing.
Because we hadn't done it before.
I've never seen anything like it
But back then, I thought it should be like the Qilin device
It could be done in two years
With a bit of effort, we could build it
Of course, at the beginning, there were a lot of things we didn't understand
We learned as we went
But looking back now
I'm amazed we actually pulled it off
Yes
But at the very beginning,
you didn't think he was incapable of doing anything,
you just felt there were so many problems to solve,
it's probably similar to how we feel now when we look at 170,
or even 380,
there are just so many issues to tackle,
only after you've completed it,
do you realize,
there were so many challenges.
Looking back, I feel like I was really brave back then.
But in reality, while you're going through it,
all you see is a pile of problems.
And we believe that all these problems have solutions.
So we need to find all the solutions.
That's the process.
So at least up until now,
I haven't felt like there's anything I can't do or any logo issues.
Have there been times when you felt really pressured?
I feel like this pressure is kind of dispersed.
It's not concentrated, you know.
It's not focused over a few days.
The sense of pressure is intense.
If you're talking about short-term fluctuations, though,
the peak is definitely when we conduct experiments.
That's when the pressure is at its highest.
Because that's the culmination of years of work on the project.
A two-year project, right?
And then, will it finally light up at that moment?
What was your mood before that?
Actually, it took quite a while to adjust.
This wasn't something that happened at that moment.
You might have spent one or two months adjusting to get it right, right?
So when you couldn't get it to work,
you'd wonder why it still wouldn't work, right?
Which step was wrong?
Which device didn't meet the required conditions?
You felt like you were constantly troubleshooting,
constantly calculating,
and then, finally, it lit up, huh?
The moment it lit up,
it just lit up.
Actually, the process of 22 TeV was similar,
but during the process, before you reached the experimental results,
waiting was quite agonizing.
The pressure could be quite high at that time.
But once you got there, you got there.
Do you have team-building activities?
Hardly any,
even when we finish a project, there's none.
We basically don't have team-building activities.
Once we finish a project, we immediately move on to the next one.
Do you have meetings regularly?
Quite a lot,
each project has at least weekly meetings, yeah.
Of course, there are only a few major projects,
so on Mondays,
Tuesdays, and Wednesdays, there are many meetings.
There are few occasions where the whole team speaks, right?
This is relatively rare.
Maybe for the whole team,
we occasionally have some major goals on Mondays,
quarterly results, and other important matters that the whole team needs to address.
After we achieved the 70 milestone,
we had a team-wide conversation,
discussing what happened with the 70 milestone.
Not everyone was at the experiment site, and not everyone knew what was discussed.
Basically, we summarized the process of 70,
what went well,
what problems we encountered during the process,
and what issues we need to address next.
Including the goals for the 702 phase.
I think the main point was to emphasize that from 70 to 170 and 380,
the difficulty and the amount of work required are on a different scale.
Of course, it's an exponential growth process.
Although we achieved the 70 milestone,
a team that can only achieve 70 is very different from a team that can achieve 170.
It's a world apart, maybe less than 10% of the capability.
Yeah, so it's important to make this clear to everyone,
that we've achieved this milestone, we're done with it, and we need to move on to the next one.
And the gap to our next goal is enormous.
Why is it so large?
Let's take some ongoing projects as examples,
where the gaps lie,
and what optimizations are needed.
Basically, it's about looking back at the team from six months ago,
and how different the current team is from the one six months ago.
This feeling has been consistent over the past two years.
So, it's important for everyone to understand,
especially after a significant achievement, not to let up,
but to have a clear understanding of their current capabilities and the next steps.
First, recognize the gap,
only then can you improve.
If you think everything is fine, then you won't be able to move forward.
What do you think are your strengths and weaknesses as a CEO?
Well, it's mainly about this aspect of things.
Mostly, it feels like looking back at what happened half a year ago.
The team now is vastly different from what it was six months ago.
This feeling has been present over the past two years or so.
It's always been this way.
So everyone needs to
Especially after completing a phase of work
Can't you loosen the strings a bit?
It's still important to have a clear understanding of yourself
and the current capabilities and what truly needs to be done next
First, we need to recognize the gap.
You might have the chance to improve.
I feel like I'm doing pretty well.
Then there's no way to do it.
What do you think are your strengths and weaknesses as a CEO?
The longer version might be relatively more rational.
There will be less emotional fluctuation, I guess.
It will be a bit smaller, right?
Of course, after starting a business
Actually, emotional fluctuations have become increasingly restrained.
Back then, it was even further ahead.
He has a better temper
There really isn't much time to go into a lot of details.
So, emotionally, it can still be quite intense.
But I feel that compared to most people,
It's still about the mood.
a very stable person
Then, for those who might be more skilled
And quite frequently carry out this kind of analysis.
Let's reflect.
Are you open to advice?
I guess these might be considered good things.
And if it needs to be done,
It can be done either way
a crucial matter
Then find someone more suitable to do it
As long as you know what the standards are
Just have everyone in the team move forward and catch up.
So this might be an advantage.
To the disadvantage
I think it might also come through in the conversation
Just like you said, team building
This kind of motivation
These matters might be related to emotions.
Indeed, I still have a lot to do.
It's indeed quite rare
This part might have been a bit overlooked.
But I haven't figured out exactly what its purpose is.
So, less effort was put into it, then.
So I believe he is definitely valuable.
or it might be valuable at certain stages
But at least now, he's not my default anymore.
a thing one can do
We should think this through before taking action.
Rather than some people being better at utilizing certain aspects,
The power and value of emotions.
Do you insult people?
I'm about to swear
But, for example, a significant part of the team, of course,
Especially those in R&D often feel the pressure is immense.
But for a CEO who really knows how to lay into someone,
Or, for example, some more down-to-earth people
He might think that what I said isn't really insulting.
He just gave a stern reprimand
In daily work,
My negative feedback is for
Positive feedback far outweighs negative feedback.
You always feel like there's an issue, don't you?
If you have any, please provide your feedback.
And it provides negative emotional feedback
It's a fairly effective method.
Otherwise, people wouldn't realize that this isn't the right thing to do.
It's definitely a physiological response first and foremost.
This is quite a significant emotional impact.
Then, you'll enter a reflective mode.
What's the issue?
If from the very beginning, it doesn’t seem like there’s an issue
So, are you just letting what I say go in one ear and out the other?
What about you, pa?
Here's how I see it.
But our team also says the same thing.
I think a necessary condition for being a PV
For example, A manipulates B through PUA
Person A for their own purposes or interests
to harm Party B's interests
And package it as something that's actually good for everyone's benefit
This is called PUA
I think most of the feedback on Me should be covered.
I can't even say
It's a hundred percent about getting this done.
If the other party is also interested in getting this done,
There's no question of doing anything that would harm your interests.
I think he doesn't meet the criteria for PUA.
But if the other party hasn't
The main goal is to get this done.
His interests might align with the company's interests.
The directions are not entirely consistent.
There might be a conflict of interest.
People like that don't tend to stay in the team for long.
This is how I see it
So, it's actually a process of selection.
Including what I said, there are many people in our team who are not adapting well.
He might have just left, yeah.
for a place that can be a long-term stay
Those who become pillars of the community
Actually, everyone is quite committed to getting this done.
It's all about getting the job done.
Well, I just get things done.
In this rapidly changing world
How far do you think you can see?
Especially in the transformation of energy
I think we can only see the trend.
As you said, ten years later
It's hard to say exactly what form this will take.
But ten years later
Fusion power, at least the first demonstration plant, can be built worldwide.
I think this matter can be seen as
Will it be possible to commercialize it in another 10 years?
I think there's a good chance we can pull it off.
But what does it specifically look like?
Which matter's optimization
Compared to the demonstration power plant, this can be achieved.
Not really sure.
It can only be a milestone, a pivotal moment for summarization.
You might be able to see
For example, 10 or 20 years like that
But if you want to see a road ahead,
You might see a period of five to ten years.
Can you see how to get down that road?
Well, the road ahead might be full of forks.
That's really impressive.
You can't guess what the change is.
At that time, more information from you was needed.
in order to make a judgment on the path
What do you think are the reasons?
The starting point of energy has failed.
We don't have enough people
We couldn't get it done due to the lack of funds.
Um
Three things.
Alright
Not enough money
You might not even be able to start the next thing you want to do.
Then we'll just have to keep a low profile and wait for an opportunity.
If there's enough money
Then it's also fine if there aren't enough people
It's okay even if we don't get it done.
So, in the end, it comes down to the final delivery.
It didn't meet your design objectives.
Is there still a chance for a second round?
Not necessarily
Because the cost of everything you have is so high, it's not feasible for people.
It might be a process
Since his reaction, the matter still hasn't been resolved.
So, for example, I think the money wasn't enough and the task wasn't accomplished.
One that won't start
An undeliverable one
These two things didn't work out.
For example, 170
Well, you definitely won't be able to sell it for 380, right?
So if you can sell it for 380
It didn't turn out the same
I think the core of our approach aligns with the central business logic.
It was said sooner or later.
His PMF is straightforward.
The demand is a genuine one.
Its product is a well-defined one.
As long as you can create this product
The demand will certainly be met.
So, the question is whether we can actually develop this product.
The question of whether we can actually produce the product
Do you have the resources to make this happen?
And with this resource
Can you really deliver it just as you designed it?
something with a sufficiently low cost
As long as you can make it happen
The cost of electricity is lower than that of coal power.
You can definitely make it happen.
So his question was transformed into a very specific one.
How can you vividly describe this startup?
Do you want to walk the tightrope?
He doesn't seem to be either.
Because I think your daily life is also very peaceful.
Then, and content with a corner of the world
This is a bit like what I was discussing with Kirin and the whole team.
He is a consistent mountain climber.
And the height of this mountain grows exponentially.
It's just that you might start from scratch at every step.
We might only be able to take a small step at a time.
By the end, you might be able to take a step as long as a meter.
You might have more advanced equipment
It might be possible to take a step of ten meters in the future.
However, the height of its mountains grows exponentially.
And you've been climbing the mountain all along.
It didn't work out that way.
So you fell down, right?
Then it rolled down.
It requires a lot of patience with him.
It also requires being very careful.
And does this mountain have a peak height at any point?
I haven't seen it yet, at least not now.
Every step you've climbed is a testament to your accumulation.
But what you might be doing in the future is tackling increasingly higher challenges.
And its growth rate is accelerating.
Is it now harder to achieve controllable and aggregable surfaces compared to AJI?
I don't have a deep understanding of AJI.
Actually, I'm not really sure what AGI means either.
What exactly defines the level of achievement for AGI?
This standard isn't very clear, is it?
But at least fusion is, in my view,
There is a clear path to commercialization.
If every item can meet those specifications
It can definitely make it happen.
And can these parameters be achieved?
We believe that as long as there's enough time and money
He's sure to make it.
This
He is an engineer who believes a solution always exists for any problem.
Right, that's our basic assessment.
From the perspective of fusion,
I think when you have a clear path to follow,
For instance, when talking about the Shidian Power Station
It's a gradual process of climbing the mountain.
The mountains just keep getting higher.
It's not that there's no way to get through
Or there's something you seem to have discovered that might not actually be a mountain.
There's also a pit in the middle.
No, that's not the case.
It's really tough to climb.
But he will definitely be able to climb up.
You are a food processing contractor.
You'll definitely make it up there.
And don't give up
AI is all the rage these days
Do you want to switch tracks?
No, not really.
At least, I feel that it's only in this industry
It's just like doing research
Actually, many things aren't something you can calculate.
It's your feeling
When I was a PhD student
My advisor often says you do research
You have good taste.
If you don't have that feeling
You're not in this profession.
Most of what you think about is superficial.
I just have that feeling
Which way should we go?
So he might be, at least from my current perspective,
It's not that I prefer films over series
It's not exactly my forte.
And for me, it might carry even greater significance.
Your partner said you have a good taste in physics.
So you're the CEO, huh?
Hmm, it's possible.
After all, at this stage, you're still, as I mentioned,
Your process of climbing the mountain
You're actually what's called a climber
So, you should get this done, right?
A significant part of your daily work involves making many judgments.
A lot of the information is not sufficiently comprehensive.
some judgments in the situation
Then you just have to make your best guess
You still need to figure it out.
And he has expertise in many fields.
Well, you can't possibly be an expert in everything.
Then you'll have to rely on some physical intuition combined with logical reasoning
Then let's come up with a solution.
If you fall while climbing this mountain
What would you think?
That's really a pity.
But let's see if there's a chance to keep moving up.
Just see where you fell.
Then continue climbing up
Just practice more.
I can't see any reason not to climb up.
If you can't climb up, it means you're not skilled enough.
Can you not be so inexperienced?
Or, if the dish isn't good, just keep practicing.
It's about climbing up on your own
That's the logic I follow, right?
I'll ask you a few quick questions.
Your favorite food from around the globe
All kinds of meat are quite delicious.
a place you like the most without a strong preference
I'm not really bothered about this matter.
Something few people know
But it's crucial to understand the key points.
I think there's a crucial concept
Indeed, the concept of 'shang'
It's actually connected behind the scenes.
It's about understanding the most likely events from a statistical perspective
It's a very basic one
A very fundamental concept
It's crucial for you when making decisions based on probabilities.
It's been really helpful.
It's a very simplified measure.
Then condense these complex probability issues into the mix.
Based on all the books read
I'd like to recommend two books
I remember there was a book I really liked called The Fatal Conceit.
It's a lethal character
This should be a book by Hayek
I'm going to talk about a matter concerning the transformation of some social institutions.
Right, it's capitalism and uh
Well, at the time, what was the reason for centralized management?
This book is quite interesting
The second one is also the one I've been reading recently, the Comprehensive Mirror to Aid in Government.
I'm reading the annotated version of the Comprehensive Mirror to Aid in Government.
It's also quite thick.
It's written in great detail
Indeed, this is also an old scholar's common saying.
Most things, in fact, have happened before in history.
We've all been through it.
and be able to understand in considerable detail
Let's look at how this situation unfolded and think about it.
Why did these people make such decisions at that time?
Or these people might think this way
make such value judgments
The uprising might succeed.
Why did he fail?
When the matter is significant enough
There are some fundamental reasons for that.
So I find it quite interesting.
Talk about a promising venture opportunity you've identified recently.
This issue
When doing this
I'm not following anything else.
Right, got it.
Most of what we see
Actually, this field has already become quite hot.
It's quite hot, you know.
like quantum information or AI
I find this kind of thing very interesting.
It's not as hot now.
But it's because I've been following this issue all along.
How often do you come into town?
It’s about once a month that we can get into this frequency.
Based on your imagination of the future world
What's the most crucial BT you're facing right now?
Let's go with this route.
Commercializing fusion is definitely achievable.
Within 10 years, this might be the most we've thought about it.
And that's why we chose this.
including the chosen technical approach
Including the way things are done
Hmm, Iron Man
The energy source in his chest is capable of fusion, isn't it?
What route is he taking?
His is the sci-fi route.
There's no such route
It just had me talking to the sun
And I said
I didn't like the way
He managed to get things done even while sleeping on the job
Loops
Raindrops are tapping on my head
They keep falling
Alright
That's all for this episode.
If you enjoy my show
Welcome to the Little Universe Apple Podcast
Tencent News
Subscribe to the Himalaya QQ Music channel for Zhang Xiaojun's business interview series
If you have other guests you'd like to invite or topics you'd like to hear about
Or if you have any topics you'd like to discuss
We welcome all listeners to leave your comments in the comment section.
See you in the next episode.
Bye
Raindrops keep falling on my head
But that doesn't mean
My eyes are about to turn red; this isn't my cup of tea.
Because I'm never going to stop the rain by complaining
Because I'm free
There's nothing to worry about for me